<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Push | The Communication Protocol of Web3 Blog</title>
        <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog</link>
        <description>Push | The Communication Protocol of Web3 Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is Push Chain Another L1?]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/another-l1</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/another-l1</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Learn why Push Chain is built different]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Is Push Chain Another L1?" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-f4b365f77610bf81ff34771f6320c687.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-curious">The Curious<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/another-l1#the-curious" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Curious" title="Direct link to The Curious">​</a></h3>
<p>At crypto conferences I'm often asked how our approach at Push differs from other L1 projects. And at normie gatherings I'm asked which crypto is best for starters. Until now I used to think of these as two distinct questions coming from two distinct audiences, i.e. technical and non-technical. My responses were conditioned by this assumption. At the former I used to talk about our '<a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">shared state</a>' approach and how it is distinguishable from interoperability (more on that below and in subsequent articles). And to the normies I used to suggest that starting-points can be subjective because different projects are trying to do different things. Some for instance are building reliable forms of decentralised cash, while others are trying to democratise the financial system. Still others are trying to get social media out of the hands of big tech, and a lot of them are just having fun.</p>
<p>The problem with my approach was that it left out the real audience: the 'web3 curious'. This is a huge category which cannot be ignored, and I'm going to define it rather broadly as those people who have heard of crypto and played around with it a bit <a href="https://push.org/blog/why-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">without digging deeper</a>. You could say the real reason why they got into the whole thing was quick money. But in order for that to happen I feel they must <em>at some level believe</em> in the larger crypto project. To put it differently, <em>even if</em> they thought they were playing around with 'magic internet money', some part of them must have known that the magic was real (or had the potential of <em>becoming</em> real). That's the part of the collective psyche we need to reach.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ecosystem-abstraction">Ecosystem Abstraction<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/another-l1#ecosystem-abstraction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ecosystem Abstraction" title="Direct link to Ecosystem Abstraction">​</a></h3>
<p>To return to the earlier point, I now feel that both audiences were asking me the same thing in different ways, i.e. <em>which ecosystem?</em> It's often said that a few years in crypto equals decades in the real world. To me this was never a throwaway sentiment but a profound ground-truth about our industry. When crypto was just starting out people used to debate whether it had 'inherent value' and whether it could ever become 'money'. Those questions have more or less disappeared today because most people have concluded that it does. Thanks to the SEC, the critical regulatory question today seems to be whether a particular crypto is a <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/digital-assets/2023/08/14/how-the-secs-charge-that-cryptos-are-securities-could-face-an-uphill-battle/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">security</a> or not. But of course it took humanity more than a thousand years to get from money to finance.</p>
<p>The lesson we can draw from this is that the forms of '<a href="https://medium.com/@adamnite/a-history-of-crypto-tribalism-11f9f9c5cbaf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">crypto tribalism</a>' we see today are comparable to <a href="https://www.wideopenspaces.com/native-american-totem-animals-origins-totem-poles-meaning/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">historical tribes</a> who hitched their identity to particular totems and money-objects. We took a giant leap when we adopted the human-first-tribe-later perspective. This allowed us to <em>abstract away particular ecosystems</em> and develop a more global outlook. Of course I am not suggesting that our particular cultural attributes disappeared with modernity, but rather that they were preserved within a more <a href="https://www.notion.so/Is-Push-Chain-another-L1-188188aea7f4801a8e5dc22d0c20e0f3?pvs=21" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">'universal' wrapper</a>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="cities--bridges">Cities &amp; Bridges<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/another-l1#cities--bridges" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Cities &amp; Bridges" title="Direct link to Cities &amp; Bridges">​</a></h3>
<p>Simply put, ‘ecosystem abstraction’ is my general response to both questions posed above. I see it as <a href="https://thenetworkstate.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">an ongoing process</a> that Push aims to accelerate -- comparable perhaps to globalisation which aims to overcome national boundaries -- rather than as a quantifiable end state. What this means in concrete terms is that we are building a non-competitive L1 that does not distinguish between normies and crypto-natives.</p>
<p>Why, you wonder? Because it’s the <a href="https://push.org/blog/what-is-consumer-crypto-and-why-does-it-matter/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">final ecosystem barrier</a> standing between us and mass adoption. Moreover, it allows us to approach technical problems with a fresh perspective. Consider interoperability. By and large it means two things in crypto: unifying different chains via bridges and developing common standards. The first is a necessary, but more importantly, <em>organic</em> approach because bridges between two parts of a city aren't built unless there is significant traffic between them. The trouble right now is that the two sides are run by different municipal authorities, and every time you have to cross between them you must take fresh authorisation from an agent who operates a toll booth.</p>
<p>Now if this were a real city the citizens would petition the Mayor and get things changed. They would most likely ask for a monthly ticket and some sort of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FASTag" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">‘fast tag’</a> on their cars which could automatically calculate and deduct the toll-fees from their wallets. But crypto is decentralised and there is no Mayor to petition. So for us the only solution is to get both municipal authorities to agree on a system for quick and trustworthy communication. Moreover, if both sides have different ticketing systems then they would need to develop a common ticketing standard which is mutually recognised.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="necessity-led-invention">Necessity-led invention<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/another-l1#necessity-led-invention" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Necessity-led invention" title="Direct link to Necessity-led invention">​</a></h3>
<p>In crypto, the reason why interoperability is an especially difficult problem to crack is because it requires unbroken coordination and synchronicity between different ecosystems. With every new chain that is added to the mix, the patchwork expands and becomes more unwieldy. It is therefore legitimate for people to wonder whether we are ‘another L1’ which is ultimately going to increase this messiness.</p>
<p>The short answer is no: Push is not building its own separate municipality in its own corner of the city. Instead we are building systems (such as <a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">solver networks and fees quotas</a>) through which bridge-operators can communicate and coordinate. Imagine if a <a href="https://www.notion.so/189188aea7f480faaba5f80052406759?pvs=21" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tourist</a> was visiting the city and wanted to pass through three different bridges in a single drive. The bridge-operators would need to reach consensus on various things including: (a) does he have enough money for all the tolls? (2) is he a legitimate (non-malicious) actor, and (c) has he received necessary permissions from the respective Mayors of the source and destination cities, etc.</p>
<p>In the context of crypto these steps are reducible to verifiable cross-chain communications, and because Push has been working on this problem from its origin, it is uniquely positioned to create such a system. In other words, the move towards Push Chain was driven by the realisation that we had to do our bit to move the needle on interoperability, not in order to create our own fragmented ecosystem.</p>
<p>Personally, what is most exciting for me is thinking about the new use-cases that such a cross-chain-communication-grid unlocks. Imagine if an <em>Aurory</em> or <em>Star Atlas</em> player is able to leverage Uniswap or Polymarket through in-game intent solvers, or if an artist is able to launch NFTs of their work simultanously across Opensea, Magic Eden and Jpg.store. Here's how my friend and colleague Zee put it in a recent conversation: "we're trying to build systems where people can use their favourite apps on their favourite chains without friction or second thought."</p>
<p>Yes it's an ambitious road, but we're determined.</p>
<p>LFPush!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push</category>
            <category>Chain</category>
            <category>Insights</category>
            <category>Vision</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Fuse]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Fuse]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Fuse " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-fe8d0c46f15ac254417825ae02e736ef.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Wondering how businesses can unlock Universal On-chain experiences?</p>
<p>Look no further!
Push Chain is joining forces with the Fuse Network to transform the way enterprises and users transact, operate, and flourish in the ever-expanding web3 economy.</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for Fuse and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-fuse-network">What is Fuse Network?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#what-is-fuse-network" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Fuse Network?" title="Direct link to What is Fuse Network?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://www.fuse.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fuse</a> is an Ethereum compatible public blockchain built for businesses and developers to access  web3 tech and secure, verifiable global payments.</p>
<p>Focusing on UX, ease of operation, accessibility and scalability, Fuse is built to onboard all types of enterprise users, from Web2 companies that want to integrate blockchain functionality into their apps, to Web3-native projects.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-fuse-to-push-chain">Bringing Fuse to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#bringing-fuse-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Fuse to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Fuse to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-fuse-and-push-chain-users">👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Fuse and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#what-does-this-mean-for-fuse-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Fuse and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Fuse and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Borderless On-chain Business Txns</strong></p>
<p>Enabling on-chain transactions, whether monetary or non-monetary - between businesses from entirely different blockchain ecosystems is a complex process, burdened by communication overhead, intricate bridging, and settlement challenges.</p>
<p>Push Chain abstracts this burden away by unifying the settlements of any EVM and non-evm chains - providing Fuse users a super smooth and quick any-chain transaction experience without leaving the Fuse ethos.</p>
<p><strong>Unified Invoicing and Accounting</strong></p>
<p>Enterprise apps on Fuse Chain can leverage Push Chain’s universal identity solution, Push ID, to track and monitor spending and invoicing across addresses in a unified manner by linking them to Push ID.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build Universally Abstracted Enterprise Apps</strong></p>
<p>With shared settlement capabilities of Push Chain  - devs can build enterprise apps with powerful chain, fee and wallet abstraction capabilities - allowing transactions from any chain with near instant finality.</p>
<p><strong>Attract Universal Users</strong></p>
<p>Fuse apps deployed on Push Chain can seamlessly open their doors to users from other EVM, and non-EVM chains and foster true shared experiences with Push Chain’s key innovations like - Shared State and Universal Smart Contracts.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="usecase-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Usecase unlock<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#usecase-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase unlock" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase unlock">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Universal Growth Tools</strong></p>
<p>Tools like <a href="https://midle.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Midle</a> can leverage Push Chain to create comprehensive growth campaigns combining both on-chain and off-chain tasks, verifiable and accessible from any blockchain. Users can participate using their preferred wallets, complete tasks on any chain, and receive instant rewards on their chosen network.</p>
<p><strong>Universal B2B / B2C Threat Monitoring Services</strong></p>
<p>Security monitoring solutions like <a href="https://www.ironblocks.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ironblocks</a> and utilize Push Chain for powering a universal security monitoring system that protects assets and transactions across all blockchain ecosystems simultaneously. For instance, if a security threat is detected for a cross-chain wallet on one chain, the system could instantly broadcast alerts and implement protective measures across all connected chains creating a unified security perimeter where threats are identified, tracked, and mitigated instantly.</p>
<p><strong>Universal AI Trading Agents</strong></p>
<p>AI agents can analyse and execute trades across both Fuse and other chains unifying liquidity for optimal arbitrage, yield and trading strategies.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3">🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?" title="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a>&nbsp;to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join&nbsp;<a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Stacks]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Stacks]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Morph " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-65d767c53bcbf237c02cded3be4d8976.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain is building with Stacks to unlock accessibility to Bitcoin apps from any chain, any app, and any wallet.</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for Stacks and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-stacks">What is Stacks?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#what-is-stacks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Stacks?" title="Direct link to What is Stacks?">​</a></h2>
<p>Built on top of Bitcoin, Stacks is a Layer 2 blockchain that brings general-purpose programmability to Bitcoin, enabling developers to create censorship-resistant apps while leveraging Bitcoin as a foundational settlement layer.</p>
<p>With its native language - ‘Clarity’ Stacks brings smart contracts to Bitcoin without altering its core, ensuring txns remain as secure &amp; irreversible as on BTC.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-stacks-to-push-chain">Bringing Stacks to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#bringing-stacks-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Stacks to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Stacks to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="-what-does-this-mean-for-stacks-and-push-chain-users">👥 What does this mean for Stacks and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#-what-does-this-mean-for-stacks-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥 What does this mean for Stacks and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥 What does this mean for Stacks and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Explore EVM and Non-EVM ecosystems without leaving Bitcoin</strong></p>
<p>With Push Chain, Stacks native users can explore and access applications across any blockchain ecosystem without learning new complex wallet systems, all while maintaining their Bitcoin-native experience on Stacks.</p>
<p><strong>Tap into the Trillion Dollar Bitcoin economy</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain's integration with Stacks opens up Bitcoin's massive liquidity and market presence for users from any blockchain ecosystem. Users can now participate in Bitcoin-native applications, access BTC-denominated assets, and engage with Stacks' growing ecosystem via their preferred blockchain and wallet.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Build Universal Bitcoin native Apps</strong></p>
<p>Apps deployed on Stacks and Push Chain can accept transactions from users belonging from any wallet belonging to any chain!</p>
<p><strong>Build&nbsp;<em>Superfast</em>&nbsp;Unified Apps</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain’s flexible architecture and its ability to allow transactions from any chain with sub-zero finality opens up a plethora of possibilities to build - Consumer, Financial, and Mixed Financial Applications.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="usecase-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#usecase-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Universal NFT Marketplaces</strong></p>
<p>NFT Marketplaces like <a href="https://gamma.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gamma</a> can open their gates for EVM and other Non-EVM NFT patrons enabling instant access, trade, and settlement!</p>
<p><strong>Borderless On-chain gaming</strong></p>
<p>Access Stacks’s rich gaming ecosystem including <a href="https://forceprime.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ForcePrime</a> and <a href="https://www.skullco.in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Skullco</a> via any EVM/Non-EVM chains - using Push’s Shared Settlement and Consumer Txns!</p>
<p><strong>Shared State DEX:</strong></p>
<p>DEXs like&nbsp;<a href="https://app.alexlab.co/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ALEX</a> can leverage Push Chain to provide access to Stacks and Bitcoin’s liquidity from users from any chain via their preferred wallets.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3">🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?" title="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a>&nbsp;to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>*&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join&nbsp;<a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Morph]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Morph]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Morph " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-187da463e3ccd5f98628e886b390a7cd.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain is about to facelift the consumer app experience by teaming up with Morph L2!</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for Morph and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-morph">What is Morph?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#what-is-morph" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Morph?" title="Direct link to What is Morph?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://www.morphl2.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Morph</a> is a consumer app focused Ethereum Layer 2 solution that combines the best of Optimistic and ZK Rollups to provide a secure and super fast consumer experience.</p>
<p>With over 5M txns to date, Morph is rallying towards becoming the global consumer layer for empowering everyday on-chain usage for every internet user.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push">What is Push?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#what-is-push" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push?" title="Direct link to What is Push?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain
built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-morph-to-push-chain">Bringing Morph to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#bringing-morph-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Morph to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Morph to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-morph-and-push-chain-users">👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Morph and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#what-does-this-mean-for-morph-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Morph and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Morph and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Borderless consumer App experience</strong></p>
<p>Morph users can expand their on-chain usage beyond EVMs into Solana and other nonEVMs without ever leaving Morph’s ecosystem and UX comfort.</p>
<p><strong>Bring web2 normies to consumer crypto</strong></p>
<p>With Push Chain’s wallet and fee abstraction - everyday internet users (web2 users) can easily experience Morph’s consumer crypto ecosystem with minimal UX overhead - simply by using their social accounts like Google, Apple, Github, X and Discord.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build hyper scalable universal consumer apps</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain empowers developers to build truly universal applications that work seamlessly across all blockchains.</p>
<p>Push unlocks hyper-scalability for consumer and mixed consumer apps that have potential of handling millions of daily users with its innovative '<strong>Consumer Transactions</strong>' feature, enabling stateless and unordered processing of non-value transfers like social interactions, content sharing, and game actions.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Read from any chain using shared settlement</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain's shared settlement layer provides a powerful foundation for apps on Morph to unlock shaped universal experiences with its ability to read state across any blockchain through its shared settlement layer. This means developers can focus on building engaging user experiences instead of managing complex cross-chain interactions.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="usecase-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#usecase-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Universal ZK AI agents</strong></p>
<p>Privacy centric agentic networks like <a href="https://zypher.network/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Zypher</a> can leverage Push Chain to expand its AI agents reach to any blockchain. Ensuring a Universal, secure and verifiable execution without exposing sensitive data.</p>
<p><strong>Universal Predication Markets</strong></p>
<p>Prediction markets like <a href="https://soccersm.ai/ai-predictions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Soccersm</a> can not only house users from Morph but also from any other chains to collectively speculate on real-life events. Markets can aggregate liquidity from all chains simultaneously bringing more user traction and better yield opportunities.</p>
<p><strong>Universally Accessible token launchpads</strong> - Like <a href="https://muffun.fun/board" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Muffun</a> on Morph, can utilize the Push Chain and Push Wallet to enable users from any chain (EVM or non EVM) to effortlessly launch tokens on Morph without leaving their existing wallet systems or manually bridge funds.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow <a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a> to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a> for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join <a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
            <category>Shared App Experience</category>
            <category>Any Chain Tx</category>
            <category>Universal Smart Contracts</category>
            <category>Shared State Blockchain</category>
            <category>Consumer Tx</category>
            <category>Parallel Validators</category>
            <category>Dynamic Sharding</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With zkPass]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain joins forces with zkPass!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain joins forces with zkPass " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-7d413c2d4f1b806201039c5cee8339b7.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push chain is pumped to join forces with zkPass to transform user privacy in the new internet world.</p>
<p>Discover how this collaboration empowers developers and users, unlocks groundbreaking use cases, and drives the web3 ecosystem forward.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-zkpass">What is zkPass?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass#what-is-zkpass" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is zkPass?" title="Direct link to What is zkPass?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://zkpass.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">zkPass</a> is a privacy-first zkTLS oracle protocol that enables private internet data to be verifiable on-chain without revealing the actual information, using zero-knowledge proofs and innovative TLS architecture to ensure data verifiability, privacy and composability.</p>
<p>With over 4 million ZK Proofs generated, zkPass provides tools and applications for secure, verifiable data sharing with privacy and integrity assurances from any HTTPS website without requiring OAuth APIs.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain
built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="-how-does-this-benefit-zkpass-and-push-chain-users">👥 How does this benefit zkPass and Push Chain users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass#-how-does-this-benefit-zkpass-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥 How does this benefit zkPass and Push Chain users?" title="Direct link to 👥 How does this benefit zkPass and Push Chain users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Verify your private data on any app and any chain.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain extends zkPass’s proving capabilities by enabling verification support for any EVM as well as non-EVM chains like Solana, Aptos etc.</p>
<p><strong>Universal private identity</strong></p>
<p>Users can now create a truly private and unified blockchain presence through Push ID - a universal identity system that seamlessly connects all their wallets (EVM and non-EVM) into one profile.</p>
<p>This unified identity gains enhanced privacy through zkPass, enabling <strong>users to prove wallet ownership, assets or any other private information across any blockchain</strong> without revealing their actual wallet details and enabling selective disclosure of wallets while linking to any application. <strong>One private KYC that can be instantly validated on all apps and all chains.</strong></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️how-does-it-benefit-builders">👷‍♂️How does it benefit builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass#%EF%B8%8Fhow-does-it-benefit-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️How does it benefit builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️How does it benefit builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build Universally accessible privacy-centric DApps</strong>
Push Chain enables developers to build applications that work across any blockchain, while zkPass adds powerful privacy-preservation capabilities to this universal reach. Developers can use the <a href="https://github.com/push-protocol/push-chain-sdk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain</a> and <a href="https://zkpass.gitbook.io/zkpass/developer-guides/extension-js-sdk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Transgate</a> SDKs to create apps that verify user credentials, assets, or achievements across chains without managing complex privacy infrastructure or dealing with multiple chain-specific identity systems.</p>
<p><strong>Build privately - verifiable DeFi Protocols</strong></p>
<p>Build more sophisticated DeFi applications that can access verified user credentials while respecting privacy.</p>
<p>Through Push Chain's shared state and zkPass's verification system, protocols can validate credit scores, collateral, and transaction history across chains without exposing sensitive user data enabling better risk assessment and more efficient capital allocation while maintaining user privacy.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-usecases-does-the-collab-unlock">🔓&nbsp;What usecases does the collab unlock?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass#what-usecases-does-the-collab-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;What usecases does the collab unlock?" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;What usecases does the collab unlock?">​</a></h2>
<p>In addition to the unified KYC and universal privacy-focused DeFi applications discussed above, the collaboration between Push Chain and zkPass unlocks the following use cases:</p>
<p><strong>Universal Private RWA Hub</strong>
RWA marketplaces like <a href="https://canza.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kanza Finance</a> can leverage Push Chain and zkPass to enable instant cross-chain RWA operations with built-in compliance verification, all while keeping sensitive user data private and secure.</p>
<p><strong>Unified AI marketplaces</strong></p>
<p>AI &amp; Privacy centric chains like <a href="https://www.polyhedra.network/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Polyhedra EXP</a> can host AI data marketplaces for using zkPass, users can privately contribute data to AI models while: Proving data authenticity without exposure and receiving rewards tied to any chain.</p>
<p>Users can optimise their on-chain data collection process by using Push Chain’s unified shared settlement layer.</p>
<p><strong>Universal launchpads.</strong></p>
<p>Cross chain launchpads like <a href="https://www.poolz.finance/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pools Finance</a> can leverage Push Chain and zkPass to power - universal DApp launchpads where Developers can utilize Push Chain’s Universal Shared State and Parallel txn processing to deploy dApps once and instantly reach users across all or any specified networks while maintaining privacy preservation, credential verification and compliance through zkPass.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3"><strong>🌌</strong>&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-web3" title="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-web3">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zkpass#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow <a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain</a> on X to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join <a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
            <category>Shared App Experience</category>
            <category>Any Chain Tx</category>
            <category>Universal Smart Contracts</category>
            <category>Shared State Blockchain</category>
            <category>Consumer Tx</category>
            <category>Parallel Validators</category>
            <category>Dynamic Sharding</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Plume]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain joins forces with Plume!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain joins forces with Plume " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-a78d6f48168867bb2bf3ec63f7541a92.webp" width="1920" height="1080" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain is set to revolutionize RWAfi by joining forces with Plume!</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for Plume and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-plume">What is Plume?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume#what-is-plume" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Plume?" title="Direct link to What is Plume?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://plumenetwork.xyz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Plume</a> is a purpose-built layer 1 blockchain for tokenized Real World Assets (RWAs).</p>
<p>With an ecosystem of over 180 apps and over 3.75 Million users in its early testnet Plume brings RWAs into the on-chain digital economy.</p>
<p>With built-in AML compliance and a modular full stack architecture, Plume provides a super flexible platform for trading, financing, collateralizng RWAs for enhanced yield and market-making opportunities!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain
built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-plume-to-push-chain">Bringing Plume to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume#bringing-plume-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Plume to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Plume to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="-what-does-this-mean-for-plume-and-push-chain-users">👥 What does this mean for Plume and Push Chain users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume#-what-does-this-mean-for-plume-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥 What does this mean for Plume and Push Chain users?" title="Direct link to 👥 What does this mean for Plume and Push Chain users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Borderless access for maximising yield opportunities</strong></p>
<p>Plume native users can access RWAfi instruments on any other EVM and non-EVM chains without leaving the operational comfort offered by Plume.</p>
<p>Via Push Chain’s shared settlement layer - Plume ecosystem users can easily lend, borrow and sell RWAs listed on Plume to any user belonging to any chain.
For instance - A Plume native user can trade their tokenized assets with a Solana native user.</p>
<p><strong>Easily onboard web2 normies</strong></p>
<p>With Push Chain’s wallet and fee abstraction - everyday internet users (web2 users) can be onboarded to the Plume ecosystem with minimal UX overhead - simply by using their social accounts like Google, Apple, Github, X and Discord.</p>
<p><strong>Unified Experience</strong></p>
<p>As a universal settlement layer - Push Chain users belong to multiple L1, L2s and L3s - be it EVM or nonEVMs like Aptos and Solana.</p>
<p>With Push Chain - users from these wide varieties of chains can explore the rich Plume Ecosystem and send transactions to any Plume Apps without navigating multiple networks or managing multiple wallets - with zero or minimal learning curve.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️-what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️ What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume#%EF%B8%8F-what-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️ What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️ What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build universal RWAfi apps</strong></p>
<p>RWA-compliant apps deployed on Push Chain and Plume can be accessed and used by users belonging to any chain, eliminating chain fragmentation and complex bridging overhead while opening doors to users across all ecosystems.</p>
<p><strong>Build super scalable and super fast apps</strong></p>
<p>In addition to Push Chain’s transact from any chain capabilities - Push Chain provides super fast settlement with sub-second finality and theoretically, can be scaled infinitely due to its true scaling engine - that increases the write throughput (or TPS) linearly as the number of nodes grow - achieving <strong>True scale.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="-usecase-unlock">🔓 Usecase Unlock:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume#-usecase-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓 Usecase Unlock:" title="Direct link to 🔓 Usecase Unlock:">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unified RWA Vaults</strong></p>
<p>With Push Chain, RWA Staking aggregators like <a href="https://nest.credit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nest</a> can provide aggregated yield vaults across all blockchain ecosystems. With chain abstraction and Universal Smart Contracts, non-native Plume users can stake in preferred stable coins which can then be settled for platform-specific stables.</p>
<p><strong>Universal Prediction Markets</strong></p>
<p>Markets like <a href="https://cultured.finance/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cultured</a> can leverage Push Chain to create unified betting markets accessible from any chain, enable cross-chain market making and liquidity, and attract more users while offering better yield opportunities.</p>
<p><strong>Unified data source</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://docs.plumenetwork.xyz/plume/nexus-data-highway/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nexus</a> (Plume's data highway) can leverage Push Chain to distribute RWA data across all chains, enable universal price discovery and power cross-chain prediction markets</p>
<p><strong>Shared Lending RWAs</strong></p>
<p>RWA Apps on Plume like <a href="https://osprey.market/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Osprey</a> and <a href="https://metastreet.xyz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MetaStreet</a> can leverage Push Chain to provide a unified shared state borrow/lending management encompassing all chains - enabling users from any chain to lend and borrow tokenized assets with ease.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3"><strong>🌌</strong>&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-web3" title="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-web3">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<p><em>Get ready! RWAfi is set to be accessible to any user from any app on any chain with Push Chain and Plume.</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-plume#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow <a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain</a> on X to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join <a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
            <category>Shared App Experience</category>
            <category>Any Chain Tx</category>
            <category>Universal Smart Contracts</category>
            <category>Shared State Blockchain</category>
            <category>Consumer Tx</category>
            <category>Parallel Validators</category>
            <category>Dynamic Sharding</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With zkLink]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain joins forces with zkLink!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join forces with zkLink " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-e5eec6159956af52f9eb47c96e90bcb3.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain is pumped to join forces with zkLink!</p>
<p>A significant step for propelling our mission of enabling any user from any app to interact with any chain!</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for zkLink and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-zklink">What is zkLink?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink#what-is-zklink" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is zkLink?" title="Direct link to What is zkLink?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://zk.link/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">zkLink</a> is the world’s first ZK-powered Layer 3 solution that aggregates all EVM-compatible networks.</p>
<p>zkLink includes two prudent networks:</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://zklink.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">zkLink Nova</a></strong>: A general-purpose Layer 3 rollup designed to resolve liquidity fragmentation across Ethereum Layer 2s by providing a shared aggregated settlement layer.</p>
<p>To date, zkLink Nova boasts over 26 Million Transactions with 1.3 million Unique Addresses, Aggregating over 17 networks!</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://zk.link/X" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">zkLink X</a></strong>: A highly customizable and secure application-specific rollup, optimized for trading-focused applications.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain
built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-zklink-to-push-chain">Bringing zkLink to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink#bringing-zklink-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing zkLink to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing zkLink to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-zklink-and-push-chain-users">👥&nbsp;What does this mean for zkLink and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink#what-does-this-mean-for-zklink-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for zkLink and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for zkLink and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Interact with any non-evm app, without leaving zkLink</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain extends the aggregation capabilities of zkLink enabling zkLink users to easily interact with and explore non-evm ecosystems like Solana, Aptos and Cosmos - all without leaving the operational comfort offered by zkLink.</p>
<p>No need to create new wallets, learn and follow complex bridging steps- simply utilize Push Chain to seamlessly interplay between zkLink and the non-evm ecosystem</p>
<p><strong>Unified Experience</strong></p>
<p>Since zkLink aggregates Ethereum networks and serves as a unified point of access, users from non-evm space can easily leverage Push Chain to explore and interact with EVM space- abstracting away all the manual complexities traditionally faced by non-EVM users when transacting on EVM chains.</p>
<p>All of the above with the advantage of - instant finality, security and superfast execution.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build super abstracted - shared settlement apps</strong></p>
<p>With shared settlement capabilities of Push Chain and zkLink - devs can build apps with powerful chain, fee and wallet abstraction capabilities - allowing transactions from any chain with near-instant finality.</p>
<p><strong>Build universally compliant consumer and mixed financial apps</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain introduces a new transaction type: <strong>‘consumer transactions’</strong>, where transaction ordering is not essential.</p>
<p>Why consumer tx?</p>
<p>Two major challenges hinder the scalability of consumer web3 apps:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain Fragmentation:</strong> User bases are over-diversified across hundreds of chains, impeding user growth, UX and retention.</li>
<li><strong>Scalability constraints</strong> Most chains process transactions in a strictly ordered manner, which imposes unnecessary constraints on apps that don’t rely on transaction ordering.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is where Push Chain’s Consumer Tx feature enables non-financial and consumer applications to operate with lightning-fast speed and hyper-scalability. Push Chain enables these apps to manage millions of users seamlessly across any chain environment.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="use-case-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink#use-case-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock:" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock:">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Chain Agnostic AI Agents</strong> - Push Chain’s universal shared state and ZKLink’s <a href="https://blog.zk.link/zklink-research-roadmap-ai-agents-in-application-abstraction-fff297ef4577" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">application abstraction</a> pave the way for a new generation of chain-agnostic AI agents. These agents can perform autonomous operations in a borderless manner - unlocking a wide variety of financial, mixed financial, and non-financial use cases.</p>
<p><strong>Universal Domains</strong> - Applications like <a href="https://zns.bio/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ZNS Connect</a> can utilize Push IDs- ( A unified user identity by Push Chain that spans every user wallet, both EVM and non-EVM) to expand their domain capabilities with unified analytics, user footprint tracking and universal resolution.</p>
<p><strong>Unified Liquidity Markets</strong> - EVM-bound liquidity markets like <a href="https://lido.fi/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lido</a>, <a href="https://curve.fi/#/ethereum/swap" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Curve</a>, and <a href="https://native.org/app/credit-pool/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Native</a> can utilize fee and chain abstraction features of Push Chain to seamlessly allow non-evm Liquidity Providers to effortlessly participate in market-making opportunities within a few clicks with no extra UX overhead.</p>
<p><strong>Universal Prediction Markets</strong> - Where users from zkLink and other chains can collectively speculate on real-life events. Markets can aggregate liquidity from all chains simultaneously bringing more user traction and better yield opportunities.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3"><strong>🌌</strong>&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-web3" title="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-web3">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-zklink#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow <a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain</a> on X to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a> for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/?" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join <a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
            <category>Shared App Experience</category>
            <category>Any Chain Tx</category>
            <category>Universal Smart Contracts</category>
            <category>Shared State Blockchain</category>
            <category>Consumer Tx</category>
            <category>Parallel Validators</category>
            <category>Dynamic Sharding</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Aptos]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Aptos]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Aptos " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-ff50be818fca9abacf8a87076c592bcd.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain is pumped to join forces with Aptos!</p>
<p>This marks a giant leap in Push Chain’s march towards unifying web3 and enabling a shared universal app experience.</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for Aptos and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-aptos">What is Aptos?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#what-is-aptos" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Aptos?" title="Direct link to What is Aptos?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://aptosfoundation.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Aptos</a> is a Layer 1 non-EVM blockchain renowned for its ultra-fast execution, parallel transaction processing, incredibly low gas fees, and serving as the foundation for some of the most popular consumer and financial applications.</p>
<p>With over 38.8 Million active addresses - Aptos is home to some of the most popular DeFi, Gaming and Consumer Apps like Stani, Merkle.trade, Cellana Fi, Chingari, Panora, Pancake Swap and many more.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain
built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-aptos-to-push-chain">Bringing Aptos to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#bringing-aptos-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Aptos to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Aptos to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-aptos-and-push-chain-users"><strong>👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Aptos and Push Chain Users?</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#what-does-this-mean-for-aptos-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-aptos-and-push-chain-users" title="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-aptos-and-push-chain-users">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Interact with any app on any other chain, without leaving Aptos.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain empowers Aptos users to seamlessly interact with DApps, services, and protocols across any chain.</p>
<p>Thus eliminating the need for complex wallet setups and bridging, delivering a shared universal experience within the Aptos ecosystem.</p>
<p>For instance, with Push Chain - An Aptos user can trade ERC tokens on Uniswap, Participate in Polygon-based DAOs, create meme coins on Solana - without needing to leave Apto’s ecosystem comfort and learn new wallet systems.</p>
<p><strong>Enable shared experiences for all EVM and non-EVM Push Chain users on Aptos.</strong></p>
<p>As a universal settlement layer - Push Chain users belong to multiple L1, L2s and L3s - be it EVM or nonEVMs like Aptos and Solana.</p>
<p>With Push Chain’s native Fee and Wallet abstraction support - users from these wide varieties of chains can explore the rich Aptos Ecosystem and send transactions to any Move-based Apps without navigating multiple networks or managing multiple wallets - with zero or minimal learning curve.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build <em>Superfast</em> Universal Apps</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain’s flexible architecture and its ability to allow transactions from any chain with sub-zero finality opens up a plethora of possibilities to build - Consumer, Financial and Mixed Financial Applications.</p>
<p><strong>Attract Universal Users.</strong></p>
<p>Aptos apps deployed on Push Chain can seamlessly open their doors to users from other EVM, and non-EVM chains and foster true shared experiences with Push Chain’s key innovations like - Shared State and Universal Smart Contracts.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="use-case-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#use-case-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock:" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock:">​</a></h2>
<p>While the possibilities of this collaboration are limitless, here’s a quick list that touches on various use cases across various web3 segments that can be practically executed on Aptos with Push Chain.</p>
<p><strong>Universal Gaming:</strong> - Multiplayer games like roulette, casinos and RPG games on Aptos can utilize Push Chain to bring users across different chains to compete together in a unified manner.</p>
<p><strong>Universal Prediction Markets:</strong> - Where users from Aptos and other chains can collectively speculate on real-life events. Markets can aggregate liquidity from all chains simultaneously bringing more user traction and better yield opportunities.</p>
<p><strong>Universal AI Trading Agents:</strong> AI agents can analyse and execute trades across both Move and EVM ecosystems, accessing liquidity from Aptos alongside other DEXs for optimal arbitrage and trading strategies.</p>
<p><strong>Shared RWAs:</strong> - RWA Apps on Aptos like <a href="https://www.propbase.app/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Propbase</a> can leverage Push Chain to provide shared state real estate tokenization and achieve unified RWA markets accessible to users from any blockchain.</p>
<p><strong>Cross Chain - Shared Liquid Staking:</strong> Liquid Staking Apps like <a href="https://amnis.finance/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Amnis Finance</a> can leverage Push Chain to provide cross-chain liquid staking and achieve unified staking positions across Aptos and other blockchain ecosystems. Users from any chain can stake their native tokens and use their liquid staking derivatives across all supported protocols.</p>
<p><strong>Shared Sate DEX:</strong> - DEXs like <a href="https://cellana.finance/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cellana Finance</a> can leverage Push Chain to provide chain-agnostic Ve(3,3) governance and achieve unified liquidity management across multiple blockchain ecosystems.</p>
<p><strong>Unified Lending &amp; Borrowing Apps:</strong> Users from any chain can lend and borrow, addressing fragmented liquidity and enabling applications that act as universal liquidity hubs—taking liquidity from one chain and providing it to another.</p>
<p><strong>Cross-Chain Identity System:</strong> - Leveraging PushID ( A unified user identity by Push Chain that spans every user wallet, both EVM and non-EVM) to build reputation systems that aggregate user activity across Aptos and other chains, creating unified web3 identities.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3">🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?" title="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<p><em>As we wrap up, the Push Notifications Protocol has some extra special news with Aptos!</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="-push-notifications-and-chat-to-support-the-aptos-ecosystem">🔔 Push Notifications and Chat to support the Aptos Ecosystem<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#-push-notifications-and-chat-to-support-the-aptos-ecosystem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔔 Push Notifications and Chat to support the Aptos Ecosystem" title="Direct link to 🔔 Push Notifications and Chat to support the Aptos Ecosystem">​</a></h2>
<p>With our quest to make Push Communications Protocol the universal layer of communication, supporting any and every chain, we’re excited to expand our reach to Aptos!</p>
<p>Aptos users can soon - be able to communicate with each other using their wallets, form group chats and gated communities on Push Chat!</p>
<p>We’re also extending our notification support to Aptos Ecosystem enabling lightning-fast notifications to Aptos users.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-aptos#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow <a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a> to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>**&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join <a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
            <category>Shared App Experience</category>
            <category>Any Chain Tx</category>
            <category>Universal Smart Contracts</category>
            <category>Shared State Blockchain</category>
            <category>Consumer Tx</category>
            <category>Parallel Validators</category>
            <category>Dynamic Sharding</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Year In Review 2024]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Year In Review 2024]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Year In Review 2024" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-d1f7d6efc8933f23345a79dabb05eefd.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><strong>2024 was a Push-tastic year for Push!</strong></p>
<p>Marked with super ambitious achievements, incredible growth and everlasting community support!</p>
<p>We crossed multiple milestones with Push Notifications Protocol and unveiled the next - most awaited phase of our evolution: <a href="https://push.org/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain - A shared state blockchain for shared app experiences</a>.</p>
<p>Special thanks to all our Push Communications Protocol users for supporting our journey and making Push the de-facto communication layer for web3!</p>
<p>Let’s take a quick look at ‘Push Rewind 2024’
<em>Don't miss the final reel (We have a major alpha reveal!)</em></p>
<!-- -->
<!-- -->
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-by-numbers">Push by Numbers<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#push-by-numbers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push by Numbers" title="Direct link to Push by Numbers">​</a></h2>
<p>We finally achieved one of our most ambitious goals of sending over <strong>100M</strong> notifications to date!!</p>
<p>As of year-end - Push has sent over <strong>138+ Million notifications to its 300k+ subscribers</strong>.</p>
<p>That’s almost <strong>3x</strong> the number of notifications sent and double the number of <a href="https://push.org/blog/push-roadmap-recap-2023/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">subscribers from last year</a> 😱.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="subscribers gained in 2024" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image1-2600a2bfab9e9abdf59298254150ee02.webp" width="1600" height="840" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The Push ecosystem has expanded to <strong>500 amazing projects</strong>, including - <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0xf198eBCc8dB86F707bAdDdBa236aB5b619c59D3c" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QuickSwap</a>, <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0xf1A1542Ca902AE861B59bffE77D92E8CD76146f1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">HyperLiquid</a>,<a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0x65bB67c2416186aE3107F7c2C6728b272a579e3d" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Revoke</a>, <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1859145460939628803" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ethOS</a> and many more.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="highlights">Highlights<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#highlights" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Highlights" title="Direct link to Highlights">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="1-push-points-program-">1. Push Points Program ✨<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#1-push-points-program-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Push Points Program ✨" title="Direct link to 1. Push Points Program ✨">​</a></h3>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="push points program" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image2-abc93e9a518d10c2741d1ed526740859.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>We kickstarted Phase 1 of <a href="https://app.push.org/points?utm_source=push_blog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=Push+Points&amp;utm_content=blog_post" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Points Program</a> - a gamified reputation system, aimed at giving back to our Push Fam, ecosystem communities and devs who have supported Push every step of the way and helped us reach greater heights.</p>
<p>Within three months of its launch, the program distributed millions of points to thousands of users for completing various activities centred around Push Communications Protocol, its ecosystem, and $PUSH staking.</p>
<a href="https://app.push.org/points" title="Push Points Program Link" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap">Push Points Program S1 concludes soon - Explore Now!</a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="2-sdk-support-for-ethers-v6-and-viem-️">2. SDK Support for Ethers V6 and Viem 🛠️<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#2-sdk-support-for-ethers-v6-and-viem-%EF%B8%8F" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. SDK Support for Ethers V6 and Viem 🛠️" title="Direct link to 2. SDK Support for Ethers V6 and Viem 🛠️">​</a></h2>
<p>The builder activity with Push Protocol SDKs continues to reach new ATHs!
To better support their journey the Push SDK underwent massive upgrades and optimisations!</p>
<p>We upgraded our Push SDK to support Ethers V6 along with Ethers V5 and viem enabling devs to use our SDK with the latest version of Ethers.</p>
<a href="https://github.com/push-protocol/push-sdk" title="Push Communications Protocol SDK " class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap">Checkout our upgraded SDK here</a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="3-introduced-cross-chain-requests-">3. Introduced Cross Chain Requests 🔗<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#3-introduced-cross-chain-requests-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Introduced Cross Chain Requests 🔗" title="Direct link to 3. Introduced Cross Chain Requests 🔗">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="cross chain requests" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image3-57bca9ea6556a16c996e32f0d3721977.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Extending a step towards seamless cross-chain communication and UX, we launched the <strong>Cross Chain Requests</strong> Feature - Where users can interact with Push Communication Protocol smart contracts on the Ethereum blockchain from any other blockchain network, whether it’s EVM or non-EVM. Which enables users to stay on their preferred blockchain while accessing Push Communication Protocol's services, offering enhanced convenience and flexibility.</p>
<a href="https://push.org/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip/" title="Cross Chain Requests " class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap">Click here to learn how we achieve cross-chain requests</a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="4-notification-and-channel-categories-️">4. Notification and Channel Categories 🗂️<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#4-notification-and-channel-categories-%EF%B8%8F" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. Notification and Channel Categories 🗂️" title="Direct link to 4. Notification and Channel Categories 🗂️">​</a></h2>
<p>Exploring over 500+ channels on Push can be a time-consuming adventure.
We launched the channel category feature so that you can better track and find the channel of your choice!</p>
<a href="https://app.push.org/channels?chain=1&amp;category=All" title="Cross Chain Requests " class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap">Explore over 500 channels and 13 channel categories today!</a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="5-added-open-frames-reaction-and-reply-to-chat-">5. Added open Frames, Reaction and Reply to Chat 💬<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#5-added-open-frames-reaction-and-reply-to-chat-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. Added open Frames, Reaction and Reply to Chat 💬" title="Direct link to 5. Added open Frames, Reaction and Reply to Chat 💬">​</a></h2>
<p>Addressing the growing adoption of Push Chat we added some extra cool features to make your on-chain wallet-to-wallet and group chatting experience more fun!</p>
<p>Starting with adding support for <strong>Farcaster frames</strong>!
With the growing adoption of <a href="https://www.farcaster.xyz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Farcaster</a>, a popular web3 social app on Base, we’ve integrated support for Farcaster Frames in Push Chat. These frames unlock unique in-chat experiences, from making payments and subscribing to notifications to playing games or building any functionality developers envision.</p>
<p>In addition to frames, we added two of the most wildly used web2 chat features - <strong>Reactions and Reply to Chat features!</strong></p>
<p>Especially helpful in group and conditionally gated group chats where a user needs to revert to a specific user's conversation.</p>
<a href="https://app.push.org/chat" title="Cross Chain Requests " class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap">Start chatting using your wallets today!</a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="6-push-web3-app-gets-better-️">6. Push WEB3 App Gets Better!! ⚡️<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#6-push-web3-app-gets-better-%EF%B8%8F" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 6. Push WEB3 App Gets Better!! ⚡️" title="Direct link to 6. Push WEB3 App Gets Better!! ⚡️">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Communications DApp, underwent some super cool upgrades to smoothen as well as fasten users' on-chain communication journey even more!
Starting with:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="user-dashboard">User dashboard:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#user-dashboard" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to User dashboard:" title="Direct link to User dashboard:">​</a></h3>
<p>We unveiled a brand-new dashboard for Push Communication Protocol users, designed to provide a quick and intuitive overview of the entire Push Communications ecosystem - all within a single page.</p>
<p><strong>Subscribed Channels:</strong> View and manage your channel subscriptions effortlessly.</p>
<p><strong>Trending Notification Channels:</strong> Discover the most popular channels right now.</p>
<p><strong>Latest Push Chat Recommendations:</strong> Stay updated with chat groups tailored to your interests.</p>
<p><strong>Analytics Overview:</strong> Get insights into Push Notifications and Staking Fee Pools at a glance.</p>
<p>The dashboard brings everything you need to explore and engage with Push Protocol, making your experience seamless and efficient! 🚀</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="guest-mode--remember-me">Guest Mode + Remember Me<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#guest-mode--remember-me" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Guest Mode + Remember Me" title="Direct link to Guest Mode + Remember Me">​</a></h3>
<p>Ensuring an all-around inclusive, smooth and Privacy-packed user onboarding has always been Push’s top priority, this is why we introduced the <strong>'Guest' mode</strong> feature on our dApp, making it easier than ever to explore Push without connecting your wallet!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Guest mode" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image4-b5596747df8aa54d70281fb91a843ff3.gif" width="800" height="800" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>With the ‘<strong>Remember Me</strong>’ feature Checking the option on our PushChat Login keeps you logged in for days, even after closing your browser.</p>
<p>No more repeated logins and wallet signings - Just a one-click access to your fav chats every time you return!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Remember me" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image5-8a5b908cbb1ff616a8577cb9a22a4117.gif" width="800" height="499" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<a href="https://app.push.org/" title="Push Communications Protocol" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Safeguard your on-chain privacy by trying out these features today!</a>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="redesigned-channel-dashboard">Redesigned Channel Dashboard:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#redesigned-channel-dashboard" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Redesigned Channel Dashboard:" title="Direct link to Redesigned Channel Dashboard:">​</a></h3>
<p>With the launch of the channel categories feature, we also revamped our Channel Dashboard - organizing over 500+ channels across 13 categories including Defi, media, DAO and many more.
Users can now filter and explore channels based on specific networks, such as <a href="https://app.push.org/channels?chain=1&amp;category=DeFi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DeFi channels on Arbitrum</a>, <a href="https://app.push.org/channels?chain=1&amp;category=Media" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Media channels on Polygon</a>, and beyond—making channel discovery more intuitive and personalized.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="7-push-expands-into-base-arbitrum-fuse-linea-and-cyber-networks-">7. Push expands into Base, Arbitrum, Fuse, Linea and Cyber Networks 💹<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#7-push-expands-into-base-arbitrum-fuse-linea-and-cyber-networks-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 7. Push expands into Base, Arbitrum, Fuse, Linea and Cyber Networks 💹" title="Direct link to 7. Push expands into Base, Arbitrum, Fuse, Linea and Cyber Networks 💹">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="moving across an open web" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image6-8cb3c06fad5597712c2e5903ee769b30.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>With our quest of making push Communications Protocol the universal layer of communication, supporting any and every chain, this year, we expanded our reach to more chains including <strong>Arbitrum, Fuse and Cyber</strong>!</p>
<p>Push now supports over 9 networks including <strong>Ethereum, Polygon, Polygon Zkevm, BNB, and Fuse.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/interoperable-communications-moving-across-an-open-web-with-push/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Time to move across the open web with Push!</a></p>
<a href="https://app.push.org/channels?chain=1&amp;category=All" title="Networks Supported by Push" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> More networks, More new channels → Check them out here</a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="8-analytics-dashboard-and-website-revamp-">8. Analytics Dashboard (and Website Revamp) 📊<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#8-analytics-dashboard-and-website-revamp-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 8. Analytics Dashboard (and Website Revamp) 📊" title="Direct link to 8. Analytics Dashboard (and Website Revamp) 📊">​</a></h2>
<p>Want a glance at Protocol’s LIVE numbers?</p>
<p>Meet the Push Analytics Dashboard - A comprehensive source of real-time data, tracking every aspect of Push Protocol’s services - notifications, subscribers, channel performance and many more!</p>
<a href="https://push.network/dashboard" title="Push Communications Protocol Dashboard" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Checkout Push Communications Protocol’s Analytics here</a>
<p>User activity and footprint on Push’s landing page have been growing immensely, every passing day!</p>
<p>To ensure any unique (new) as well as seasoned web3 user understands the protocol’s mission, features and offerings - we’ve taken our website to the next level! This upgrade spans both Push Communications Protocol and Push Chain.</p>
<p><em>If you’ve read so far: a. you’re the best! b. more about Push Chain, in our final section 🏁</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="9-launched-wallet-to-email--telegram-notifications-">9. Launched Wallet to Email / Telegram Notifications 📧<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#9-launched-wallet-to-email--telegram-notifications-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 9. Launched Wallet to Email / Telegram Notifications 📧" title="Direct link to 9. Launched Wallet to Email / Telegram Notifications 📧">​</a></h2>
<p>After tapping into over 300,000 wallets and sending over 100 million notifications we thought - <strong><em>how about sending on-chain notifications directly to your email or telegram?</em></strong></p>
<p>This helps Push Communications to reach billions of everyday Email and TG users while paving the way for much smoother onboarding for web2 normies and budding web2 users.</p>
<p>Now, users can receive web3 notifications from over 500 DApps straight to their Telegram or email accounts - no need to connect a wallet or endure various friction points while entering the web3 space. Simply, connect your TG and Email and receive notifs.</p>
<p>It's that easy!</p>
<a href="https://app.push.org/points/activity" title="Push Notifications on Telegram and Email" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Connect your Tg and Email to receive instant alerts!</a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="10-push-metmamask-snap-v2">10. Push Metmamask Snap V2<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#10-push-metmamask-snap-v2" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 10. Push Metmamask Snap V2" title="Direct link to 10. Push Metmamask Snap V2">​</a></h2>
<p>In 2023, we bought Push Notifications to over 30 million Metamask users -by launching the <a href="https://app.push.org/?/snap" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Metamask Snap</a>. In 2024, we upgraded the snap to <strong>support chat and snooze notifications features</strong> - to help users manage their notifications at their own pace and other forms of communication as well.</p>
<p>Due to Metamasks limitations for supporting communications across its mobile apps, we introduced in-app chat notifications on Push Mobile App <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/push-epns/id1528614910" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">iOS</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=io.epns.epns&amp;hl=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Android</a></p>
<a href="https://app.push.org/snap" title="Push Metamask Snap" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Get notified on your Metamask Wallet </a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="11-incredible-integrations-">11. Incredible Integrations! 🤝<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#11-incredible-integrations-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 11. Incredible Integrations! 🤝" title="Direct link to 11. Incredible Integrations! 🤝">​</a></h2>
<p>2024 was a year filled with incredible integrations. The Push Ecosystem has expanded to 500+ Projects!</p>
<p>Notable mentions include - <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1851625233654153716" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hyperliquid</a>, <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1826957066520383638" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QuickSwap</a>,<a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1844008819954970813" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cartesi</a>, <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1842198518418612357" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Revoke</a> and many more.</p>
<a href="https://push.org/frens/" title="Frens Of Push" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Explore the Push Ecosystem here </a>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="12-push-dao-soaring-to-new-heights-">12. Push DAO soaring to new heights 🔝<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#12-push-dao-soaring-to-new-heights-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 12. Push DAO soaring to new heights ���🔝" title="Direct link to 12. Push DAO soaring to new heights 🔝">​</a></h2>
<p>Push DAO witnessed extraordinary exposure and participation in 2024.</p>
<p>With hundreds of new participants, over 50 regular contributors, global exposure, quality grantees, and tremendous support from the Push Fam community, we've made exceptional progress.</p>
<p>In June 2024, we launched Push DAO V2 to advance our journey toward progressive decentralization.
This new framework, supported by the DAO Council, streamlines engagement for contributors and builders.</p>
<p>The launch of our <strong>Push Grants Program V3</strong> empowered both, early-stage and established projects building innovative social, gaming, and mobile apps. This initiative has driven impressive results—increasing grant applications tenfold and multiplying our active grantees five times over since the beginning of the year.</p>
<p>Our Push DAO BD SubDAO Program now offers rewards ranging from <strong>$500–$1500</strong> for successful integrations of Push Notifications/Chat with DAOs, DeFi protocols, dApps, and other projects. Through our council and contributors' dedicated efforts, this program has generated over 80 qualified leads for our ecosystem.</p>
<p>Our revamped ambassador programs have reached new heights of influence, establishing a student hub at <strong>Texas Tech University</strong> and forming connections with event organizers across more than four continents.</p>
<p>As we prepare to launch Push Chain, our DAO stands ready to make a significant impact on the ecosystem and beyond. Our core team brings together professionals with cross-industry expertise, while our current and prospective grantees span key industry sectors.
Having achieved extraordinary growth in less than a year, we're positioned for even greater achievements in 2025.</p>
<p>With our coordinated event and marketing strategy for the launch in place, you can expect to see the DAO everywhere next year, driving the chain's progress.</p>
<p>With hundreds of new contributors, global exposures, quality grantees and a lot of love from the Push Fam community!</p>
<p>To continue our journey of Push DAO towards progressive decentralisation we introduced a new DAO framework, <a href="https://gov.push.org/t/push-dao-v2-push-dao-council/1631" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push DAO V2</a>. This framework simplifies the process for contributors and builders to engage with the DAO, with the support of the DAO Council.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Push Grants Council" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image8-fb63f99e0dde1f5b49996626d2618524.webp" width="2000" height="1127" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<a href="https://gov.push.org/" title="Push Governance Forum" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Explore Push Governance Forum </a>
<p><em>And now - time for the special ALPHA!</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="13-gm-push-chain">13. GM Push Chain!👋<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#13-gm-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 13. GM Push Chain!👋" title="Direct link to 13. GM Push Chain!👋">​</a></h2>
<p>After years of building one of the first consumer apps in web3, one key takeaway we learnt, was the pressing need for a consumer app-centric chain capable of unifying the entire web3 ecosystem under a shared state.</p>
<p>This realization inspired the creation of <a href="https://push.org/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain</a> - <strong>a shared-state Layer 1 blockchain that unifies the settlement of all the incredible L1s, L2s, and L3s, enabling any user from any chain to access any app through one unified shared state.</strong></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="governance">Governance<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#governance" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Governance" title="Direct link to Governance">​</a></h3>
<p>The Push Chain proposal received an overwhelming response at the Push Gov Forum with over 92% acceptance.
The proposal then went on to SnapShot for formal voting - and we’re super stoked to announce that the community heavily participated in showing their voice and <a href="https://snapshot.box/#/s:pushdao.eth/proposal/0xa4a301c9a346356326d59e425245459d9fbde71b02aabc49a4ce191f0504f66a" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">passing the massive majority!</a> Indicating a positive alignment with the team’s and the community’s vision.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-chain-whitepaper">Push Chain WhitePaper<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#push-chain-whitepaper" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push Chain WhitePaper" title="Direct link to Push Chain WhitePaper">​</a></h3>
<p>If you're curious about Push Chain's philosophical and technical foundations and want to take a detailed look, dive into the <a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>.</p>
<p>The Whitepaper constitutes everything you need to know about Push Chain’s Vision, Mission and all the underlying technical innovations that solve the current hardships in Web3.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-chain-litepaper">Push Chain LitePaper<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#push-chain-litepaper" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push Chain LitePaper" title="Direct link to Push Chain LitePaper">​</a></h3>
<p>Want a quick tour of Push Chain - And learn about the problem it solves, key innovations it brings and the usecases it unlocks - explore the <a href="https://push.org/litepaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push LitePaper</a>!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="14-launched-push-chain-devnet--push-scan--push-chain-website-">14. Launched Push Chain Devnet + Push Scan + Push Chain Website 🌐<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#14-launched-push-chain-devnet--push-scan--push-chain-website-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 14. Launched Push Chain Devnet + Push Scan + Push Chain Website 🌐" title="Direct link to 14. Launched Push Chain Devnet + Push Scan + Push Chain Website 🌐">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-chain-devnet">Push Chain Devnet<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#push-chain-devnet" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push Chain Devnet" title="Direct link to Push Chain Devnet">​</a></h3>
<p>We launched the <strong>Push Chain Devnet</strong>, offering an exciting sneak peek into transactions confirmed with sub-second finality - all while interacting with the chain in a <strong>chain-and wallet-agnostic</strong> manner. 🫣</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-scan">Push Scan<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#push-scan" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push Scan" title="Direct link to Push Scan">​</a></h3>
<p>Also, say hello to <a href="https://scan.push.org/home" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Scan</a> 👋 - A comprehensive explorer to view and analyze all transactions on the Push Chain.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-website">Push Website<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#push-website" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push Website" title="Direct link to Push Website">​</a></h3>
<p>Alongside, we unveiled the <a href="https://push.org/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a> - your go-to hub for all things Push Chain! Whether you’re looking for insights into its vision, key innovations, ecosystem, or developer tooling, the website acts as your gateway to the <strong>Universe of Universal Apps.</strong></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="15-push-nodes-are-here">15. Push Nodes are here!<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#15-push-nodes-are-here" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 15. Push Nodes are here!" title="Direct link to 15. Push Nodes are here!">​</a></h2>
<p>Push fam, we know you were extremely eager for Push Nodes, after its announcement early, this year.</p>
<p>Unlike most of the L1s, Push Chain too is a Proof Of Stake network - but with its own innovative flavour.</p>
<p>Push Chain splits the nodes into three types - Validator, Storage and Archival and enables a node governance smart contract that keeps track of all the nodes that are present in the network.</p>
<p><strong>Validator nodes</strong> - Responsible for validating transactions;</p>
<p><strong>Storage nodes</strong> - Dynamically shard data based on the hash of blockchain-agnostic addresses and store it; and</p>
<p><strong>Archival nodes</strong> - Maintain a full snapshot of all transactions on the network.</p>
<p>Push Chain also introduced <strong>Node Registry Smart Contracts</strong> a key innovation that : - Registers nodes. - Manage dynamic sharding. - Set replication factors. - Enable parallel validators that scale dynamically with the number of nodes in the network and thus achieve <strong>True Scale</strong>!</p>
<a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" title="Push Governance Forum" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Innovations by Push Chain </a>
<p><strong>Want a trial run and learn more about Push Nodes?</strong>
Checkout Push Nodes GitHub Repos:</p>
<p>👉 <a href="https://github.com/push-protocol/push-vnode" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Run Validator Node</a></p>
<p>👉 <a href="https://github.com/push-protocol/push-snode" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Run Storage Node</a></p>
<p>👉 <a href="https://github.com/push-protocol/push-anode" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Run Archival Node</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="15-launched-push-wallet--simulate-tx-">15. Launched Push Wallet + Simulate Tx 👝<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#15-launched-push-wallet--simulate-tx-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 15. Launched Push Wallet + Simulate Tx 👝" title="Direct link to 15. Launched Push Wallet + Simulate Tx 👝">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain incorporates <strong>Wallet Abstraction to diminish the growing divide in operational level comfort experienced by Existing Web3 users and New users (Web2 normies) by creating a balanced ground for every web3 user persona.</strong></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-wallet">Push Wallet<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#push-wallet" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push Wallet" title="Direct link to Push Wallet">​</a></h3>
<p>We were thrilled to introduce the <a href="https://wallet.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Wallet</a>—a secure, user-friendly, and interoperable key management solution designed for the Push unified network.</p>
<p>Push Wallet offers: - A flexible and embeddable wallet experience tailored to individual user journeys. - Web2-style sign-ins. - Seamless connectivity, interaction, and transactions for wallets from any chain.</p>
<a href="https://wallet.push.org/" title="Push Governance Forum" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Try Push Wallet</a>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="simulate-transactions">Simulate Transactions<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#simulate-transactions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Simulate Transactions" title="Direct link to Simulate Transactions">​</a></h3>
<p>To offer an early glimpse into transacting on Push Chain, we launched the Push Simulate Transactions App. This app showcases:</p>
<ul>
<li>Consumer (unordered) transactions on Push Devnet.</li>
<li>Key innovations like PoS consensus, parallel validators, dynamic sharding, and wallet abstraction in action.</li>
</ul>
<a href="https://simulate.push.org/" title="Simulate Push" class="SharedStyling__ABlock-sc-1enui31-20 dNvHap"> Experience Push Chain with Simulate Transactions</a>
<p><strong><em>There's so much more to reveal and even more to ship! 🚀</em></strong>
<strong><em>Can't wait for Q1 2025.</em></strong></p>
<p>The entire Push Team is equally proud and excited to bring Push Chain to the public!</p>
<p>Push Chain is the future of an all-inclusive web3 - and we’re super humbled and honoured to build it with all of you.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="honorary-mentions-">Honorary mentions 🙌<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/push-year-in-review-2024#honorary-mentions-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Honorary mentions 🙌" title="Direct link to Honorary mentions 🙌">​</a></h2>
<p>→ <strong>Hyper Scalable Group Chats</strong> - With new architectural upgrades, <a href="https://app.push.org/chat" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chats</a> have become faster and more scalable. Public group limits have skyrocketed from 1500 to an impressive 25,000 members. Similarly, private groups once capped at 50 members, now support up to 5,000 participants. <a href="https://push.org/blog/benchmarking-push-chat-message/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Checkout our Push Chat Benchmarks here</a></p>
<p>→ <strong>Push Group Chats for Guilds</strong> - We <a href="https://guild.xyz/explorer" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Guild</a> gated the group chats. Now, any guild LIVE on Guild.xyz can start a Push-based group chat, bringing us closer to our goal of providing customizable support for all forms of group conversations. <a href="https://push.org/blog/push-group-chats-for-guilds/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Know, how to create your guild gated chat today!</a></p>
<p>→ <strong>Billion Reasons to Build (BRB) Bootcamp was back with a bang!</strong> - This time with a <a href="https://push.org/blog/billion-reason-to-build-bootcamp-covering-every-dimension-of-the-web3-ecosystem/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">global online edition</a> with participation from over <strong>21</strong>countries and prizes worth <strong>5,500$</strong>!
The 6-week boot camp inducted over 80 gem students amongst thousands of competing applications. Spanned over 11 sessions, the BRB boot camp was built to - Equip participants with the skills and knowledge needed to thrive in the evolving landscape of blockchain and web3 technologies, as well as essential skills in marketing, design, and startup development.</p>
<p>The boot camp gained a global outreach with over <strong>60,000</strong> impressions and unmeasurable love!</p>
<p>→ <strong>More SDK Upgrades</strong> - We further enhanced the Push SDK by optimizing the code to align with the new design system, added support for <strong>ERC1155 Gated Chat Groups</strong>, launched the <strong>Push SDK Demo React app</strong>, ensured <strong>compatibility with the Base chain</strong>, and integrated <strong>SpaceID’s</strong> package to resolve .arb and .bnb domains.</p>
<p>→ <strong>Say hello to the Push Alpha Community</strong> - We created an exclusive community for long-time Push Supporters and various contest winners - called <a href="https://push.org/blog/how-to-join-the-push-alpha-community/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Alpha Community</a> - The Alpha Access NFT holders gain exclusive access to alpha-only events, campaigns, airdrops, and partner surprises.</p>
<p>→ Launched exclusive <a href="https://push.org/blog/announcing-group-chat-from-push-unstoppable/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">domain-gated group chats</a> for 3.8M+ Unstoppable Domain users</p>
<p>→ Revamped the channel creation process for a more intuitive UX.</p>
<p>→ Made tons of improvements to our Developer Docs to make your building journey with Push Protocol truly <em>Pushtastic!</em> 🚀</p>
<p>→ A plethora of podcast appearances including <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zpqP_b-ch1A" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hipther Podcast Show</a>, <a href="https://www.charlieshrem.com/pushing-crypto-to-the-edge-redefining-communication-and-security-with-ian-leviness-and-pascal-gauth/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Charlie Shrem Podcast</a> and many more.</p>
<p>→ Participated in major hackathons, conferences and sponsored bounties around the globe including, <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1811046959353880785" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eth CC Brussels</a>, Token 2049 Singapore &amp; Dubai, <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1857365249239679134" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ETH Bangkok</a>, <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1846597335859540055" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eth Safari</a>, <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1840669685177557334" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Invisible Gardens</a>, <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1849709744002630131" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Binance Blockchain Week(Dubai)</a>, India Blockchain Week.</p>
<p>→ Kickstarted <a href="https://x.com/PushChain/status/1826313152176251142" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write for Push</a> initiative - aimed at enabling anyone in the Push community to contribute to the protocol’s blog repository and help shape its voice.</p>
<p>Before looking at what's ahead this coming year, we want to take a moment to thank the entire Push team, all our partners, investors and builders. 2024 was an amazing year for Push and we are excited to share what we have planned for 2025! Stay tuned. With loads of love ❤️ from the Push team!</p>
<p>That’s a wrap!
See you all in 2025 🫡</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Updates</category>
            <category>Insights</category>
            <category>Year In Review</category>
            <category>Shared App Experience</category>
            <category>Any Chain Tx</category>
            <category>Universal Smart Contracts</category>
            <category>Shared State Blockchain</category>
            <category>Consumer Tx</category>
            <category>Parallel Validators</category>
            <category>Dynamic Sharding</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Innovations by Push Chain]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Innovations by Push Chain]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Innovations By Push Chain" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/cover-image-d4de94c63723c0248a825a015a1f2c78.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="introduction">Introduction<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#introduction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Introduction" title="Direct link to Introduction">​</a></h2>
<p>Push recently unveiled its new layer 1 blockchain - Push Chain, a shared state blockchain designed for shared app experiences.</p>
<p>Unlike traditional Layer 1 chains, Push Chain introduces ten key innovations and optimized mechanisms to unify any chain, any user, and any app.</p>
<p>This article will help you understand:</p>
<ul>
<li>What innovations Push Chain brings to web3</li>
<li>How Push Chain enables any user to connect to any app from any chain</li>
<li>How Push Chain is positioned to onboard the first billion users to web3 (for real!)</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="tldr">TLDR;<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#tldr" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to TLDR;" title="Direct link to TLDR;">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://push.org/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain</a> is a Proof of Stake shared state blockchain designed to support the development of hyper-scalable, consumer-centric, universal web3 applications by unifying settlement from any L1s, L2s and L3s.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="push architecture diagram" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image1-f0449ab66b8b7f04df4944bab35b03ff.webp" width="1600" height="1432" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Key Innovations and Superpowers of Push Chain include:</p>
<p>→ 1. <strong>Blockchain agnostic wallet addresses</strong></p>
<p>→ 2. <strong>Support Txns from any chain</strong></p>
<p>→ 3. <strong>Fee Abstraction</strong></p>
<p>→ 4. <strong>Wallet Abstraction</strong></p>
<p>→ 5. <strong>Consumer (Unordered) and Traditional (Ordered) Transactions</strong></p>
<p>→ 6. <strong>True Scale: Sub Second Finality (speed)</strong></p>
<p>→ 7. <strong>True Scale: Parallel validators (scaling write throughput)</strong></p>
<p>→ 8. <strong>True Scale: Dynamic Sharding (scaling read throughput)</strong></p>
<p>→ 9. <strong>Push ID</strong></p>
<p>→ 10. <strong>Universal Smart Contracts and Shared State</strong></p>
<p>Let’s take a closer look at each of these innovations and enhancements</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="innovations-by-push-chain">Innovations By Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#innovations-by-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Innovations By Push Chain" title="Direct link to Innovations By Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="1-blockchain-agnostic-wallet-addresses">1. Blockchain agnostic wallet addresses<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#1-blockchain-agnostic-wallet-addresses" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Blockchain agnostic wallet addresses" title="Direct link to 1. Blockchain agnostic wallet addresses">​</a></h3>
<p>For Apps to support users from any chain and achieve <strong>universal compatibility</strong> - there must be a way to identify, interpret and transact with addresses incoming from various chains.</p>
<p>As a shared-state blockchain, Push Chain is designed to parse and handle blockchain addresses alongside the specific chains they originate from.</p>
<p>For instance, Push Chain can identify and support Solana, EVM, Cosmos and any other chain’s addresses.
To achieve this, Push Chain fully adopts <a href="https://github.com/ChainAgnostic/CAIPs/blob/main/CAIPs/caip-10.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CAIP-10</a> blockchain-agnostic wallet addresses, enabling it to deduce the chain, network, and address associated with each transaction ensuring universal compatibility across multiple blockchain ecosystems.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="2-support-txns-from-any-chain">2. Support Txns from any chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#2-support-txns-from-any-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Support Txns from any chain" title="Direct link to 2. Support Txns from any chain">​</a></h3>
<p>In addition to parsing addresses across various chains, Push Chain supports transactions from any wallet, regardless of the originating chain—be it Ethereum, Solana, or any other network.</p>
<p>Push Chain achieves this by accepting signed payload data and supporting the native signers of individual chains. Validator nodes then verify these signatures → conduct pre-transaction checks (such as fee validation) → and then admit the transactions to the network.</p>
<p>To clarify, a user doesn’t have to “bridge” to another chain to use our platform. Instead, the app becomes universal and available to all users of any chain.</p>
<p>Push Chain also introduces a new mechanism called <strong>Push ID</strong> to create a consistent and unified interface for users, no matter which wallet they use.</p>
<p><strong><em>More on Push ID below...</em></strong></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="3-fee-abstraction">3. Fee Abstraction<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#3-fee-abstraction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Fee Abstraction" title="Direct link to 3. Fee Abstraction">​</a></h3>
<p>With web3’s progression towards true interoperability, the necessity to hold native tokens for basic interactions creates unnecessary barriers in what should be a borderless ecosystem.</p>
<p><strong>Push Chain’s Fee Abstraction eliminates these digital borders, ensuring universal accessibility and removing the economic friction of owning native tokens for network fees.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Onchain Swappers</strong>: Fee contracts on every chain convert native tokens to cover fees automatically—no explicit swaps for Push Chain’s tokens are required.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Bulk Fee Payments</strong>: Lock and release fees in bulk, then send them to Push Chain directly in the transaction. This removes the bottleneck of waiting on a specific blockchain’s speed.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Delegated Fees</strong>: Wallets or web3 apps can cover fees, enabling a web2-like UX where the “website” pays for the user.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These mechanisms bridge web2 paradigms into web3 enabling web2 UX in a web3 world -</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Pay-for-content models</strong>: Apps like Facebook and Instagram cover user interaction fees.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Freemium models</strong>: Apps absorb user costs temporarily, enabling users to later pay in bulk for services after experiencing them for free (e.g., Spotify, Google Drive).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Push Chain makes these models possible, creating a frictionless experience and paving the way for building universal apps with borderless shared experiences.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="4-wallet-abstraction">4. Wallet abstraction<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#4-wallet-abstraction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. Wallet abstraction" title="Direct link to 4. Wallet abstraction">​</a></h3>
<p>At a higher level, there are two user personas in web3:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Degens (aka existing web3 users)</strong> - Well accustomed to the fragmented UX, have app &amp; chain specific preferences for every on-chain activity.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Normies (aka new web3 users)</strong> - New or casual users unfamiliar with web3 complexities - Struggle with the manual and often complicated process of setting up a wallet.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>With the rapid proliferation of L1s, L2s and L3s, the UX gap between Degens and Normies is widening, creating a disproportionate balance in user experiences.</p>
<p><strong>Push Chain’s Wallet Abstraction diminishes this divide by creating a balanced ground for every web3 user persona.</strong></p>
<p>Wallet abstraction provides a flexible, <strong>embeddable wallet experience</strong>, tailored to individual user journeys enabling any wallet from any chain to connect, interact and transact with Push Chain.</p>
<p><strong>Existing Web3 Users?</strong></p>
<p>Already using Ethereum, Solana, or another chain? Push Wallet lets you continue using your existing setup—no extra hoops. Combined with fee abstraction, transactions stay native to the source blockchain, making cross-chain use effortless.</p>
<p><strong>New Web3 Users (Web2 Normies)?</strong></p>
<p>Not web3-savvy? No problem. Just log in with an email or social account. Under the hood, the wallet uses sharding and pass keys to stay non-custodial but feels as simple and intuitive as web2.</p>
<p><strong>For users logging in via email or social platforms</strong>, Push Chain ensures security and non-custodial functionality through key sharding. The user’s credentials are divided into three encrypted shards stored across the Push Backend (trusted), local storage (encrypted via a passkey), and Push Chain (also encrypted via a passkey). This approach allows key reconstruction only when accessed by the user, providing a secure yet user-friendly experience that bridges the gap between web2 familiarity and web3 security.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="5-consumer-unordered-and-traditional-ordered-transactions">5. Consumer (Unordered) and Traditional (Ordered) Transactions<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#5-consumer-unordered-and-traditional-ordered-transactions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. Consumer (Unordered) and Traditional (Ordered) Transactions" title="Direct link to 5. Consumer (Unordered) and Traditional (Ordered) Transactions">​</a></h3>
<p>Present web3 infra is heavily skewed towards financial apps that require strict ordering of transactions and precise state accuracy.
However consumer apps, on the other hand, are inclined towards more flexible, faster and parallel transaction needs.
Consumer apps are made of two primary elements where:</p>
<ol>
<li><em>Order is necessary (user payments, financial instruments) and</em></li>
<li><em>Order is not critical (messages, comments or likes on a post, retweet, chat, email, gameplay, etc.).</em></li>
</ol>
<p>Traditional chains don’t provide the right experience for such use cases forcing consumer apps to make suboptimal compromises impacting their performance and usability.</p>
<p><strong><em>Could there be a way of supporting consumer actions in an unordered, parallel and yet decentralised manner?</em></strong></p>
<p>Absolutely yes! This is where <strong>Push Chain innovates a new transaction type - Consumer Transaction</strong>- which instantly unlocks non-financial, mixed-financial apps for web3 helping consumer apps reach faster PMF.</p>
<p>Managing hyper-scalable apps with thousands of parallel transactions on-chain - is not easy.
Push Chain makes it possible using its new innovation - <strong>True Scale</strong>.</p>
<p>With True Scale, Push Chain's network capacity and its read-write throughput grow organically, as more nodes join its consensus.
This enables parallel execution of thousands of consumer transactions, near-instant finality and quicker information storage and retrieval.</p>
<p>Here’s how the Push Chain achieves true scale.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="6-true-scale-sub-second-finality-speed">6. True Scale: Sub second finality (speed)<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#6-true-scale-sub-second-finality-speed" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 6. True Scale: Sub second finality (speed)" title="Direct link to 6. True Scale: Sub second finality (speed)">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Chain splits the nodes into three types - <strong>Validator, Storage and Archival</strong> and enables a node governance smart contract that keeps track of all the nodes that are present in the network.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Validator Nodes</strong> - Responsible for validating transactions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Storage Nodes</strong> - Dynamically shard data based on the hash of blockchain-agnostic addresses and store it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Archival Nodes</strong> - Maintain a full snapshot of all transactions on the network.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These role-specific nodes enable parallel validation to be done on any type of consumer transaction ensuring near-instant finality.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> All txs (write or read) are attested by random validators/storage nodes ensuring that malicious nodes result in slashing.</p>
<p><strong>Node Registry Smart Contract:</strong> Push Chain employs a registry smart contract to register these nodes, manage dynamic sharding, set replication factors, and enable parallel validators that scale dynamically with the number of nodes in the network. This approach ensures linear scaling, allowing the network to handle increased read and write demands efficiently as it grows.</p>
<p>Because of these different nodes and smart contract setting up parallel validators, the tx sent to the network can land on any of the <em>‘n’</em> number of parallel validators which are then instantly moved to processing (250ms block), this is what enables sub-second finality for Push Chain.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="7-true-scale-parallel-validators-scaling-write-throughput">7. True Scale: Parallel validators (scaling write throughput)<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#7-true-scale-parallel-validators-scaling-write-throughput" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 7. True Scale: Parallel validators (scaling write throughput)" title="Direct link to 7. True Scale: Parallel validators (scaling write throughput)">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Chain achieves true scaling of write transactions, particularly for consumer transactions, where the consumer txs are packed in unordered blocks (or should we call them <strong>stateless blocks</strong>!? ).</p>
<p>Allowing these transactions to be processed through any active validator node promises near-instant finality, and the write throughput (or TPS) of the chain increases linearly as the number of nodes in the network grows.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="8-true-scale-dynamic-sharding-scaling-read-throughput">8. True Scale: Dynamic Sharding (scaling read throughput)<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#8-true-scale-dynamic-sharding-scaling-read-throughput" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 8. True Scale: Dynamic Sharding (scaling read throughput)" title="Direct link to 8. True Scale: Dynamic Sharding (scaling read throughput)">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Push Chain achieves true scaling of reading transactions by implementing dynamic sharding on storage nodes.</strong></p>
<p>Data chunks within each shard are mapped to blockchain-agnostic addresses and are dynamically redistributed as new storage nodes are added to the network.</p>
<p>In addition, the chain introduces a node governing smart contract onto which each node (regardless of the type) is registered before getting admitted to the network. Since this node-registry smart contract knows the number of nodes in the network, it is able to dynamically shard and assign data chunks and replication factors ensuring the network is fast and becomes faster in retrieving data as new nodes are added.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="9-push-id">9. Push ID<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#9-push-id" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 9. Push ID" title="Direct link to 9. Push ID">​</a></h3>
<p>In a universal chain like Push Chain - One essential element for bringing shared app experiences to users is the ability to track users’ on-chain identity - and not just their wallets.</p>
<p>One user may have multiple wallets, spanning various chains and ecosystems whether EVM or nonEVM.
This led us to create the unified Push ID, giving each user one identity that spans all their wallets, both EVM and non-EVM. Instead of tying interactions strictly to a single wallet, transactions are now accredited to a user’s Push ID.</p>
<p>The Push ID mapping allows for reverse lookups guaranteeing a consistent and unified interface for users, no matter which wallet they use. developers can fetch, index, and understand a user’s full spectrum of interactions across chains, all mapped to one identity.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="10-shared-state-and-universal-smart-contracts">10. Shared State and Universal Smart Contracts<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#10-shared-state-and-universal-smart-contracts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 10. Shared State and Universal Smart Contracts" title="Direct link to 10. Shared State and Universal Smart Contracts">​</a></h3>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="shared state diagram" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/assets/images/image2-f0f9ca159f743240746e1fb8914950b4.webp" width="1600" height="1213" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><strong>Shared State</strong></p>
<p>With Push ID and Any Chain Tx, we realized that accessing a wallet’s state across different blockchains is a game changer.</p>
<p>One thing that’s missing over here though was the ability to get the individual state of all the wallets which in essence will allow smart contracts to know the entire state of individual wallet(s) that are connected to the user. This feature is what we call a Shared state.</p>
<p><strong>Shared state allows Push Chain to access data from its own chain as well as supported external chains!</strong></p>
<p>With shared state, you can read wallet activities like NFTs, DeFi positions, governance participation, and so much more!</p>
<p><strong>Universal Smart Contracts</strong></p>
<p>A shared state chain is essential to enable shared app experiences. This chain must have the ability to read the state of wallets across other chains, facilitating universal smart contracts and creating an ecosystem where users from any chain—or even web2—can interact seamlessly. Such a chain would provide shared settlement across both EVM and non-EVM chains, ushering in an era of universal apps and shared experiences.</p>
<p>Using shared state in VM, Push allows developers to write universal smart contracts with which universal app experiences become possible. Users, regardless of their origin—whether from any chain or ecosystem—can effortlessly interact with consumer apps that prioritize user engagement without regard to how or where they enter the system.</p>
<p>Ultimately, <strong>Universal Smart Contracts and the ability to interact with all chains through Push Chain and represent our ultimate goal: Eliminating Web3 friction and delivering the best shared app experience possible.</strong></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="build-universal-apps">Build Universal Apps!<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#build-universal-apps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Build Universal Apps!" title="Direct link to Build Universal Apps!">​</a></h2>
<p>Universal AI apps, Universal social apps, Unified Prediction markets and many more!
Want to know the countless app innovations that you can make happen because of Push Chain?
Explore our <a href="https://push.org/blog/consumer-apps-that-can-be-built-on-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Innovations that can be built on Push Chain Blog</a></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps​👇<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1012/blog/innovations-by-push-chain#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps​👇" title="Direct link to Next Steps​👇">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Check out the <a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a> for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Visit the <a href="https://push.org/chain/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a> to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://scan.push.org/home?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a> is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://simulate.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a> already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</p>
</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Shared App Experience</category>
            <category>Any Chain Tx</category>
            <category>Universal Smart Contracts</category>
            <category>Shared State Blockchain</category>
            <category>Consumer Tx</category>
            <category>Parallel Validators</category>
            <category>Dynamic Sharding</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>