<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Push Chain | Any Chain. Any Wallet. Any App. Blog</title>
        <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog</link>
        <description>Push Chain | Any Chain. Any Wallet. Any App. Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Interop as a Spectrum]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[How Web3 Interop Started and Where its Going]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Interop as a Spectrum" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-106422a36c33aa1ea942a9b199a40b5d.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="intro">Intro<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#intro" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Intro" title="Direct link to Intro">​</a></h2>
<p>Web3 Interoperability (interop) is often seen as an imaginary creature, a unicorn that will never become real. This is because it's like a path on which the perfect destination is difficult to find, and there are tons of design choices, learning curves as well as UX compromises along the way.</p>
<p>Attempts to 'solve' interop within these constraints has led to a variety of solutions.</p>
<p>In this article, we provide a general overview of these approaches and show how they are all interconnected. We also highlight how the meaning of interop has shifted as the web3 industry has matured and expanded, and outline a possible endgame.</p>
<p>Before we get to that, i.e. full stack interoperability, we will discuss how interop started and, more importantly, why it should be viewed as a spectrum rather than a binary ‘0’ or ‘1‘. In reality, interop and the desire to defragment has been with us from the moment Bitcoin on/off-ramp came to existence!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-interop-spectrum">The Interop Spectrum<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#the-interop-spectrum" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Interop Spectrum" title="Direct link to The Interop Spectrum">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="1-the-first-interop---centralized-exchanges">1. The First Interop - Centralized Exchanges<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#1-the-first-interop---centralized-exchanges" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. The First Interop - Centralized Exchanges" title="Direct link to 1. The First Interop - Centralized Exchanges">​</a></h3>
<p>The desire for an interoperable and defragmented web3 has been with us ever since the first Bitcoin on/off-ramp took off. No sooner did it come into existence than our desire to make it tradable with traditional finance (TradFi) arose. This need was further deepened with the rise of other layer 1s such as Ethereum, Ripple, Cardano etc.</p>
<p>The user's need was clear: a unified interface which allowed the trading of different crypto assets directly and instantly. Centralised exchanges (CEXs) arose to fulfil this need. They abstracted away the complexity of different chains from the frontend at the cost of introducing trust assumptions and centralisation at the backend.</p>
<p>This era saw the origin of many CEXs, some of which have since disappeared (such as Mt. Gox), and others that have become household crypto names (such as Coinbase and Binance). While this worked for the users who wanted convenience, it also exposed issues with centralizing decentralized assets, giving us the next problem we had to tackle.</p>
<p>The Progressive Problem - CEXs, with their centralized custody, opened up new issues for crypto and web3. Most of them arose from the very nature of custodial design which included exchanges getting hacked, users getting locked out or losing time before getting their funds and of course, the rare but not uncommon issue of exchange founders vanishing with keys that custodied the user funds.</p>
<p>This led us, the web3 collective, to work towards solving these issues which resulted in the <strong>next iterative innovation</strong> in chasing interop. A solution known as <strong>atomic swaps</strong> - a method by which two chains could perform a trustless exchange.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="2-atomic-swaps---hashlock-time-contracts-between-compatible-chains">2. Atomic Swaps - Hashlock time contracts between compatible chains<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#2-atomic-swaps---hashlock-time-contracts-between-compatible-chains" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Atomic Swaps - Hashlock time contracts between compatible chains" title="Direct link to 2. Atomic Swaps - Hashlock time contracts between compatible chains">​</a></h3>
<p>Atomic swaps were so named because they turned a 'swap' into a self-contained unit of operations on smart contracts which would succeed or fail as a bundle. This was done to prevent situations in which one side fulfils its side of the bargain but the other does not. We will later see how this idea of 'atomicity' survives to this day in solver networks.</p>
<p>Proposed on a Bitcoin forum in 2013 as 'hash-time locked contracts' (HTLCs), the first iteration of atomic swaps involved two smart contracts (one each on the source and destination chains) operating together to form a digital escrow with a shared secret.</p>
<p>What makes them historically significant is that they were the first peer-to-peer chain-agnostic interop solution. Initially, they unified the interop design space by showing that trustless cross-chain swaps were possible between all ecosystems. Over time, however, they resulted in a new round of competition between 'HTLC compatible' chains.</p>
<p><strong>The Progressive Problem</strong> - Despite being peer-to-peer, HTLCs were unable to 'solve' the interop problem due to two important limitations: (a) They involved multiple transactions leading to scalability challenges. (b) Different blockchains had their own standards which were not compatible.</p>
<p>These bottlenecks led to the <strong>next iterative innovations</strong>: in the form of <strong>decentralised exchanges</strong> (DEXs) and <strong>multi-chain wallets</strong>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="3-local-interop-and-non-custodial-solutions">3. Local Interop and non-custodial solutions<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#3-local-interop-and-non-custodial-solutions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Local Interop and non-custodial solutions" title="Direct link to 3. Local Interop and non-custodial solutions">​</a></h3>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="31-local-interop-via-dexs">3.1 Local Interop via DEXs<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#31-local-interop-via-dexs" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3.1 Local Interop via DEXs" title="Direct link to 3.1 Local Interop via DEXs">​</a></h4>
<p>This breakthrough was led by Uniswap, which later pioneered not only decentralized finance (DeFi) but also kicked off the era of web3 apps. Its key innovation was to replace centralised orderbooks with automated market making algorithms (AMMs) and decentralised liquidity pools. This solved a lot of problems for advanced web3 users as they could conduct asset swaps directly from their wallets (yes if you used Metamask back then, you were an advanced user!).</p>
<p>Technically speaking, such systems suffered from two fundamental limitations: (a) They required knowledge of how particular blockchains work (for instance, ERC-20 token function calls of Approve and Transfer was not something an average joe understood). (b) They were limited to their own chains.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="32-multi-chain-wallets">3.2 Multi-Chain Wallets<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#32-multi-chain-wallets" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3.2 Multi-Chain Wallets" title="Direct link to 3.2 Multi-Chain Wallets">​</a></h4>
<p>Around the same time, crypto wallets emerged that offered the convenience of self-custody, i.e., the ability to store tokens outside the ambit of exchanges. Although bulk of the trading still took place on CEXs, the user now had the option of using non-custodial wallets which could be standalone (e.g. Metamask, Electron) or multi-chain (e.g. Exodus, Trust).</p>
<p><strong>The Progressive Problem</strong> - Even with DEXs and multi-chain wallets, problems with swapping between different chains remained. At the same time, EVMs were going through countless innovations and purpose built L2 chains started propping up.</p>
<p>This led to the <strong>next iterative innovation</strong>, i.e. <strong>Bridging</strong>, which usually followed a ‘Lock and Mint’ solution. A standard on Cosmos also became popular in this time known as IBC(Inter-Blockchain Communication Protocol).</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="4-bridging-to-solve-interop-between-chains">4. Bridging to solve Interop between chains<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#4-bridging-to-solve-interop-between-chains" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. Bridging to solve Interop between chains" title="Direct link to 4. Bridging to solve Interop between chains">​</a></h3>
<p>Bridging was an excellent solution, albeit not without its own set of issues. It aimed to tackle moving funds between chains by first locking them on a smart contract and then using a set of validators, attesting and releasing the funds on other chains.</p>
<p>As is the nature of permissionless technologies, countless innovations emerged in parallel. We will consider the two main ones. First, trusted or semi-trusted bridging, which was how BTC was locked to mint WBTC, with minting being handled by a trusted set of custodians (WBTC DAO).</p>
<p>Second, which became the successor and was largely adopted in the industry was trustless bridging, involving a set of nodes attesting to the asset movement between chains. Some of the popular bridging solutions that we got were:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wormhole</strong>, where you locked your token on one chain and released it on another chain, the caveat being that as a developer, you had to tweak your smart contracts and bridging was usually slow. But this also meant locking all funds on one smart contract on a chain which opened a couple of attack vectors such as smart contract vulnerabilities or oracle manipulations, etc.</li>
<li><strong>IBC</strong>, which required running light clients on both the chains, which handled proof verification before moving funds; though this was limited mainly to Cosmos or required oracles with light node smart contracts on non-Cosmos chains to function leading to adaptation limited to only the Cosmos ecosystem.</li>
<li><strong>ZK Proofs</strong> and <strong>Optimistic Proofs</strong> that ensured Ethereum L1 to L2s transfer which were quite fast but at times expensive to compute or required several days of challenge period to escape (revert) back to L1.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The Progressive Problem</strong> - Bridging solved the trustlessness problem to an extent but largely was slow, forcing users to wait between movements or were fragmented or limited to a few eco-systems of chains.</p>
<p>This led to the <strong>next iterative innovation</strong>, which is known as the intent-solver system. In which an off-chain operator takes the risk (in exchange for a fee) for offering convenience and speed for moving funds across chains.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="5-intent-solvers-networks---bridging-on-steroids">5. Intent Solvers Networks - Bridging on Steroids<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#5-intent-solvers-networks---bridging-on-steroids" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. Intent Solvers Networks - Bridging on Steroids" title="Direct link to 5. Intent Solvers Networks - Bridging on Steroids">​</a></h3>
<p>With intent solver networks, we have entered the current era of interop solutions. They are arguably the biggest improvement we have seen since the days of CEXs.</p>
<p>The way they work is quite novel: instead of bridging (that requires trusted validators or decentralized validators to slowly attest and then move funds) they flip the attestation and risk away from the smart contract (used to lock and mint in bridges) and gives it to off-chain specialized actors that almost instantly fill the user’s intent(bridging, trading of assets, etc) using their own liquidity.</p>
<p>This feature works in the following way: :</p>
<ul>
<li>The user provides their intent such as “swap minimum ETH for USDT on Base” or “Swap SOL for minimum USDT on Ethereum”.</li>
<li>Along with this, the user either deposits assets, plus a small fee for solvers on a smart contract on the source chain or approves the assets to be used off-chain (mostly after they have already called approve on that app-specific smart contract).</li>
<li>These instructions are then taken to a solver network, which, in the simplest terms are made of single off-chain actors that at least have the desired asset liquidity on the destination chain.</li>
<li>The network then does an auction of sorts, which can be based on speed or cost. One popular auction mechanism done over is reverse Dutch auction, where the fee starts from the maximum point that will be paid and these off-chain solvers each bid a fee to win the auction. In the end, the lowest fee solver wins the bid and is tasked with fulfilling the intent.</li>
<li>All of this takes less than a few seconds to be completed, after which the solver fulfils the obligation using its own liquidity on the destination chain, ensuring that the user gets their funds lightning fast.</li>
<li>Later on, the solver submits the proof on the source smart contract, which mostly uses oracles to verify that the solver has done their job and then subsequently releases the funds to them.</li>
</ul>
<p>This approach improves speed (typically happens within a few seconds), eliminates the attack vector of a single bloated smart contract worth millions of dollars, and is also scalable. But it does not (yet) mean that we have a magic bullet for web3 interop.</p>
<p><strong>The Progressive Problem</strong> - The main problem with such networks is that they require a high degree of specialisation with unclear incentives for participation (e.g. solvers would much rather become liquidity providers and earn more). They may also be app-controlled which can lead to vendor lock-in, or highly function-specific which can result in avoidable coordination costs.</p>
<p>Furthermore, they need a reliable infrastructure on the app side (such as an oracle network) in order to determine the best trade routes. Even the simplest intents require precise and up to date knowledge of prices, a problem which is compounded as more chains get involved. And finally, there's the problem of liquidity pool coordination and rebalancing, which creates additional risk and complexity.</p>
<p>These problems have led us to design a new approach or the <strong>next iterative innovation</strong> keeping with the spirits of this article. We are terming them as '<strong>generalised programmable solvers'</strong> that can optimise, eliminate added infra and execute any custom routes which might be required by any developers of any app.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="6-generalized-programmable-solvers---solvers-that-are-smarter-co-ordinated-and-generalized">6. Generalized Programmable Solvers - Solvers that are smarter, co-ordinated and generalized<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#6-generalized-programmable-solvers---solvers-that-are-smarter-co-ordinated-and-generalized" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 6. Generalized Programmable Solvers - Solvers that are smarter, co-ordinated and generalized" title="Direct link to 6. Generalized Programmable Solvers - Solvers that are smarter, co-ordinated and generalized">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Programmable solvers</strong> is a term that we have coined at Push Chain to distinguish the next step in innovation that the solvers require to work at scale.</p>
<p>At its simplest, it means that developers will have shared state access to other blockchains, i.e. the ability to read, fetch and utilise the state of other chains. This will allow them to create custom pathways for fulfilling intents, all from a single universal EVM smart contract deployed on Push Chain.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Universal Smart Contract Example (Pseudocode)" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/image-2-b2d98b955f86d833d7c1872a9cd5f944.webp" width="2048" height="1103" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This approach solves a lot of issues that hamper the adoption of solvers in web3. In particular:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Eliminates the need for having an external oracle or underlying infrastructure</strong>: Shared state within Push Chain enables developers to logically code what their solvers need to do given different circumstances.</li>
</ul>
<p>For example, if someone wants to swap $TRUMP from Solana and they have USDT on BNB, they will be able to read the BNB-USDT value from PancakeSwap, the SOL-USDT value from Raydium, and thus calculate the $TRUMP-USDT value from Raydium; all from a single smart contract deployed on Push Chain!</p>
<p>Once you have these values, just provide basic(atomic) solver instructions from your smart contract (still on Push Chain) and then let the solver network do its magic.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enables anyone to be a solver / solves LP co-ordination:</strong> Once the solver network has a basic path, anyone can simply choose to run a basic solver software instead of creating a specialized one as the basic path is already provided. Though this doesn’t stop specialized solvers as they can then optimize the pathway by creating their own custom logic. The Solver network is now for everyone, instead of a few specialized actors.</li>
<li><strong>Allows specialized solvers pooling</strong>: Since the path can consist of different atomic steps – in the above example: swapping, bridging, protocol interaction – each one of these can be provided to action-specific specialized solvers, further solving the co-ordination issue.</li>
<li><strong>Enables any app to use solver network and be fully interoperable</strong>: Since all the functionalities are driven by a single universal smart contract deployed by the developer on Push Chain, the interop solution is now developer friendly, no matter what apps they are creating. Furthermore, it can be deployed in hours if not minutes!</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The Progressive Problem</strong> - The only problem this solution doesn’t address is the burden it places on the user to come to Push Chain to leverage the solution.</p>
<p>Which, of course, brings us to the <strong>next and final iterative solution - Full Stack Interop</strong>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="7-full-stack-interop---push-chain-universal-l1">7. Full Stack Interop - Push Chain (Universal L1)<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#7-full-stack-interop---push-chain-universal-l1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 7. Full Stack Interop - Push Chain (Universal L1)" title="Direct link to 7. Full Stack Interop - Push Chain (Universal L1)">​</a></h3>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Image" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/image-3-7eec2fece4c0893ad137838f4ea40f9a.webp" width="720" height="546" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain which is a universal L1 chain offers full stack interop to enable a synergetic, unified web3, where <strong>any apps</strong> of <strong>any chain</strong> become accessible by <strong>any user or wallet</strong> of any chain.</p>
<p>To facilitate seamless functionality for <strong>developers</strong>, it enables <strong>programmable solvers, shared state</strong> and <strong>universal smart contracts</strong> making it the most seamless Developer Experience (DevEX) crypto has ever seen.</p>
<p>And to ensure a frictionless, zero-learning and hassle-free environment for users, it employs <strong>Cross-chain fee</strong> &amp; <strong>Wallet Abstraction</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Cross-chain fee abstraction</strong> enables the user, no matter which chain they are on, to fund the gas for their transaction on Push Chain using native token of the chain they are currently on, eliminating the hassle for the user to bridge gas and allowing them to use the app from any chain.</p>
<p><strong>Wallet abstraction</strong> provides a flexible, embeddable wallet experience, tailored to individual user journeys while preserving decentralization. This type of abstraction offers a simpler UX to both existing and new web3 users.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Existing Web3 Users:</strong> Already using Ethereum, Solana, or another chain? The Push Chain wallet lets you continue using your existing setup -—no extra hoops. Combined with fee abstraction, transactions stay native to the source blockchain, making cross-chain use effortless.</li>
<li><strong>New Web3 Users (Web2 Normies):</strong> Not web3-savvy? No problem. Just log in with an email or social account. Under the hood, the wallet uses sharding and passkeys to stay non-custodial, but feels as simple and intuitive as web2.</li>
</ul>
<p>By enabling seamless transactions from any chain, abstracting away gas and wallet complexities, and fostering interoperability across L1s, L2s, and L3s, Push Chain ensures a frictionless web3 experience for users and developers alike.</p>
<p>This results in a terraformed world of universal (fully interoperable) applications for web3. In this paradigm, instead of being a user of "Uniswap on Ethereum," "Uniswap on Polygon," or "Uniswap on Arbitrum," a person simply becomes a <strong>user of Uniswap</strong>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/interop-spectrum#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>Interop is the end goal for ensuring that crypto apps arrive to mainstream users, no matter where they are from, or even if they get onboarded from web2.</p>
<p>Seeing interop as a spectrum helps us realize that it’s a problem that we have iteratively solved. Just like how web1 evolved to web2 and then to web3 to fix the problems of its predecessor.</p>
<p>Solving this is within our reach and thus the dream of enabling true interoperability from any app of any chain to any user of any chain.</p>
<p>Let’s build this future together, let’s build a better, more functional web3… and let’s build Universal / Fully Interoperable Apps!</p>
<p>It’s about time anyway 💪</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Interop</category>
            <category>Intent Solvers</category>
            <category>Bridges</category>
            <category>Deep dives</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing Push Chain Devnet Drop Points Program S2]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Introducing Push Chain Devnet Drop Points Program S2]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Introducing the Push Points Program S2" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-52992d3ad9e898f95dfc96818819cc68.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The announcement you’ve been eagerly waiting for is here!</p>
<p>Say Hello to <a href="https://portal.push.org/rewards" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet Drop Points Program S2!</a></p>
<p>The Devnet Drop Points Program leads to one of many upcoming Gratitude Drops scheduled to give back to our amazing Push Chain community as we collectively turbo charge our way towards the Push Chain Mainnet 🚀</p>
<p><em><strong>How do I participate in Devnet Drop Points Program?</strong></em></p>
<p><em><strong>Who is this drop eligible for?</strong></em></p>
<p><em><strong>Does the Devnet Drop Points Program benefit Points Program S1 participants?</strong></em></p>
<p><em><strong>How awesome is Push Chain?</strong></em></p>
<p>This guide entails all the required details for you to kick start your Universal Appverse journey with Push!</p>
<p><em>Don’t skip the extra perks section at the end!</em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-the-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program">What is the Push Chain Devnet Drop Points Program?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2#what-is-the-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is the Push Chain Devnet Drop Points Program?" title="Direct link to What is the Push Chain Devnet Drop Points Program?">​</a></h2>
<p>The <a href="https://portal.push.org/rewards?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=push_rewards" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet Drop Points Program</a> - is an Incentivized Devnet Program tied together with Push Points Program S2 - enabling users to earn Push Points in exchange for Airdrops for exploring the Early Ecosystem apps of Push Devnet.</p>
<p>Points Earned will unlock your eligibility for the Push Chain Token Airdrop, post Push Chain Mainnet.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="how-do-i-get-started-and-what-are-the-rules">How do I get started and what are the rules?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2#how-do-i-get-started-and-what-are-the-rules" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How do I get started and what are the rules?" title="Direct link to How do I get started and what are the rules?">​</a></h2>
<p>Quite Straightforward..</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Join the program at <a href="https://portal.push.org/rewards?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=push_rewards" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://portal.push.org/rewards</a></strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Connect using Push Wallet</strong></p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><em>Push Wallet is an in-browser wallet, which opens in a new tab.Thus, no downloads required.</em>
<em>You can connect using your existing Solana, EVM wallets to it - OR - Simply Login via Google &amp; Email.</em></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>
<p><strong>Validate your socials (X &amp; Discord)</strong> <em>(we hate bots🤖, we love fair play🤝)</em></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Tweet about Push Chain</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>You’re all set!</strong></p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Now…..</p>
<p><strong>Dive into the realm of Push’s Universal Apps like</strong>:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://email.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Any Chain Mail</a> - Your wallet address = your email id.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Transaction Simulator</a> - Send superfast txns on Push Chain - from any chain!</li>
<li><a href="https://rumors.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rumors</a>  - Share Secrets, No sign up, no personal data, vote on spicy rumors.
&amp; 4. SURPRISE APP (revealing soon!)</li>
</ol>
<p>Use these apps, perform actions (gasless + no money involved) and earn XP and Multipliers the more you level.</p>
<p><strong>There are 50 levels per app. The more you use an app, the more levels you climb, the more XP and Multipliers you earn and thus - higher you rank in the Leaderboard.</strong></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="whats-special-about-push-chain-devnet-universal-apps">What’s special about Push Chain Devnet Universal Apps?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2#whats-special-about-push-chain-devnet-universal-apps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What’s special about Push Chain Devnet Universal Apps?" title="Direct link to What’s special about Push Chain Devnet Universal Apps?">​</a></h3>
<p>These apps are Universal in nature.</p>
<p>Meaning…</p>
<p>These apps have the ability to support users from any wallet, belonging to any chain - with ZERO Friction!!</p>
<p>For instance - With <a href="https://email.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Anychain Email</a> - a Solana user can instantly send mails to an Ethereum user - instantly, with 0 gas fees!!</p>
<p>All thanks to Push Chain’s Chain Abstraction and Full Stack Interoperability!</p>
<p><em><strong>For nerds - here’s a detailed read: <a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Innovations By Push Chain</a></strong></em></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="who-does-the-devnet-drop-points-program-benefit">Who Does the Devnet Drop Points Program Benefit?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2#who-does-the-devnet-drop-points-program-benefit" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Who Does the Devnet Drop Points Program Benefit?" title="Direct link to Who Does the Devnet Drop Points Program Benefit?">​</a></h2>
<p>Short Answer - Everyone!</p>
<p>Which also includes:</p>
<p>1️⃣ S2 Program Participants (of course!)</p>
<p>2️⃣&nbsp;S1 Program Graduates (Push protocol users)</p>
<p>3️⃣&nbsp;And EVERYONE who’s truly part of Push Chain’s Vision and its journey to Mainnet!</p>
<p>….</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="note-for-s1-participants"><strong>💡NOTE For S1 Participants:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2#note-for-s1-participants" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to note-for-s1-participants" title="Direct link to note-for-s1-participants">​</a></h3>
<p>Claim an exclusive headstart boost <strong>20k points + 4x Multiplier</strong> just by logging in with the same socials &amp; wallet used in S1.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="extra-perks">Extra Perks:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2#extra-perks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Extra Perks:" title="Direct link to Extra Perks:">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>⚡️ Multipliers:</strong></p>
<p>Multipliers allow users to boost their Points by performing special activities. For e.g. if you have 100 points, after earning a 2x Multiplier, you will now have 200 Points. Multipliers also apply to any points earned after activating the Multiplier making it a permanent feature.</p>
<p>The best part,</p>
<p><strong>Multipliers are additive</strong>. A 2X + 2X Multiplier will make the account multiplier 4X. Collect more multipliers to earn mega rewards.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>✅ Daily Reward CheckIns:</strong></p>
<p>Users can also check-in daily on <a href="https://portal.push.org/rewards?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=push_rewards" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Points Portal</a> to claim points. Check-in for 7 days to earn bonus points.</p>
<p>→ Check in daily at <a href="https://portal.push.org/rewards?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=push_rewards" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">portal.push.org</a> to earn <strong>bonus 5,500 Points!</strong></p>
<p>→ Use Devnet Apps Daily to earn an additional <strong>1000 XPs boost.</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>🤝 Referrals:</strong></p>
<p>Onboard your loved ones to the S2 program &amp; earn <strong>+12%</strong> of any Points your invites earn and <strong>+2%</strong> of any Points your invitee’s invites earn.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-is-push-chain-awesome">Why is Push Chain Awesome?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/introducing-push-chain-devnet-drop-points-program-s2#why-is-push-chain-awesome" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why is Push Chain Awesome?" title="Direct link to Why is Push Chain Awesome?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps, powered by&nbsp;<strong>Chain Abstraction</strong>. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain that allows developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><strong>Push Chain's Superpowers Include:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Complete Wallet and Fee Abstraction</li>
<li>Support for Any Chain Tx (Solana, Eth, EVM, or non-EVM)</li>
<li>True Scale and Universal Smart Contracts</li>
<li>Consumer tx (unordered) and Traditional tx (ordered)</li>
<li>Sub-second finality</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<p><strong>⚡️READY, SET, EARN!</strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://portal.push.org/rewards?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=push_rewards" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://portal.push.org/rewards</a></strong></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Push Points</category>
            <category>Rewards</category>
            <category>Announcements</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing Push Chain Tokenomics]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Tokenomics - Details and Deepdive]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Tokenomics" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-21a999aac2a05aa234e58392f08294d0.webp" width="1920" height="1080" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="overview">Overview<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#overview" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Overview" title="Direct link to Overview">​</a></h2>
<p>In late 2024, the Push community voted to approve the launch of Push Chain, a shared state layer 1 blockchain designed to enable the development and scale of universal applications.</p>
<p>Push Chain is a purpose-built layer that connects L1s, L2s, and L3s with near-instant finality and true scalability, which solves the fundamental issue with web3 applications: fragmentation. With the successful voting of the governance proposal, the Push Chain mission is now on its way toward building <strong>any chain, any user, and any app.</strong></p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-caution admonition_xJq3 alert alert--warning"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 16 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M8.893 1.5c-.183-.31-.52-.5-.887-.5s-.703.19-.886.5L.138 13.499a.98.98 0 0 0 0 1.001c.193.31.53.501.886.501h13.964c.367 0 .704-.19.877-.5a1.03 1.03 0 0 0 .01-1.002L8.893 1.5zm.133 11.497H6.987v-2.003h2.039v2.003zm0-3.004H6.987V5.987h2.039v4.006z"></path></svg></span>caution</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>The Push Chain token is not live, nor is any presale live. The Push Chain token is not yet named. The migration from Push Protocol $PUSH to the Push Chain token is not live.</p><p>Do not believe anyone offering early access or early migration to the Push Chain token. All communications regarding Push Chain will be announced simultaneously from official Push channels — <a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="X handle of Push Chain">Twitter / X</a>, <a href="https://discord.gg/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Discord of Push Chain">Discord</a>, <a href="https://t.me/epnsproject" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Telegram of Push Chain">Telegram</a>, <a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Push Website">Website</a>.</p></div></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-the-vision-of-push-chain">What is the Vision of Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#what-is-the-vision-of-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is the Vision of Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is the Vision of Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>All blockchains have proven particularly useful for specific apps and use cases. Bitcoin enabled smart money. Ethereum enabled innovations for DeFi. Solana enabled fast apps and meme culture. Several L2s and new L1s are targeting other areas of concern.</p>
<p>However, a blockchain that is purpose-built to enable chain abstraction and seamless interoperability in the space is still required. This chain would enable transactions from any chain (ETH, SOL, EVM or non-EVM) to power apps that can be used by <strong>any user —</strong> no matter their chain or wallet. This is the chain of <strong>Universal Apps</strong>. This is Push Chain!</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="built-on-innovation-to-eliminate-blockchain-isolation">Built on innovation to eliminate blockchain isolation!<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#built-on-innovation-to-eliminate-blockchain-isolation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Built on innovation to eliminate blockchain isolation!" title="Direct link to Built on innovation to eliminate blockchain isolation!">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Chain is revolutionary for both users and developers as it creates an environment for any developer to deploy their universal app in hours via a single universal smart contract deployment.</p>
<p>It also enables users to transact from the comfort, convenience, and choice of their ecosystem, no matter where the app resides.</p>
<p>Under the hood, this is achieved by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ability to do <strong>transactions from any chain</strong></li>
<li><strong>Fee &amp; Wallet Abstraction</strong> (universal wallet + guest wallet)</li>
<li><strong>Shared State</strong> (read data from other blockchain) 👀</li>
<li><strong>Generalised Programmable Solve</strong>r (enables acting on the data read from other chains)</li>
<li><strong>Universal Smart Contract</strong> (enables devs to deploy universal interop apps in hours)</li>
<li><strong>Shared App Experience</strong> (any user from any chain can access any app of any chain)</li>
</ul>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>info</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p><strong>Full Stack Interop (Universal Apps)</strong> = Universal Wallet + Generalized Programmable Solvers + Shared State + Universal Smart Contracts</p></div></div>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="where-does-push-chain-fit-in">Where does Push Chain fit in?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#where-does-push-chain-fit-in" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Where does Push Chain fit in?" title="Direct link to Where does Push Chain fit in?">​</a></h3>
<p>Push chain fits <strong>every project…</strong> <strong>on every chain!</strong></p>
<p>- <strong>It allows developers</strong> from any chain to create seamless full interop apps that can be used from any chain, via any wallet.<br>
- <strong>It allows users</strong> the freedom to interact with the wallet of their choice or have a seamless signless experience via Push Universal Wallet with social login.<br>
- <strong>It allows shared app experiences</strong> where users of all chains can come together and engage with Omni DeFi, Omni gaming, Omni NFT, Omni Governance, etc.<br></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-can-be-built-on-push-chain">What can be built on Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#what-can-be-built-on-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What can be built on Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What can be built on Push Chain?">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Chain brings seamless interoperability and unifies all L1s, L2s, &amp; L3s and therefore is poised to become the playground of innovation and interop. You can build existing web3 use cases such as:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Primary use cases of Push Chain" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/usecasesmain-7bf3f161414466d0fcb388aebc850a92.webp" width="1600" height="888" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Or you can better web3 and create innovations:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Consumer use cases of Push Chain" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/consumerusecases-fb5a802dd9698e5f6eec1feb441e7bb3.webp" width="1600" height="888" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Or you can see some popular app examples and to take inspiration from:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Universal app use cases of Push Chain" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/appusecases-9fe86d3d9cad2e692b490a8d75c340da.webp" width="1600" height="881" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="-push-chain-tokenomics">👋 Push Chain Tokenomics<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#-push-chain-tokenomics" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👋 Push Chain Tokenomics" title="Direct link to 👋 Push Chain Tokenomics">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Push Chain Tokenomics" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/vestingpc-060f57f17be4b64981eaa404fabe5572.webp" width="1600" height="866" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="token-utility-and-functionality">Token Utility and Functionality<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#token-utility-and-functionality" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Token Utility and Functionality" title="Direct link to Token Utility and Functionality">​</a></h3>
<p>In the proposal, the Push Chain token is designed with multiple utilities that support the network's operation and growth.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Network Security</strong>: The token powers Push Chain’s Proof-of-Stake consensus mechanism through staking and slashing, ensuring the security and reliability of the network.</li>
<li><strong>Transaction Fees</strong>: The token serves as the primary method for network fees for transactions and app usage.</li>
<li><strong>Governance</strong>: Token holders gain voting rights to propose and decide on protocol changes, actively contributing to the chain’s future.</li>
<li><strong>Fee Abstraction</strong>: Push’s Fee+Solver contract is used to enable users of any chain (whether ETH, SOL), etc to pay for gas via native token. A portion of the fee collected will be swapped and burned for Push Chain native token.</li>
<li><strong>Incentives</strong>: The token supports an ecosystem of rewards for validators, users, and community members through fee sharing and a reward system.</li>
</ol>
<p>Push Chain adopts a dynamic supply model, which is used among popular chains (like Ethereum and Solana). Post mainnet, new tokens for the chain would be mined solely for node rewards, relayer rewards, and other participants that are required for ensuring chain security, functionality, and decentralization needs.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="burn-and-deflationary-mechanism">Burn and Deflationary Mechanism<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#burn-and-deflationary-mechanism" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Burn and Deflationary Mechanism" title="Direct link to Burn and Deflationary Mechanism">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Chain has a couple of burn mechanisms owing to it being a Universal Blockchain.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Native Chain Burn</strong>: A part of the fees is always burned when native transactions are done on Push Chain.</li>
<li><strong>Cross Chain Burn</strong>: Using Fee Abstractions, a part of the fee collected on other blockchain’s native token (ETH, SOL) is swapped for Push Chain native token and burned.</li>
</ol>
<p>This ensures a deflationary blockchain design that burns tokens as the network and the transactions that happen on it grow. This allows the chain to achieve deflationary tokenomics design while still awarding the validators and other actors. This design enables the creation of an incentivized, sustainable long-term future for Push Chain and all its participants.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="migration-details">Migration Details<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#migration-details" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Migration Details" title="Direct link to Migration Details">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Chain is the result of years of learning from building the leading notification and communication protocol of web3, which was one of the first consumer apps for crypto.</p>
<p>Owing to this, apart from the airdrop allocated (see details below) to Push Chain users, creators, developers and ecosystem partners, <strong>there is also a migration drop reserved for the $PUSH holders</strong> (which was the native token of Push Protocol).</p>
<p><strong>For existing $PUSH token holders</strong>, the Push Chain tokenomics proposal allocates 15% of the total Push Chain token supply specifically for migration. The migration will occur at a ratio of <strong>1:15</strong>—meaning for each Push Protocol ($PUSH) token you hold, you'll receive 15 Push Chain tokens. For example, if you currently hold 40 $PUSH tokens, you'll receive 600 Push Chain tokens after migration.</p>
<p>The launch of Push Chain is designed to reward and incentivize prior Push Protocol ($PUSH) holders for their loyalty and contribution. The migration process for existing $PUSH token holders will work as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tokens will migrate at a 1:15 ratio (1 Push Protocol token = 15 Push Chain tokens).</li>
<li>Participants in the Push Chain migration will see 50% of their migrated tokens unlocked immediately, and an additional 50% unlocked after 3 months.</li>
<li>Token migrators will also benefit from a dedicated yield farming pool reserved for them. These rewards will be distributed to token migrators if they stake their migrated Push Chain tokens, to reward them for long-term contribution to the ecosystem.</li>
<li>For example, if you have 100 Push Protocol $PUSH tokens, you’ll receive 750 Push Chain tokens when you migrate and 750 Push Chain tokens after 3 months — for a total of 1,500 Push Chain tokens. You can choose to stake these tokens to get additional rewards from the Push Chain yield farming pool, distributed periodically.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Push Chain token migration will be open for 12 months after launch, after which any remaining tokens will go to the community and ecosystem reserve.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="airdrop-details">Airdrop Details<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#airdrop-details" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Airdrop Details" title="Direct link to Airdrop Details">​</a></h3>
<p>Additionally, the tokenomics proposal allocates 10% of the total Push Chain token supply for airdrops to past and present Push Protocol application users (notifications, messaging, chat). Along with new users, creators, developers, and ecosystem partners of Push Chain.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="token-distribution-details">Token Distribution Details<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-tokenomics#token-distribution-details" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Token Distribution Details" title="Direct link to Token Distribution Details">​</a></h2>
<p>The total supply of Push Chain tokens is proposed at <strong>10 billion</strong>, distributed as follows:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Push Chain Tokenomics" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/vestingpc-060f57f17be4b64981eaa404fabe5572.webp" width="1600" height="866" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Push Chain Tokenomics Vesting Details" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/vestingdetailspc-0db680646d1f04029a57322e8dfc830d.webp" width="1600" height="877" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<ol>
<li>Push Protocol $PUSH migrators have 50% of migrated tokens unlocked at TGE, followed by the remaining 50% after 3 months.</li>
<li>Airdrop distributions begin at TGE, but will happen over the course of multiple seasons.</li>
<li>Core Contributors have a 12-month delay, followed by 24-month vesting.</li>
<li>Push Labs Treasury has a 36-month vesting.</li>
<li>Investors have 24-month linear vesting.</li>
<li>Community and Ecosystem Reserves has a 13.5% unlock at TGE, followed by 36-month vesting.</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Tokenomics</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Gaia Network]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-gaia</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-gaia</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Scroll]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Gaia " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-4d42229e4378f28c2587e2000072ee62.webp" width="1920" height="1080" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>It’s time to make on-chain AI Agents go Universal!
Push Chain is joining forces with Gaia Network to make chain abstracted AI Agents accessible to anyone via any chain, any wallet.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-gaia">What is Gaia?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-gaia#what-is-gaia" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Gaia?" title="Direct link to What is Gaia?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://www.gaianet.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gaia</a> is an autonomous agents marketplace that enables anyone to build, deploy and utilize AI agents with unique expertise, &amp; personalized capabilities.</p>
<p>As a decentralized computing network, Gaia powers its nodes with every essential component - required to seamlessly configure and operate AI agents.</p>
<p>Gaia node includes - a powerful cross-platform runtime, fine-tuned LLM, vectorDB and embedding models, prompt manager and much more.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-gaia#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps, powered by Chain Abstraction. Push is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain that allows developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><strong>Push Chain's Superpowers Include:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Consumer tx (unordered) and Traditional tx (ordered)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Any Chain Tx (Solana, Eth, EVM, or non-EVM)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sub-second finality** &nbsp;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>True Scale and Universal Smart Contracts</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Wallet and Fee Abstraction</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="-what-does-this-mean-for-gaia-and-push-chain-users">👥 What does this mean for Gaia and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-gaia#-what-does-this-mean-for-gaia-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥 What does this mean for Gaia and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥 What does this mean for Gaia and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Interact with Universally operable AI Agents</strong></p>
<p>With Push’s Universal capabilities - users operating AI agents built on Gaia can conveniently perform autonomous tasks across any chain!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️-what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️ What does this mean for Builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-gaia#%EF%B8%8F-what-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️ What does this mean for Builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️ What does this mean for Builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Develop Universally Operable AI Agents</strong></p>
<p>With Gaia and Push, Builders can create borderless ai agents - that can perform financial, mixed financial and consumer read/write operations across any chain in an autonomous manner.</p>
<p><strong>Build Agents with Universal Identities</strong></p>
<p>Leveraging PushID ( A unified user identity by Push Chain that spans across every user wallet, both EVM and non-EVM). Instances of Gaia agents can carry a unified identity that aggregates their activity across all chains - simplifying agent tracking, history collection and analysis.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="usecase-unlock">🔓Usecase unlock<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-gaia#usecase-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓Usecase unlock" title="Direct link to 🔓Usecase unlock">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Cross Chain AI agents with autonomous intelligence</strong></p>
<p>Having the ability to execute actions between any chains, irrespective of their virtual machine design, with the power of Push Chain’s Universal Smart Contracts and Shared State ledger.</p>
<p><strong>Unified Data Layers for AI Agents</strong></p>
<p>Data Layers like <a href="https://www.0xscope.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Oxscope</a> can utilize Push Chain’s shared state settlement layer to read transactions across chains in a unified manner.</p>
<p><strong>Chain Agnostic Autonomous Actions</strong></p>
<p>Autonomous agents like <a href="https://github.com/elizaOS/eliza" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eliza</a> can extend its support for Push Chain, opening opportunities for chain-abstracted interoperable communications and actions.</p>
<p>Example: rebalance a user's DeFi positions on Ethereum, list NFTs on Polygon, and communicate status updates to the user via a messaging app on another chain, all through one unified settlement layer</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-gaia#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a>&nbsp;to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Want to build on Push Chain? Explore the docs and example snippets here →&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/docs/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Docs</a></li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Scroll]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-scroll</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-scroll</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Scroll]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Scroll " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-acf09114aeeb70e7cd9011d2fb9ccc26.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Scroll is coming to Push Chain!</p>
<p>It’s time to make EVM’s Open Economy Universally Accessible to anyone from anywhere, be it evm or non-evm.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-scroll">What is Scroll?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-scroll#what-is-scroll" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Scroll?" title="Direct link to What is Scroll?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://scroll.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Scroll</a> is an EVM compatible - Layer 2 Scaling Solution. At a finer level, Scroll is a zkEvm Rollup - that executes and publishes transactions to Ethereum in bundles, which then can be proved with minimum compute requirements while preserving transaction privacy using Zero Knowledge technology.</p>
<p>Scroll is a byte-code equivalent zkevm that closely emulates EVM, enabling almost identical development and user experiences to Ethereum.</p>
<p>Developing on Scroll is super easy for Ethereum Devs :</p>
<ul>
<li>Solidity, Vyper, and Huff work out of the box</li>
<li>No re-auditing necessary</li>
<li>Most existing tooling is inherited</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-scroll#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps, powered by <strong>Chain Abstraction</strong>. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain that allows developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><strong>Push Chain's Superpowers Include:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Consumer tx (unordered) and Traditional tx (ordered)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Any Chain Tx (Solana, Eth, EVM, or non-EVM)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sub-second finality** &nbsp;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>True Scale and Universal Smart Contracts</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Wallet and Fee Abstraction</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-scroll-and-push-chain-users"><strong>👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Scroll and Push Chain Users?</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-scroll#what-does-this-mean-for-scroll-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-scroll-and-push-chain-users" title="Direct link to what-does-this-mean-for-scroll-and-push-chain-users">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Explore non-evm without leaving Scroll</strong></p>
<p>Scroll users can interact with DApps across Solana, Aptos, Bitcoin L2s or any other non evms via Push’s Shared Settlement Layer. All, without manually bridging funds, installing and learning complex wallet systems and ever-leaving Scroll’s Ecosystem Comfort.</p>
<p><strong>Universal  Identity</strong></p>
<p>Exploring an open and universal web3 economy requires a universal passport.</p>
<p>This is where Push ID makes a difference- Provides a universal identity system that seamlessly connects all their wallets (EVM and non-EVM) into one profile.
Enabling users to track their web3 activity, across Scroll, Ethereum, Solana or any other chain in a unified manner.</p>
<p>The opportunities with Push ID are endless:
Think about gated applications - where you’re universal passport gives you access based on your web3 repetition. Or  instances where an app requires you to KYC to prove cross-chain asset ownership.</p>
<p>Additionally, with this partnership - Developers get an opportunity to lean on Scroll’s decentralized prover network and work on fascinating new areas such as post-danksharding blob markets, hardware-friendly ZK algorithms and new ZK primitives. With Push Chain - Devs will be able to take these innovations one notch higher by unlocking the states of other layer 1s and layer 2s, in order to build truly scalable consumer-friendly apps.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-scroll#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build Apps that enable Txns from Any Chain</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain supports transactions from any wallet, regardless of the originating chain—be it Ethereum, Solana, or any other L1s, L2s or L3s.</p>
<p>Use <a href="https://push.org/docs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain’s Universal SDK</a> to bring these apps to life - opening doors to craft chain abstracted experiences.</p>
<p><strong>Build hyper-scalable consumer apps</strong></p>
<p>Using Scroll’s inherent scalability strength and Push Chain’s <strong>Sharded Storage and Parallel txn processing</strong> - Devs can build <em>hyperscalable consumer apps</em>  that can be executed with sub-second finality using Push’s  borderless &amp; stateless consumer txns.</p>
<p><em>This is the era of Consumer DApps thriving with millions of users!</em></p>
<p>Additionally, with this partnership - Developers get an opportunity to lean on Scroll’s decentralized prover network and work on fascinating new areas such as post-danksharding blob markets, hardware-friendly ZK algorithms and new ZK primitives. With Push Chain - Devs will be able to take these innovations one notch higher by unlocking the states of other layer 1s and layer 2s, in order to build truly scalable consumer-friendly apps.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="use-case-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-scroll#use-case-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Universally playable games:</strong>
MMORPG games like <a href="https://www.omnikingdoms.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Omnikingdoms</a> can support users from any non-evm chain supporting in game purchases, state transitions and much more.</p>
<p>Even Multiplayer games like roulette, casinos and RPG games on Scroll can utilize Push Chain to bring users across different chains to compete together in a unified manner.</p>
<p><strong>Universal NFTs:</strong></p>
<p><em>Shared state + universal smart contracts = true multi-chain magic!</em></p>
<p>Imagine launching Univeral NFT collections using launchpads like <a href="https://omnihub.xyz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Omnihub</a> and <a href="https://nfts2me.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NFTs2Me</a> seamlessly across different L1s which can be traded and transfered across any chain!</p>
<p><strong>Universal Privacy:</strong></p>
<p>ZK tech has solved one of the biggest problems plaguing today’s internet, i.e. the trade-off between privacy and transparency. We are fast moving towards a world where every bit of valuable user-data will be ZK proved. With the Push x Scroll partnership, this important primitive will become truly universal and can be integrated with cross-chain applications as well as liquidity.</p>
<p><strong>Chain Agnostic AI Agents:</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain’s universal shared state and Scroll’s open economy  pave the way for a new generation of chain-agnostic AI agents. These agents can perform autonomous operations in a borderless manner - unlocking a wide variety of financial, mixed financial, and non-financial use cases.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-scroll#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a>&nbsp;to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Want to build on Push Chain? Explore the docs and example snippets here →&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/docs/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Docs</a></li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Diamante]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Diamante]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Diamante " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-d82a44ec9d87776e8f640998b2476a5f.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain 🤝 Diamante</p>
<p>Push is proud to partner with Diamante - A high-speed, quantum-attack-resistant L1 to forge a unified shared app experience for both, retail and institutional users!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-diamante"><strong>What is Diamante?</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante#what-is-diamante" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-is-diamante" title="Direct link to what-is-diamante">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://www.diamante.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diamante</a> is a hybrid Layer1 blockchain that connects institutional and retail applications under one ecosystem with blazing-fast execution, quantum-proof security, and super smooth UX.</p>
<p>With extra emphasis on its chain’s security - Diamante employs quantum-resistant algorithms to fortify its network against quantum threats!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps, powered by <strong>Chain Abstraction</strong>. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain that allows developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-diamante-to-push-chain">Bringing Diamante to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante#bringing-diamante-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Diamante to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Diamante to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-diamante-and-push-chain-users">👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Diamante and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante#what-does-this-mean-for-diamante-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Diamante and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Diamante and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Universally accessible on-chain institutions</strong></p>
<p>Institutions thriving on Diamante can unlock a chain-less business experience that helps them to transact, and operate with its customers/clients in a chain-abstracted manner.</p>
<p>Thus, removing the need for any complex compliance measures for cross-chain transactions. All without leaving the ecosystem comfort offered by the Diamante chain.</p>
<p><strong>Unified web3 experiences</strong></p>
<p>As a universal settlement layer - Push Chain users belong to multiple L1, L2s and L3s - be it EVM or non-EVMs like Aptos and Solana.</p>
<p>With Push Chain - users from these wide varieties of chains can explore the rich Diamante Ecosystem and send transactions to any Diamante Apps without navigating multiple networks or managing multiple wallets - with zero or minimal learning curve!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build super abstracted - shared settlement institutional and consumer DApps</strong></p>
<p>With shared settlement capabilities of Push Chain and Diamante - devs can build apps with powerful chain, fee and wallet abstraction capabilities - allowing transactions from any chain with near-instant finality.</p>
<p><strong>Build universally compliant consumer and mixed financial apps</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain introduces a new transaction type: <strong>‘consumer transactions’</strong>, where transaction ordering is not essential.</p>
<p>Why consumer tx?</p>
<p>Two major challenges hinder the scalability of consumer web3 apps:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chain Fragmentation-</strong> User bases are over-diversified across hundreds of chains, impeding user growth, UX and retention.</li>
<li><strong>Scalability constraints-</strong> Most chains process transactions in a strictly ordered manner, which imposes unnecessary constraints on apps that don’t rely on transaction ordering.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is where Push Chain’s Consumer Tx feature enables non-financial and consumer applications to operate with lightning-fast speed and hyper-scalability. Push Chain enables these apps to manage millions of users seamlessly across any chain environment.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="use-case-unlock"><strong>🔓&nbsp;Use case unlock:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante#use-case-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to use-case-unlock" title="Direct link to use-case-unlock">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unified Compliance Solutions-</strong> Crypto KYC Services like <a href="https://www.notion.so/17c188aea7f480fca231d69da721208d?pvs=21" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">HyperSign</a> can unlock wider distribution by providing their Crypto KYC services across any app belonging form any chain (evm or non-evm) by using Push’s Shared Settlement and Consumer Txn support.</p>
<p><strong>Universal GameFi-</strong> - Game Studios and Launchpads like <a href="https://www.notion.so/17c188aea7f480fca231d69da721208d?pvs=21" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mon Protocol</a> and <a href="https://isotopic.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Isotopic</a> can leverage Push Chain to build <strong>Universally Playable On-chain Games (UPOGs)</strong>, supporting users from any chain with the power of Universal Smart Contracts and Any chain Consumer Transactions - providing sub-second finality and any chain compatibility.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3">🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?" title="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-diamante#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow &nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a> to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Want to build on Push Chain? Explore the docs and example snippets here → <a href="https://push.org/docs/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Docs</a></li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/?utm_source=pushblog&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=pcgov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is Push Chain Another L1?]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/another-l1</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/another-l1</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Learn why Push Chain is built different]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Is Push Chain Another L1?" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-f4b365f77610bf81ff34771f6320c687.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-curious">The Curious<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/another-l1#the-curious" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Curious" title="Direct link to The Curious">​</a></h3>
<p>At crypto conferences I'm often asked how our approach at Push differs from other L1 projects. And at normie gatherings I'm asked which crypto is best for starters. Until now I used to think of these as two distinct questions coming from two distinct audiences, i.e. technical and non-technical. My responses were conditioned by this assumption. At the former I used to talk about our '<a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">shared state</a>' approach and how it is distinguishable from interoperability (more on that below and in subsequent articles). And to the normies I used to suggest that starting-points can be subjective because different projects are trying to do different things. Some for instance are building reliable forms of decentralised cash, while others are trying to democratise the financial system. Still others are trying to get social media out of the hands of big tech, and a lot of them are just having fun.</p>
<p>The problem with my approach was that it left out the real audience: the 'web3 curious'. This is a huge category which cannot be ignored, and I'm going to define it rather broadly as those people who have heard of crypto and played around with it a bit <a href="https://push.org/blog/why-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">without digging deeper</a>. You could say the real reason why they got into the whole thing was quick money. But in order for that to happen I feel they must <em>at some level believe</em> in the larger crypto project. To put it differently, <em>even if</em> they thought they were playing around with 'magic internet money', some part of them must have known that the magic was real (or had the potential of <em>becoming</em> real). That's the part of the collective psyche we need to reach.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ecosystem-abstraction">Ecosystem Abstraction<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/another-l1#ecosystem-abstraction" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ecosystem Abstraction" title="Direct link to Ecosystem Abstraction">​</a></h3>
<p>To return to the earlier point, I now feel that both audiences were asking me the same thing in different ways, i.e. <em>which ecosystem?</em> It's often said that a few years in crypto equals decades in the real world. To me this was never a throwaway sentiment but a profound ground-truth about our industry. When crypto was just starting out people used to debate whether it had 'inherent value' and whether it could ever become 'money'. Those questions have more or less disappeared today because most people have concluded that it does. Thanks to the SEC, the critical regulatory question today seems to be whether a particular crypto is a <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/digital-assets/2023/08/14/how-the-secs-charge-that-cryptos-are-securities-could-face-an-uphill-battle/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">security</a> or not. But of course it took humanity more than a thousand years to get from money to finance.</p>
<p>The lesson we can draw from this is that the forms of '<a href="https://medium.com/@adamnite/a-history-of-crypto-tribalism-11f9f9c5cbaf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">crypto tribalism</a>' we see today are comparable to <a href="https://www.wideopenspaces.com/native-american-totem-animals-origins-totem-poles-meaning/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">historical tribes</a> who hitched their identity to particular totems and money-objects. We took a giant leap when we adopted the human-first-tribe-later perspective. This allowed us to <em>abstract away particular ecosystems</em> and develop a more global outlook. Of course I am not suggesting that our particular cultural attributes disappeared with modernity, but rather that they were preserved within a more <a href="https://www.notion.so/Is-Push-Chain-another-L1-188188aea7f4801a8e5dc22d0c20e0f3?pvs=21" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">'universal' wrapper</a>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="cities--bridges">Cities &amp; Bridges<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/another-l1#cities--bridges" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Cities &amp; Bridges" title="Direct link to Cities &amp; Bridges">​</a></h3>
<p>Simply put, ‘ecosystem abstraction’ is my general response to both questions posed above. I see it as <a href="https://thenetworkstate.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">an ongoing process</a> that Push aims to accelerate -- comparable perhaps to globalisation which aims to overcome national boundaries -- rather than as a quantifiable end state. What this means in concrete terms is that we are building a non-competitive L1 that does not distinguish between normies and crypto-natives.</p>
<p>Why, you wonder? Because it’s the <a href="https://push.org/blog/what-is-consumer-crypto-and-why-does-it-matter/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">final ecosystem barrier</a> standing between us and mass adoption. Moreover, it allows us to approach technical problems with a fresh perspective. Consider interoperability. By and large it means two things in crypto: unifying different chains via bridges and developing common standards. The first is a necessary, but more importantly, <em>organic</em> approach because bridges between two parts of a city aren't built unless there is significant traffic between them. The trouble right now is that the two sides are run by different municipal authorities, and every time you have to cross between them you must take fresh authorisation from an agent who operates a toll booth.</p>
<p>Now if this were a real city the citizens would petition the Mayor and get things changed. They would most likely ask for a monthly ticket and some sort of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FASTag" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">‘fast tag’</a> on their cars which could automatically calculate and deduct the toll-fees from their wallets. But crypto is decentralised and there is no Mayor to petition. So for us the only solution is to get both municipal authorities to agree on a system for quick and trustworthy communication. Moreover, if both sides have different ticketing systems then they would need to develop a common ticketing standard which is mutually recognised.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="necessity-led-invention">Necessity-led invention<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/another-l1#necessity-led-invention" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Necessity-led invention" title="Direct link to Necessity-led invention">​</a></h3>
<p>In crypto, the reason why interoperability is an especially difficult problem to crack is because it requires unbroken coordination and synchronicity between different ecosystems. With every new chain that is added to the mix, the patchwork expands and becomes more unwieldy. It is therefore legitimate for people to wonder whether we are ‘another L1’ which is ultimately going to increase this messiness.</p>
<p>The short answer is no: Push is not building its own separate municipality in its own corner of the city. Instead we are building systems (such as <a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">solver networks and fees quotas</a>) through which bridge-operators can communicate and coordinate. Imagine if a <a href="https://www.notion.so/189188aea7f480faaba5f80052406759?pvs=21" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tourist</a> was visiting the city and wanted to pass through three different bridges in a single drive. The bridge-operators would need to reach consensus on various things including: (a) does he have enough money for all the tolls? (2) is he a legitimate (non-malicious) actor, and (c) has he received necessary permissions from the respective Mayors of the source and destination cities, etc.</p>
<p>In the context of crypto these steps are reducible to verifiable cross-chain communications, and because Push has been working on this problem from its origin, it is uniquely positioned to create such a system. In other words, the move towards Push Chain was driven by the realisation that we had to do our bit to move the needle on interoperability, not in order to create our own fragmented ecosystem.</p>
<p>Personally, what is most exciting for me is thinking about the new use-cases that such a cross-chain-communication-grid unlocks. Imagine if an <em>Aurory</em> or <em>Star Atlas</em> player is able to leverage Uniswap or Polymarket through in-game intent solvers, or if an artist is able to launch NFTs of their work simultanously across Opensea, Magic Eden and Jpg.store. Here's how my friend and colleague Zee put it in a recent conversation: "we're trying to build systems where people can use their favourite apps on their favourite chains without friction or second thought."</p>
<p>Yes it's an ambitious road, but we're determined.</p>
<p>LFPush!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push</category>
            <category>Chain</category>
            <category>Insights</category>
            <category>Vision</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Fuse]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Fuse]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Fuse " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-fe8d0c46f15ac254417825ae02e736ef.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Wondering how businesses can unlock Universal On-chain experiences?</p>
<p>Look no further!
Push Chain is joining forces with the Fuse Network to transform the way enterprises and users transact, operate, and flourish in the ever-expanding web3 economy.</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for Fuse and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-fuse-network">What is Fuse Network?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#what-is-fuse-network" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Fuse Network?" title="Direct link to What is Fuse Network?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://www.fuse.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fuse</a> is an Ethereum compatible public blockchain built for businesses and developers to access  web3 tech and secure, verifiable global payments.</p>
<p>Focusing on UX, ease of operation, accessibility and scalability, Fuse is built to onboard all types of enterprise users, from Web2 companies that want to integrate blockchain functionality into their apps, to Web3-native projects.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-fuse-to-push-chain">Bringing Fuse to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#bringing-fuse-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Fuse to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Fuse to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-fuse-and-push-chain-users">👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Fuse and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#what-does-this-mean-for-fuse-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Fuse and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Fuse and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Borderless On-chain Business Txns</strong></p>
<p>Enabling on-chain transactions, whether monetary or non-monetary - between businesses from entirely different blockchain ecosystems is a complex process, burdened by communication overhead, intricate bridging, and settlement challenges.</p>
<p>Push Chain abstracts this burden away by unifying the settlements of any EVM and non-evm chains - providing Fuse users a super smooth and quick any-chain transaction experience without leaving the Fuse ethos.</p>
<p><strong>Unified Invoicing and Accounting</strong></p>
<p>Enterprise apps on Fuse Chain can leverage Push Chain’s universal identity solution, Push ID, to track and monitor spending and invoicing across addresses in a unified manner by linking them to Push ID.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build Universally Abstracted Enterprise Apps</strong></p>
<p>With shared settlement capabilities of Push Chain  - devs can build enterprise apps with powerful chain, fee and wallet abstraction capabilities - allowing transactions from any chain with near instant finality.</p>
<p><strong>Attract Universal Users</strong></p>
<p>Fuse apps deployed on Push Chain can seamlessly open their doors to users from other EVM, and non-EVM chains and foster true shared experiences with Push Chain’s key innovations like - Shared State and Universal Smart Contracts.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="usecase-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Usecase unlock<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#usecase-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase unlock" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase unlock">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Universal Growth Tools</strong></p>
<p>Tools like <a href="https://midle.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Midle</a> can leverage Push Chain to create comprehensive growth campaigns combining both on-chain and off-chain tasks, verifiable and accessible from any blockchain. Users can participate using their preferred wallets, complete tasks on any chain, and receive instant rewards on their chosen network.</p>
<p><strong>Universal B2B / B2C Threat Monitoring Services</strong></p>
<p>Security monitoring solutions like <a href="https://www.ironblocks.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ironblocks</a> and utilize Push Chain for powering a universal security monitoring system that protects assets and transactions across all blockchain ecosystems simultaneously. For instance, if a security threat is detected for a cross-chain wallet on one chain, the system could instantly broadcast alerts and implement protective measures across all connected chains creating a unified security perimeter where threats are identified, tracked, and mitigated instantly.</p>
<p><strong>Universal AI Trading Agents</strong></p>
<p>AI agents can analyse and execute trades across both Fuse and other chains unifying liquidity for optimal arbitrage, yield and trading strategies.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3">🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?" title="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-fuse#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a>&nbsp;to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join&nbsp;<a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Stacks]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Stacks]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Morph " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-65d767c53bcbf237c02cded3be4d8976.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain is building with Stacks to unlock accessibility to Bitcoin apps from any chain, any app, and any wallet.</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for Stacks and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-stacks">What is Stacks?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#what-is-stacks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Stacks?" title="Direct link to What is Stacks?">​</a></h2>
<p>Built on top of Bitcoin, Stacks is a Layer 2 blockchain that brings general-purpose programmability to Bitcoin, enabling developers to create censorship-resistant apps while leveraging Bitcoin as a foundational settlement layer.</p>
<p>With its native language - ‘Clarity’ Stacks brings smart contracts to Bitcoin without altering its core, ensuring txns remain as secure &amp; irreversible as on BTC.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push-chain">What is Push Chain?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#what-is-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push Chain?" title="Direct link to What is Push Chain?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-stacks-to-push-chain">Bringing Stacks to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#bringing-stacks-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Stacks to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Stacks to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="-what-does-this-mean-for-stacks-and-push-chain-users">👥 What does this mean for Stacks and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#-what-does-this-mean-for-stacks-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥 What does this mean for Stacks and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥 What does this mean for Stacks and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Explore EVM and Non-EVM ecosystems without leaving Bitcoin</strong></p>
<p>With Push Chain, Stacks native users can explore and access applications across any blockchain ecosystem without learning new complex wallet systems, all while maintaining their Bitcoin-native experience on Stacks.</p>
<p><strong>Tap into the Trillion Dollar Bitcoin economy</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain's integration with Stacks opens up Bitcoin's massive liquidity and market presence for users from any blockchain ecosystem. Users can now participate in Bitcoin-native applications, access BTC-denominated assets, and engage with Stacks' growing ecosystem via their preferred blockchain and wallet.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Build Universal Bitcoin native Apps</strong></p>
<p>Apps deployed on Stacks and Push Chain can accept transactions from users belonging from any wallet belonging to any chain!</p>
<p><strong>Build&nbsp;<em>Superfast</em>&nbsp;Unified Apps</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain’s flexible architecture and its ability to allow transactions from any chain with sub-zero finality opens up a plethora of possibilities to build - Consumer, Financial, and Mixed Financial Applications.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="usecase-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#usecase-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Universal NFT Marketplaces</strong></p>
<p>NFT Marketplaces like <a href="https://gamma.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gamma</a> can open their gates for EVM and other Non-EVM NFT patrons enabling instant access, trade, and settlement!</p>
<p><strong>Borderless On-chain gaming</strong></p>
<p>Access Stacks’s rich gaming ecosystem including <a href="https://forceprime.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ForcePrime</a> and <a href="https://www.skullco.in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Skullco</a> via any EVM/Non-EVM chains - using Push’s Shared Settlement and Consumer Txns!</p>
<p><strong>Shared State DEX:</strong></p>
<p>DEXs like&nbsp;<a href="https://app.alexlab.co/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ALEX</a> can leverage Push Chain to provide access to Stacks and Bitcoin’s liquidity from users from any chain via their preferred wallets.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-web3">🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#what-does-this-mean-for-web3" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?" title="Direct link to 🌌&nbsp;What does this mean for Web3?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Unifying experiences by bringing users together.</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain isn’t here to replace networks or compete with any; instead, it aims to eliminate the fragmented state of Web3 by unifying settlement across all chains under one universal shared state, unlocking a seamless, interconnected Web3 experience.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-stacks#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a>&nbsp;to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a>*&nbsp;for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join&nbsp;<a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Morph]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Chain Joins Forces With Morph]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover image of Push Chain Join Forces With Morph " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/assets/images/cover-image-187da463e3ccd5f98628e886b390a7cd.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Chain is about to facelift the consumer app experience by teaming up with Morph L2!</p>
<p>Learn what this announcement means for Morph and Push Chain users, the use cases it unlocks, and how the collaboration benefits the greater Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-morph">What is Morph?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#what-is-morph" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Morph?" title="Direct link to What is Morph?">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://www.morphl2.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Morph</a> is a consumer app focused Ethereum Layer 2 solution that combines the best of Optimistic and ZK Rollups to provide a secure and super fast consumer experience.</p>
<p>With over 5M txns to date, Morph is rallying towards becoming the global consumer layer for empowering everyday on-chain usage for every internet user.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-push">What is Push?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#what-is-push" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Push?" title="Direct link to What is Push?">​</a></h2>
<p>Push Chain is a shared state blockchain for universal apps. It is a Proof of Stake (PoS) chain
built to allow developers to create universal apps and act as a shared settlement layer for multiple L1s, L2s, and L3s enabling transactions from any chain - any app and any user.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Explore more about Push Chain here</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bringing-morph-to-push-chain">Bringing Morph to Push Chain<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#bringing-morph-to-push-chain" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing Morph to Push Chain" title="Direct link to Bringing Morph to Push Chain">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-does-this-mean-for-morph-and-push-chain-users">👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Morph and Push Chain Users?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#what-does-this-mean-for-morph-and-push-chain-users" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Morph and Push Chain Users?" title="Direct link to 👥&nbsp;What does this mean for Morph and Push Chain Users?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Borderless consumer App experience</strong></p>
<p>Morph users can expand their on-chain usage beyond EVMs into Solana and other nonEVMs without ever leaving Morph’s ecosystem and UX comfort.</p>
<p><strong>Bring web2 normies to consumer crypto</strong></p>
<p>With Push Chain’s wallet and fee abstraction - everyday internet users (web2 users) can easily experience Morph’s consumer crypto ecosystem with minimal UX overhead - simply by using their social accounts like Google, Apple, Github, X and Discord.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="️what-does-this-mean-for-builders">👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#%EF%B8%8Fwhat-does-this-mean-for-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?" title="Direct link to 👷‍♂️&nbsp;What does this mean for builders?">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Build hyper scalable universal consumer apps</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain empowers developers to build truly universal applications that work seamlessly across all blockchains.</p>
<p>Push unlocks hyper-scalability for consumer and mixed consumer apps that have potential of handling millions of daily users with its innovative '<strong>Consumer Transactions</strong>' feature, enabling stateless and unordered processing of non-value transfers like social interactions, content sharing, and game actions.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/innovations-by-push-chain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Learn more about Push Chain’s Innovations here</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Read from any chain using shared settlement</strong></p>
<p>Push Chain's shared settlement layer provides a powerful foundation for apps on Morph to unlock shaped universal experiences with its ability to read state across any blockchain through its shared settlement layer. This means developers can focus on building engaging user experiences instead of managing complex cross-chain interactions.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="usecase-unlock">🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#usecase-unlock" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:" title="Direct link to 🔓&nbsp;Usecase Unlock:">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Universal ZK AI agents</strong></p>
<p>Privacy centric agentic networks like <a href="https://zypher.network/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Zypher</a> can leverage Push Chain to expand its AI agents reach to any blockchain. Ensuring a Universal, secure and verifiable execution without exposing sensitive data.</p>
<p><strong>Universal Predication Markets</strong></p>
<p>Prediction markets like <a href="https://soccersm.ai/ai-predictions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Soccersm</a> can not only house users from Morph but also from any other chains to collectively speculate on real-life events. Markets can aggregate liquidity from all chains simultaneously bringing more user traction and better yield opportunities.</p>
<p><strong>Universally Accessible token launchpads</strong> - Like <a href="https://muffun.fun/board" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Muffun</a> on Morph, can utilize the Push Chain and Push Wallet to enable users from any chain (EVM or non EVM) to effortlessly launch tokens on Morph without leaving their existing wallet systems or manually bridge funds.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="next-steps">Next Steps<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-1043/blog/push-chain-joins-forces-with-morph#next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Next Steps" title="Direct link to Next Steps">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li>Follow <a href="https://x.com/PushChain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@PushChain on X</a> to get the latest updates about Push Chain</li>
<li>Check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://whitepaper.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Whitepaper</a> for a detailed overview of the vision and the underlying technicalities.</li>
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://push.org/chain" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Website</a>&nbsp;to find a one-pager explanation of the vision.</li>
<li><a href="https://scan.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Devnet</a>&nbsp;is running live on Proof-of-Stake network validators, storage and archival nodes. The network already supports consumer transactions as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://simulate.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chain Simulate Tx</a>&nbsp;already provides a way for everyone to send tx from any chain using wallet abstraction.</li>
<li>For more questions join <a href="https://discord.com/invite/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Discord</a>. Our team would be glad to help you!</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Chain</category>
            <category>Partnerships</category>
            <category>Shared App Experience</category>
            <category>Any Chain Tx</category>
            <category>Universal Smart Contracts</category>
            <category>Shared State Blockchain</category>
            <category>Consumer Tx</category>
            <category>Parallel Validators</category>
            <category>Dynamic Sharding</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>