<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Push | The Communication Protocol of Web3 Blog</title>
        <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog</link>
        <description>Push | The Communication Protocol of Web3 Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What is consumer crypto and why does it matter?]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/what-is-consumer-crypto-and-why-does-it-matter</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/what-is-consumer-crypto-and-why-does-it-matter</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[ What is consumer crypto and why does it matter?]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of What is consumer crypto and why does it matter?" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-5c051971b8e8818cad8b2b87e99a3478.webp" width="1920" height="1080" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Bitcoin showed us that a decentralized monetary system can work in practice. Ethereum did the same for applications of all shapes and sizes. DeFi extended these principles, demonstrating a wide array of large-scale use cases for institutions and traders alike.</p>
<p>Now, as an industry, we’re on the precipice of our next major tipping point.</p>
<p>Consumer crypto.</p>
<p>It has exploded onto the scene over the past year and continues to dominate web3's zeitgeist. Conferences, podcasts, thought leaders, investors, and builders are all doubling down on its themes.</p>
<p>Major investors are prioritizing consumer crypto projects, particularly in social protocols, apps, and games, highlighting the industry's evolving focus and future direction.</p>
<p>Today, consumer crypto resembles the early days of online businesses during the dot-com boom. While many consumer-focused protocols and apps may be short-lived, a select few are poised to stand the test of time.</p>
<p>Currently, we're in the nascent stages of this boom.</p>
<p>Over the last 5 ETH Global hackathons, 80% of builders building with Push Protocol have chosen to ship projects focused on the consumer crypto niche. This is a major shift from 4 years ago when the same could be said for NFT marketplaces.</p>
<p>However, when you search “consumer crypto,” you get a wide variety of answers as to what it is, why it matters, and where it’s going.</p>
<p>There’s never been a better time than now to sift through the viewpoints and fully grok it.</p>
<p>In this post, we aim to:</p>
<p><em><strong>• Establish a clear definition of consumer crypto</strong></em></p>
<p><em><strong>• Explore the key reasons for its importance</strong></em></p>
<p><em><strong>• Comment on its future trajectory</strong></em></p>
<p>Industry professionals are thoroughly split on exactly how to define consumer crypto. Some suggest it all comes back to NFTs and their related token standards. Others say everything in the industry is moving towards consumer scale and has always been meant to go that route.</p>
<p>Others term it the movement focused on web3 apps that are purpose-built for everyday use by billions of people. While this is closer to the point, it doesn’t quite hit the nail on the head either.</p>
<p>Consumer crypto isn’t solely about web3 apps becoming household names.</p>
<p>It also refers to every layer of the stack being hyper-focused on providing novel experiences powered by the blockchain, smart contracts, tokenization, and everything in between. Zooming in, it could then be said that consumer crypto is the niche of the greater crypto industry that’s focused on building the future of all apps and services, powered by blockchain tech.</p>
<p>However, that’s still not quite it.</p>
<p>There’s something more that needs to be included because to scale all things crypto or more accurately, all things web3, to the masses, we need improvements to every level of the industry’s aggregated UX.</p>
<p>However, this concept needs to be simplified for the average person to grasp it. To establish a universal definition for consumer crypto, it's important to first identify and address what isn’t working.</p>
<p>Most consumers object to using crypto or anything related because they don’t see the need to switch to it. They return to the option they already trust and continue interacting within its walls.</p>
<p>This measure of how often users keep coming back to an app is called “stickiness,” and it’s something that web3 apps have yet to achieve on any comparable level to web2’s household names.</p>
<p>Think about why Slack is sticky, even for Web3 teams.</p>
<p>Once you pass a certain threshold of all-time messages sent, it becomes the standard for communication in your workplace. It doesn’t matter, in most cases, how many alternatives pop up. Your historical conversations and all the documents you’ve ever shared are stored in your team’s Slack.</p>
<p>What about Google Meet?</p>
<p>It’s a sticky progressive web app because it seamlessly integrates with your calendar and it just works. You can schedule a meeting in four clicks, counting inputting participating emails, and you don’t even have to have a Gmail to join one you’re invited to.</p>
<p>People keep coming back because, above all else, it’s intuitive to use and it doesn’t lock anyone out.</p>
<p>Consumer crypto, as a whole, is a vision to build out sticky apps that scale far beyond the web3 niche. All in all, the key goal is for them to be just as intuitive to use as their legacy counterparts and more attractive due to the new, on-chain-enabled features they champion.</p>
<p>To narrow down what this means, let's consider the rise of DeFi.</p>
<p>Since 2020, the success of protocols like Aave, Uniswap, and Maker has demonstrated, in practice, the power of transacting with minimal fees, globally, and without intermediaries. Truthfully, the term DeFi, stretches far beyond these protocols and their counterparts to all of crypto that deals in financial use cases. Even Bitcoin, for example, may be considered “DeFi,” when it is used to store value, or simply, to do business.</p>
<p>As institutions like Blackrock continue to buy in, that’s only becoming clearer by the day.</p>
<p>While both DeFi and consumer crypto are niches within the same industry, they have considerably different target markets. DeFi aims to provide the future financial system, piece by piece, to institutions, traders, and individuals.</p>
<p>Consumer Crypto is the vision of developing intuitive, sticky, and user-governed applications that leverage blockchain technology to deliver seamless, chain-abstracted experiences. These applications extend beyond financial services, enabling any user to engage with a diverse range of web3 applications for various purposes, fostering widespread adoption, and enhancing everyday digital interactions.</p>
<p>Below, we dig into why that needs to be done, and how we, as builders, can do it.</p>
<h1>Why does consumer crypto matter?</h1>
<p>The top hurdle for web3, as a whole, continues to be how inaccessible it is to the average person. To change that, we need to commit to radically improving how we onboard new users to our apps, how we seek to retain them, and what use cases we’re building for as well as supporting, through grants programs, hackathons, and otherwise.</p>
<p>Once we achieve this, it will become clear why consumer crypto is essential and why it represents the next paradigm shift for all consumer apps.</p>
<p><strong>Seamless Onboarding</strong></p>
<p>From approval signatures to bridging, to holding multiple tokens just for gas fees on different networks, to managing multiple wallets, <a href="https://push.org/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">and beyond</a>, web3 apps are rife with complexity. Changing the status quo requires unifying the user experience regardless of all these intricacies.</p>
<p>A commitment to learning from web2’s successes and failures is a good start.</p>
<p>Chain abstraction across the board, <a href="https://push.org/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">as we describe in a past post here</a>, takes us further.</p>
<p>Spinning up an account on a web3 app must be as easy if not easier than doing so on something like Facebook.  Simplicity needs to reign across the board in our approach to UX and we need to commit to benchmarking to leading legacy apps that are household names to ensure this happens. Moreover, putting all of the innovations that make this industry great on the back end does not mean hiding them.</p>
<p>Until all of this is achieved, onboarding will continue to be a major barrier to widespread adoption and the advent of an age in which on-chain apps supplant off-chain apps.</p>
<p><strong>Long-Term Retention</strong></p>
<p>Raising retention is a multi-sided problem. To retain users over the long-term, we must ensure better and seamless UX.</p>
<p>With web2’s common approaches to it and the unique features that web3 has in mind, it becomes easier to solve.</p>
<p>Think about the apps you have on your phone. What reminds you to check them? Push notifications. There’s a reason we still need them, even in this space. When done right, they’re one of the most effective methods that apps employ to retain users.</p>
<p>When your phone’s locked and you receive a push notification saying that you got a new message from a friend on an app, you check that app. It’s a reflex, in most cases. The same principle applies to web3. If you’re a trader and you get a push notification in your wallet that says the asset you’re tracking has reached the price you’re looking for, you’ll head to your account and trade that asset. Delegates for a DAO who receive the same sort of notification that a vote has begun will head to Snapshot or wherever that vote is being held to participate. The same goes for fans of a particular NFT artist who receive a ping that a new drop is live or fans of a podcaster who see that a new episode is live.</p>
<p>Push notifications are still key to keeping people engaged, even on-chain.</p>
<p>Beyond push notifications, numerous other methods for enhancing user retention exist, both predating web3 and emerging from it. The initial rise of NFTs has already shown the power of royalties, guaranteed in perpetuity, by smart contracts. Most legacy marketplaces and social media platforms offer only negligible profit-sharing, if any.</p>
<p>It’s the call for change we’ve seen since the earliest days of social media. Give us apps that prioritize the users, including creators, first, above all else.</p>
<p>Add in DAOs as well as the lego-like composability that smart contract-based applications have and you’re starting to get the picture as to how consumer crypto can do that. At present, both creators and general users lack meaningful upside in the apps they use daily. Any significant gains—monetary or otherwise—are subject to the whims of centralized entities.</p>
<p>User-led apps flip the status quo on its head, for the better.</p>
<p>If something isn’t working, it can be changed via a vote. Apps evolve based directly on what their communities want to see and any advertising that is done is opt-in.</p>
<p>Any revenue that’s generated goes both to the app itself, to keep the lights on and keep it scaling, and to its community, with the latter receiving the lion’s share.</p>
<p>Token-based incentives such as higher statuses and higher rewards based on longevity and participation further increase retention even further.</p>
<p><strong>Diversification of Use Cases</strong></p>
<p>However, none of the above matters if we, as an industry, can't demonstrate a stronger commitment to a broader range of use cases for our apps. Currently, the majority of existing web3 apps are DeFi-focused.</p>
<p>Consumer crypto aims to change that by providing intuitive, fun, sticky apps that rival those that are today’s leaders in the social media, gaming, and marketplace niches. Chain abstraction, <a href="https://push.org/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">cross-chain requests</a>, and <a href="https://push.org/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">related solutions</a> are making it easier than ever for that to happen.</p>
<p>As previously mentioned, through recent hackathons, we’re already able to see consumer apps leading the charge.</p>
<p>Consumer crypto matters because it’s the movement through which web3 expands its boundaries to the next billion users.</p>
<p>It’s the only way that we finally cross the chasm to being the standard-bearers for all online interaction instead of a tech-heavy alternative.</p>
<p>Once everyone in our industry shows commitment to that in practice, consumer crypto will become the dominant driving force for the industry’s move to expand crypto beyond finance and achieve widespread adoption.</p>
<h1>What’s the future of consumer crypto?</h1>
<p>Since Bitcoin's inception, we've advocated for a financial system and a world that levels the playing field more than ever before. Our apps need to strike a balance—easy to use, yet demonstrating these principles in action. We need more engaging, participatory, on-chain economies, of all shapes and sizes, embedded within enjoyable user interfaces.</p>
<p>This doesn’t require reinventing the wheel. Our next break-out moment may come from a team saying, <em>“How can we make a better Instagram with features and functionalities unique to this industry?”</em></p>
<p>That app would likely also be DAOified because you can’t have consumer crypto without governance by the people, for the people. Decentralized Governance, as an overarching model for our future social apps, aligns perfectly with the broader vision of consumer crypto, as it ensures apps evolve in a more participatory fashion than ever before. Web3-app users can have a direct say in how the app they’re using evolves as well as how it approaches key questions like compensation for creators, which is technically not possible in traditional web3 apps, where all control lies in the hands of the few.</p>
<p>Consumer crypto is the next <strong>Schelling</strong> point for our industry.</p>
<p>It's the driving force propelling us toward a future where web3 becomes the standard for all global consumers' online interactions. To travel further down that road, let’s start by building things on-chain that people beyond our sphere, legitimately want to use. Let’s also commit to making crypto easier to use than ever.</p>
<p>With that, we might reach an age in which a web3 app is just an app and a protocol is just a structure behind it.</p>
<p>An age of seamless interaction, on-chain,  where users no longer have to bother about the underlying chain behind their favorite applications.</p>
<p>Here at Push, we’re all aligned and focused on this vision.</p>
<p>If you're building in consumer crypto, then we're here to support you every step of the way. <a href="https://gov.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Reach out to us</a> and we’ll get you plugged in with our grants program.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Consumer Crypto</category>
            <category>Insights</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing Push Group Chats for Guilds!]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-group-chats-for-guilds</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-group-chats-for-guilds</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Introducing Push Group Chats for Guilds!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Introducing Push Group Chats for Guilds!" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-d36328c503cf7c4cb39188b553d9a3ec.gif" width="800" height="450" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>We're excited to announce that Guild-Gated Group Chats are now available on <a href="https://app.push.org/welcome" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push</a>.</p>
<p>Previously, Push’s Group Chats could only get gated by tokens or NFTs. Now any <a href="https://guild.xyz/explorer" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">guild</a> that is live on Guild.xyz can start a Push-based group chat. This moves us closer to our vision of ensuring customizable support for all forms of group conversations.</p>
<p>As we’ve always down, we’re not just talking the talk, we’re walking the walk as well, having launched the first guild-gated group chat on Push. Here is a quick step-by-step guide on how to join it:</p>
<ol>
<li>Visit to <a href="https://guild.xyz/push-protocol-463d3f" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://guild.xyz/push-protocol-463d3f</a></li>
<li>On this page, connect a wallet you own, like MetaMask.</li>
<li>Complete the tasks mentioned and once you’re done, you will gain the Push Builders’ role for deeper access to our Guild-Gated Group Chat.</li>
<li>Click the dedicated URL that’s now unlocked to join the chat.</li>
<li>Congratulations you just joined the Push Guild Gated Group Chat community. Don’t forget to drop a gm and connect with fellow other group chat members.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-guildxyz">What is Guild.xyz?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-group-chats-for-guilds#what-is-guildxyz" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Guild.xyz?" title="Direct link to What is Guild.xyz?">​</a></h3>
<p>Guild serves as the foundation for platform-agnostic access management to on-chain and off-chain communities. It enables the creation of portable memberships and social structures that encompass both on-chain and off-chain requirements, allowing for the development of distinct user journeys across various applications.</p>
<p><a href="https://push.org/docs/chat/build/conditional-rules-for-group/#guild-gated-group-example" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Here</a> are some examples of how you can create gated group chats for guilds at guild.xyz using GUILD type-in criteria.</p>
<p>Got any questions? Ping our team on <a href="https://discord.gg/pushprotocol" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">discord</a> and we'd be happy to help you.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Announcements</category>
            <category>Updates</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Protocol Monthly Updates: A Look Back at August]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Protocol Monthly Updates: A Look Back at August]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Cold Start Solutions: Scaling Consumer Crypto" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-4a2aea69ac3d40ae51566969e15f3b25.webp" width="1600" height="840" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>August was a notable month for Push, marked by significant milestones related to user engagement, feature development, and overall community growth. <a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Protocol</a> sent over 10.2 Million New Notifications in August, reaching a cumulative <a href="https://push.network/dashboard" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">242k subscribers</a>, showcasing substantial progress in user engagement, development, and community growth.</p>
<p>Here's a quick recap of all the exciting updates:</p>
<p>We're thrilled to announce that Push has reached a significant milestone: over 100 million notifications sent all-time. This is something that we've dreamed of since we began this journey to empower, enable, and unify web3 with native communication.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="100 Million Web3 Notifications" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image1-b27dde3015eedff556e29edd85753af6.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>As a key step towards achieving our mission of becoming the communication hub for all blockchains, we debuted one of our strongest protocol upgrades - <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1821607565920497857" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pre PIP 3: Cross Chain Requests</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cross-Chain Requests" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image2-57bca9ea6556a16c996e32f0d3721977.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Moreover, the <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0x03EAAAa48ea78d1E66eA3458364d553AD981871E" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BTC Tracker</a> channel surpassed 10,000 subscribers, after witnessing a massive 160% increase in opt-ins between May-August.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Bitcoin Tracker Channel" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image3-bf47a8c87dc6a7a727d24446b4f9e00d.webp" width="512" height="288" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>And that’s not all! The <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0xef6426D522CfE5B7Ae5dB05623aB0Ef78023dBe0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lens Protocol</a> channel experienced a significant surge in notifications starting in mid-August, surpassing 2 Million Notifications sent by the end of the month.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Lens Protocol Channel" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image4-977d40a04769ec63f6541ec208cab9c6.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="product-updates"><strong>Product Updates:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august#product-updates" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to product-updates" title="Direct link to product-updates">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Protocol’s <a href="https://app.push.org/welcome" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DApp</a> received several upgrades, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>the new channel creation page, send notification page, and channel dashboard being tested and deployed to production.</li>
<li>the expansion of support to two new chains: Base and Linea.</li>
<li>the deployment of support for adding a new chain alias to channels.</li>
<li>the testing of a new reward points program, which is going live soon.</li>
<li>the addition of new components to Push’s design system.</li>
<li>the addressing of priority bug fixes.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="backend-enhancements"><strong>Backend Enhancements:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august#backend-enhancements" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to backend-enhancements" title="Direct link to backend-enhancements">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>the implementation of a referral system for the Points Program.</li>
<li>the upgrade of platform scalability by migrating production servers from AWS to GCP.</li>
<li>the beginning of work on a tool that allows channels to automate notification logic without writing a single line of code.</li>
<li>the improvement of the response format for our API calls.</li>
<li>the kickoff of work on a custom delivery node that delivers notifications on different platforms like Discord/Telegram/email.</li>
<li>the development of a pricing model for channels to leverage the custom delivery node operations.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="smart-contracts"><strong>Smart Contracts:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august#smart-contracts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to smart-contracts" title="Direct link to smart-contracts">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>The community voted in favor of the <a href="https://gov.push.org/t/pre-pip-3-cross-chain-request-feature-in-push-smart-contracts-v3/1794" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cross Chain Request</a> (CCR) Feature Proposal, with 100% approval. Community feedback is being integrated into the feature’s development.</li>
<li>Phase 3 of the Cross Chain Request features development i.e. Security R&amp;D is currently under progress.</li>
<li>Completed the first implementation of Push Comm smart contracts for a NON-EVM chain, i.e., Starknet.</li>
<li>The contracts have been developed in the Cairo Smart contract language and have now been tested. The audit for the contract shall be completed in the next 3 weeks.</li>
</ul>
<p>Additionally, the Chat SDK saw improvements to response structure and priority bug fixes.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="partnership-updates"><strong>Partnership Updates:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august#partnership-updates" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to partnership-updates" title="Direct link to partnership-updates">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Protocol continues to expand its ecosystem through new collaborations:</p>
<ul>
<li>We're thrilled to be working with <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1826957066520383638" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QuickSwap</a>, a leading decentralized exchange (DEX) on Polygon PoS, Polygon zkEVM, and Dogechain to power push notifications when user liquidity goes out of range and when the user stops earning fees.</li>
<li><a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1826262728979436009" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CoinEasy</a>, a Korean web3 education social platform, joined forces with Push to integrate Push Chat for improved user communications and UX.</li>
<li><a href="https://unstoppabledomains.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Unstoppable Domains</a>, a long-time partner, leveraged Push Protocol for group chat support for <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1819715311253307611" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Africa Rare Metaverse</a>, <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1828077913008476232" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Farmsent</a>, <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1826580811237171237" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Deadfellaz</a>, and <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1825500051621212532" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tetherball</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1825543303116554260" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Outposts</a>, a bi-weekly web3 digest platform whitelisted Push Alpha Access Pass NFT holders to its invite-only digest community and earn program points that unlock token rewards.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ecosystem-highlights"><strong>Ecosystem Highlights:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august#ecosystem-highlights" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ecosystem-highlights" title="Direct link to ecosystem-highlights">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>We hosted an engineering-focused <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1821875116390613041" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">X space with Wormhole</a> on the upcoming CCR feature with <a href="https://wormhole.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wormhole</a>, whose NTT framework is key to Push's chain-agnostic vision.</li>
<li>Push Protocol founder Harsh Rajat shared his insights on Push Protocol's evolution, the web3 consumer landscape, and upcoming upgrades on the "<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LQmHFQ7IO18" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Colors of Web3 Entrepreneurship</a>" podcast.</li>
<li>In collaboration with <a href="https://www.tally.xyz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tally</a>, a governance optimization platform, we held a Twitter space on "<a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1821441276740346320" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Improving Decentralized Governance with Push and Tally.</a>”</li>
<li>Ian, our DAO and Governance lead was invited to speak on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zpqP_b-ch1A" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hipther Podcast Show</a> to share his experience working in web3 for almost a decade while also discussing the working mechanisms of Push DAO and the upcoming launch of Push Nodes.</li>
<li>Ian was also invited to the <a href="https://blog.amberdata.io/amberdata-podcast-feat-ian-leviness-head-of-grants-at-push-protocol?hss_channel=tw-876969251617112064" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Amberdata Podcast</a> to share his unique story, our core mission, &amp; how Push is solving for scaling decentralized communications.</li>
<li>Push and CoinEasy conducted a joint Twitter space with DAO Lead Ian and Seung Lee, the co-founder of CoinEasy discussing <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1826620569053286715" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Simplifying Web3 Journey with Push and CoinEasy</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-governance-and-community-updates"><strong>Push Governance and Community Updates:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august#push-governance-and-community-updates" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to push-governance-and-community-updates" title="Direct link to push-governance-and-community-updates">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>The community passed new guidelines to streamline the performance of our ambassador hubs.</li>
<li>Push Grants V3 reached 21 applications and continues to grow!</li>
<li>Our contributor base more than tripled from all-time highs and continues to grow by the day!</li>
<li>Carla, from the DAO Council, spoke at and judged the buildathon at <a href="https://x.com/EthereumUruguay" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ethereum Uruguay</a>.</li>
<li>SixtyKeys, another DAO Council member, earned a speaking spot at this year's ETH Safari in September.</li>
<li>The DAO launched weekly DAO thoughts, sharing practical tips on DAO building, with the end goal of expanding that effort into a podcast and more!</li>
<li>We knighted our 2nd <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1827295975389499604" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Chad Discord Role</a> winner, in lieu of identifying, recognizing, and incentivizing consistent community contributors.</li>
</ul>
<p>With Push Nodes launching soon, Zaryab, our Smart Contracts Lead, wrote a blog post - “<a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1828432624273981586" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Randomness in Push Nodes</a>” to educate our ecosystem and a wider audience on how Push Nodes leverage the principle of randomness to ensure optimal network fairness and censorship resistance.</p>
<p>Our DAO Lead also penned a post <a href="https://push.org/blog/cold-start-solutions-scaling-consumer-crypto/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">on solutions to the cold start problem</a> for web3 apps aiming to be platforms, marking our first foray into editorial content spanning the consumer crypto niche.</p>
<p>Furthermore, we’re excited to introduce a new initiative - “<a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1826313152176251142" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write for Push</a>” enabling anyone in the Push community to contribute to the protocol’s blog repository and help shape its voice. From the outset, this will focus on topics related to the existing Push ecosystem and its products.</p>
<p>With this multi-faceted shift in content and our tech, we’re setting ourselves up to be a true authority on the future of consumer applications at all levels.</p>
<p>Your continued support and enthusiasm fuel our commitment to push the boundaries of technology while building a supportive and diverse Web3 ecosystem.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="whats-coming-up"><strong>What’s coming up?</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-monthly-updates-august#whats-coming-up" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to whats-coming-up" title="Direct link to whats-coming-up">​</a></h3>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates as we continue to push the boundaries of the Web3 ecosystem and keep your eyes on our <a href="https://push.org/docs/roadmap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2024 roadmap</a>, for a further glimpse into what's next. Together, let's continue to push the industry forward toward unified applications and a better UX than ever before!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Updates</category>
            <category>Community and Ecosystem</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Rise of Chains and Fall of UX in Web3 UX]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The Rise of Chains and Fall of UX in Web3 UX]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of The Rise of Chains and Fall of UX in Web3 UX" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-5fe9bba3982ef324b0a2b4ef35ae3ae0.webp" width="2000" height="1125" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>It has been around 9 years since Ethereum was born.</p>
<p>It's been 9 years since Ethereum first launched, marking the beginning of a revolutionary era in blockchain technology. What began as a general-purpose blockchain has evolved into a global, decentralized World Computer, unlocking a wave of technological innovations through the power of cryptography and decentralization.</p>
<p>Fast forward to today, the landscape has dramatically shifted.</p>
<p>We have over <a href="https://dune.com/21co/layer-2-summary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">30 Layer 2 solutions</a>, numerous rollups and now even Layer 3s. With such an explosion of chains what we now have is a fragmented ecosystem where user experience is compromised, liquidity is spread thin across multiple platforms, security of assets is a major concern, and building applications in the multi-chain world is getting increasingly difficult.</p>
<p><em>But how did we get here?</em></p>
<p>This article is designed to give a complete picture of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>How web3 ended up with so many chains,</em></li>
<li><em>How this has adversely affected the entire ecosystem,</em></li>
<li><em>And, what we can do to build better web3 apps in this multi-chain world</em></li>
</ul>
<p>Let’s get started.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-rise-of-chains">The Rise of Chains<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux#the-rise-of-chains" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Rise of Chains" title="Direct link to The Rise of Chains">​</a></h3>
<p>Since the advent of layer 1 chains, scalability and high fee (gas) requirements have been a major concern. For chains like Ethereum specifically, as the number of applications grew, so did the network’s congestion and the overall cost for users.</p>
<p>A significant step to resolve these issues was taken on October 02, 2020, when Vitalik introduced the <a href="https://ethereum-magicians.org/t/a-rollup-centric-ethereum-roadmap/4698" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Rollup-Centric Ethereum Roadmap</em></a>. This meant Ethereum moved towards rollups as its scaling strategy because <strong>bundling multiple transactions</strong> <strong>into batches</strong> significantly increased <em><strong>transaction throughput</strong></em> and <em><strong>reduced transaction costs.</strong></em></p>
<p>This solved Ethereum's scalability issue effectively as it reduced the load on the Layer 1 chain and provided cheaper transaction fees. However, we soon realized that the rollup-centric roadmap had led to the development of plethora of new L2s, Rollup solutions, and even L3s. This expansion has enabled greater scalability and reduced transaction costs, which are essential for the growth of decentralized applications (dApps).</p>
<p>Additionally, the web3 ecosystem soon realized the need for designing chains that are specifically optimized for single applications, i.e. app-specific chains. Technically, this seemed necessary to ensure that these applications could achieve optimal performance, security, and user experience tailored to their unique requirements without being affected by the general-purpose network congestion and fees of more generic Layer 1 or Layer 2 solutions.</p>
<p>While app-specific chains achieved the desired outcome by optimizing for their specific needs, this again led to the creation of multiple new chains. L3s as applications like dYdX, Hyperliquid, or Frax became standalone app chains or rollups of their own.</p>
<p>This inception of new rollups, app chains, L2, and L3s undoubtedly resolved quite a few key issues of the ecosystem like <em>scalability, block space, network usage fees</em>, etc. However, it also led to another significant concern for web3 users and devs.</p>
<p>A deep dive into this topic will lead us to many concerns that arise with the significant proliferation of chains such as f<em>ragmentation of liquidity across chains, inadequate incentive management, broken user experience, difficulties for developers, security risks, etc.</em></p>
<p>However, in this article, we will primarily focus on the ones that affect either the existing users or the newcomers.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-fall-of-web3-ux">The Fall of Web3 UX<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux#the-fall-of-web3-ux" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Fall of Web3 UX" title="Direct link to The Fall of Web3 UX">​</a></h3>
<p>As the number of chains has multiplied, so have the challenges, particularly in terms of user experience (UX). With the rise of these new chains, the overall UX of web3 has become increasingly complex for the average user to navigate.</p>
<p>Here is a quick glance at what a typical web3 user needs to deal with in this multi-chain universe:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>managing multiple wallets,</em></li>
<li><em>managing multiple native tokens/assets in their multiple wallets,</em></li>
<li><em>understanding the nuances of each network,</em></li>
<li><em>navigating multiple networks to perform simple tasks,</em></li>
<li><em>interacting with complicated dapp UIs with frequent network switching</em></li>
<li><em>navigate through inconsistent user interfaces</em></li>
<li><em>relying on the risky route of cross-chain bridging between chains</em></li>
<li><em>experiencing difficulty in maintaining a consistent cross-chain identity due to the multi-chain ecosystem</em></li>
<li><em>dealing with the lack of standardization between networks, protocols, etc</em></li>
<li><em>dealing with the learning curve of understanding different networks, each with its own set of rules, interfaces, and requirements.</em></li>
</ul>
<p>Remember that this is just a glance at the UX problem. There are undoubtedly more issues issues for a web3 user daily. The list is even longer when it comes to newbie web3 users.</p>
<p>The above-mentioned issues lead to a few major hurdles for not just users but also for developers as well as the entire web3 ecosystem:</p>
<p><strong>Fragmented User Experience</strong></p>
<p>The main drawback of navigating a multi-chain world is, well, the <em><strong>multiple chains</strong></em> (<em>instead of just one)</em>. And that leads to a completely fragmented user experience.</p>
<p>A continual requirement for users to switch between chains, often using different wallets or interfaces for each one makes it challenging for users to keep track of their assets or manage their interactions with dApps. As a result, many find the Web3 experience confusing and overwhelming, which can deter them from using these services altogether.</p>
<p><strong>User Retention Challenges</strong></p>
<p>Poor UX can directly impact user retention.</p>
<p>Truth be told, it already is impacting user retention.</p>
<p>When users encounter difficulties in navigating the web3 ecosystem, they are less likely to return to it. High-profile dApps that have struggled with user retention due to UX issues serve as cautionary tales for new projects entering the space. Complex interfaces, slow transaction times, and confusing wallet setups have all contributed to a decline in user engagement and adoption.</p>
<p><strong>Security and Trust Concerns</strong></p>
<p>The complexity of managing multiple chains also introduces security risks.</p>
<p>Users must ensure that they are interacting with the correct chain, using the right wallet, and understanding the implications of each transaction. This complexity increases the likelihood of user errors, such as sending assets to the wrong address or falling victim to phishing attacks.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the process of bridging assets between these chains is quite often cumbersome and fraught with risks. Users must rely on various bridging protocols, which not only add to the complexity but also introduce potential security vulnerabilities. For instance, a user willing to move tokens from Ethereum to an L2 solution must navigate multiple steps, including wrapping and unwrapping tokens, which can be a deterrent for new users.</p>
<p><strong>Increased Complexity for Builders</strong></p>
<p>The rise of multiple chains was never just a UX problem for the users of web3. There’s more to it. It has also introduced a host of extra challenges for developers and builders in the space.</p>
<p>For example, each chain often has its own development tools, SDKs, and environments that developers must learn &amp; adapt to, which can be time-consuming and lead to inconsistencies in development practices. Maintaining applications that operate across multiple chains requires managing multiple codebases or conditional code paths. This can lead to significant maintenance overhead, especially when chains update their protocols or APIs.</p>
<p>Each additional chain integrated into an application introduces new potential vulnerabilities. Developers must ensure that the security of cross-chain interactions is robust, as any weakness could lead to exploits or hacks.</p>
<p>Furthermore, developing for a multi-chain ecosystem that still lacks adequate standardization - is costly. It requires more time and resources, as developers need to learn and implement different protocols, test on multiple platforms, and ensure compatibility across the whole environment involved. The additional cost of extensive security audits makes the process of building &amp; maintaining apps even more difficult.</p>
<p><strong>Barrier to Mass Adoption</strong></p>
<p>The above-mentioned problems are issues that affect not just users but the web3 world as a whole.</p>
<p>One of the biggest barriers to the mass adoption of Web3 is poor UX. While early adopters and tech-savvy users may be willing to navigate the complexities of the blockchain, the average user is likely to be put off by the steep learning curve. To achieve widespread adoption, Web3 dApps must prioritize UX and make it as easy as possible for users to interact with their services. This means simplifying interfaces, reducing the need for users to understand the underlying technology, and providing clear, concise instructions.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="so-what-can-we-do-about-it">So, What Can We Do About It?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux#so-what-can-we-do-about-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to So, What Can We Do About It?" title="Direct link to So, What Can We Do About It?">​</a></h3>
<p>Web3 has come as far as it has today by collaborating to solve the major problems of the ecosystem from providing decentralized infrastructure to solving scalability concerns. The current major problem, however, is the fragmented and broken UX of web3 apps.</p>
<p>Fortunately, some teams and protocols have some of the best minds in the industry, already working on solving this problem.</p>
<p>One of the major roadmap items of Ethereum, for instance, is its plans to fix the fragmented ecosystem with <a href="https://ethcc.io/archive/universal-synchronous-composability" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em><strong>Universal Synchronous Composability</strong></em></a>, which undoubtedly would be a massive step towards solving the fragmented world we have today as well as towards providing a better UX for users.</p>
<p>Frameworks like <a href="https://frontier.tech/the-cake-framework" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CAKE</a> by Frontier Research as well as protocols like Socket, Particle Network, etc., are all building solutions to provide an abstracted user experience for web3 users where they no longer have to bother about the underlying chains, <em>which in itself resolves more than half of web3 users’ UX issues.</em></p>
<p>Most of these solutions, however, are currently in their nascent stages and it will still take a significant amount of time for them to shape the overall fragmented UX of Ethereum.</p>
<p>Moreover, this does not indicate that it all has been addressed. As web3 builders or protocols, we can still do more to expand the boundaries for improving web3 UX. There are still a few imperative actions that we can take to enhance the experience for our users because as previously mentioned - <em><strong>good UX for users impacts the overall web3 ecosystem positively.</strong></em></p>
<p>In fact, some of those actions can be taken instantly to improve your applications.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>A UX-First Approach to App Development</strong></p>
<p>In simpler terms, this means building your apps in a way that even a newbie web3 user can navigate without having to read a single page of documentation or reach out to you for extra support.</p>
<p>Most web3 applications are usually built with native web3 users in mind. It is simply assumed that users should be well aware of what a <em>hexadecimal blockchain address</em> looks like or what <em>blockchain-based</em> <em>transactions</em> mean.</p>
<p>Dapps with such assumptions, while easy to build, are a nightmare for new users who aren’t tech-savvy and this leads to a bad UX for most users.</p>
<p>To combat this, apps should focus on creating intuitive, user-friendly interfaces that abstract away the complexity of interacting with the blockchain - <em>as much as possible</em>. This includes providing clear instructions, reducing the number of steps required to complete a transaction, and ensuring that users have access to all of the information they need to make informed decisions.</p>
<p>Thus, focus on creating apps with user-friendly designs that prioritize seamless interactions and accessibility.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Provide Cross-Chain Support &amp; Solutions If required</strong></p>
<p>Cross-chain interoperability is another critical solution for improving Web3 UX. By enabling seamless communication between different chains, interoperability protocols can reduce the complexity of navigating a multi-chain environment.</p>
<p>If your protocol spreads across multiple chains, you need to figure out ways to make it seamless for your users to navigate through it and the apps built on top of it. Including cross-chain solutions for such cases eventually leads to a better UX for your users.</p>
<p>A good example of this in practice is how Push leverages cross-chain solutions for its <a href="https://push.org/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CCR feature</a> which primarily aims to improve the experience for the users.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Incentive Structure for Seamless UX</strong></p>
<p>Incentivization could play a key role as well. To encourage developers to prioritize UX, dApps can create incentive structures that reward user-centric design.</p>
<p>This could include offering grants to developers who create user-friendly interfaces, and focus on solving UX challenges in multi-chain environments. This could help fund the creation of tools and features that reduce friction for users by either optimizing existing pieces of software for better performance or simplifying user interfaces.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Good UX is more than just a User Interface</strong></p>
<p>A common misconception is to equate good UX solely with fast and visually appealing user interfaces. In reality, a truly great UX goes far beyond just the front-end design.</p>
<p>Two critical components that significantly enhance the overall UX for your users are <em><strong>usability and trust.</strong></em></p>
<p>Unlike traditional Web2 apps, Web3 applications interact with smart contracts, which require gas fees for any on-chain operations. Optimizing these smart contracts to minimize gas consumption is essential. By doing so, you ensure that users can engage with your dApp more cost-effectively, directly improving usability and making your application more accessible to a broader audience.</p>
<p>Moreover, robust security features and a commitment to transparency with users are fundamental to building <strong>reliability and trust.</strong> In the Web3 space, where apps interact with immutable databases—the blockchain—users must be confident in the safety of their transactions. Since most on-chain transactions are irreversible, providing clear security warnings before users commit and giving detailed error messages, and transparent indicators of transaction statuses (including estimated processing times) are crucial for fostering trust.</p>
<p>In addition, conducting thorough audits of your smart contracts to mitigate the risk of exploits is not just a security measure but a vital aspect of UX. Ensuring that users' assets are safe builds confidence and reliability in your app, which is indispensable for an overall positive user experience.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="building-a-web3-app-in-a-multi-chain-world">Building a Web3 App in a Multi-Chain World<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux#building-a-web3-app-in-a-multi-chain-world" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Building a Web3 App in a Multi-Chain World" title="Direct link to Building a Web3 App in a Multi-Chain World">​</a></h3>
<p>Push Protocol has always aimed to improve the overall user experience for not just its own users but the entire web3 ecosystem.</p>
<p>Since the launch of our dapp, we have led with the incorporation of a UX-Driven and Security-First approach. Be it visual interface changes to the dapp, optimizations of our smart contract, or enabling gasless opt-ins for smooth dapp interactions, we continue to put this into practice across the board.</p>
<p>Here is a quick glance at the evolution of the Push Dapp since its early days.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Push DApp" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image1-061e8a044eb8e8e2f6db3737f27d97ad.webp" width="2000" height="2000" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>However, as previously mentioned, UX is more than just user interface improvements.</p>
<p>In particular, maintaining an excellent UX in web3 app with such a fragmented ecosystem could be very challenging.</p>
<p>We faced a similar challenge as well.</p>
<p>Push has built a communication &amp; notification layer for all EVM (<em>and soon, Non-EVM</em>) chains. This means our dapp supports multiple chains which leads to a fragmented experience where user have to frequently switch between chains to perform various actions.</p>
<p>A major improvement to resolve this was recently proposed in the PRE-PIP 3 of Push Governance, i.e., <a href="https://gov.push.org/t/pre-pip-3-cross-chain-request-feature-in-push-smart-contracts-v3/1794" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em><strong>Cross Chain Requests.</strong></em></a></p>
<p><strong>Cross Chain Requests ( CCR)</strong>&nbsp;feature shall be one of the most significant features of Push Smart Contracts as it will enable users to perform important actions like c<em>hannel creation, creation of Incentivized Chat requests, or any arbitrary request</em>&nbsp;from the chain of their choice.</p>
<p>The core idea of the Cross Chain Request feature is to&nbsp;<strong>make Push smart contracts capable of handling requests that can originate from any chain and are securely relayed to Push Core contracts on Ethereum for necessary validations &amp; state changes.</strong></p>
<p>In other words, we shall be able to provide an abstracted experience to our users, one in which they no longer have to care about switching to a specific network to interact with the dapp. Users can choose to stay on their preferred chain and the dapp shall be able to handle the rest, thus providing a significantly improved UX in the currently fragmented multi-chain world of Web3.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-rise-of-chains-and-fall-of-ux-in-web3-ux#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h3>
<p>The rise of multi-chain environments has undoubtedly brought about significant advancements in scalability and efficiency within the Web3 ecosystem. However, this growth has also introduced new challenges, particularly regarding user experience. As dApps continue to evolve and expand across multiple chains, it is crucial to prioritize UX to ensure that users can navigate the ecosystem with ease.</p>
<p>By focusing on creating unified experiences, leveraging cross-chain interoperability solutions, and simplifying user interfaces, web3 apps can overcome the challenges of a multi-chain world and hopefully drive mass adoption of web3 technology.</p>
<p>To achieve mainstream adoption, it's now imperative that web3 finds ways to streamline these experiences, making it easier for average users to navigate the complex landscape of multiple chains and protocols.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Web3 UX</category>
            <category>Insights</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cold Start Solutions: Scaling Consumer Crypto]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cold-start-solutions-scaling-consumer-crypto</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cold-start-solutions-scaling-consumer-crypto</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Cold Start Solutions: Scaling Consumer Crypto]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Cold Start Solutions: Scaling Consumer Crypto" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-d6b3f4c7b0a309b6fa28467819b2461d.webp" width="1920" height="1080" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>We’ve gone from wen moon to wen widespread adoption? We, as builders, stick around in this wild, wonderful space we call home because we envision a more transparent, fairer, and overall better internet.</p>
<p>We want social networks that we’re never actually locked into. We want user-run apps. We envision a world in which we truly own what we share online, whether that’s our messages, our photos, or simply, our data.</p>
<p>Ownership of the internet by the collective rather than the few is and always will be a key part of what we’re all doing here. Still, why do 95% of consumers know what crypto is but only 22% actively use anything that constitutes a “crypto application?” How do we reach an age in which Dapps are just apps and in which web3 is just “the internet?”</p>
<p>How do we unify the world under one banner?</p>
<p>To even begin to answer any of these questions, we need to both understand why we haven’t quite crossed the chasm. We’ve redefined what the financial system and, the internet as a whole can be, but we haven’t gotten the greater global population to buy in.</p>
<p>By looking at how different projects, networks, and platforms, both in and outside of crypto, have overcome the "cold start problem," you can piece together a playbook to set your Dapp up to cross the chasm to widespread adoption.</p>
<p>For our purposes, we’ll be examining all cases under the umbrella of platforms, since almost every popular app, Dapp, or network today has turned out to be one.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-the-cold-start-problem-and-why-should-anyone-care">What is the Cold Start Problem and why should anyone care?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cold-start-solutions-scaling-consumer-crypto#what-is-the-cold-start-problem-and-why-should-anyone-care" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is the Cold Start Problem and why should anyone care?" title="Direct link to What is the Cold Start Problem and why should anyone care?">​</a></h3>
<p>You’ve built an app. You believe it’s the next place where everyone will gather to connect and share content online. It’s going to be the next member of the “billion users club.”</p>
<p>Everything’s in place technically and yet, there’s one problem. You don’t have any users and you don’t have anything for them to share.</p>
<p>If you’ve built an Airbnb without listings and users, a YouTube without videos, or a social network without content and users, then you’ve faced the cold start problem. Trying to figure out how to set the right baseline of producers(or just content) and consumers to set your app(or platform) up for success means solving the cold start problem.</p>
<p>In the context of web3, a cold start refers to launching a Dapp that has no user base yet. Alternatively, it can be defined as determining how to attract an initial user base that will engage with the Dapp in the exact ways needed to scale it from 0 to a wide audience.</p>
<p>Knowing how to address the cold start problem requires understanding how others have already done so and there’s no better place to begin than with some of web2’s most explosive successes.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="zoom-its-easy-and-it-just-works">Zoom: It’s easy and it just works<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cold-start-solutions-scaling-consumer-crypto#zoom-its-easy-and-it-just-works" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Zoom: It’s easy and it just works" title="Direct link to Zoom: It’s easy and it just works">​</a></h3>
<p>There’s something to be said for a product that’s dedicated to being as reliable as possible and as easy as possible to use. When Zoom rose to prominence during the pandemic, some claimed that its meteoric growth was simply due to luck and timing.</p>
<p>This, however, is only half of the truth.</p>
<p>They had both the right timing and the right product.</p>
<p>On the surface, Zoom appeared to be just another videoconferencing option, but two key actors prepared it to become the giant it is today. First, it was and continues to be dedicated to making every aspect of the user experience radically simple. You could and can still join a meeting just by clicking a link. Everything from reacting to a speaker to sending a message to changing your background, to integrating your planned meetings with your calendar was made as easy as possible to do.</p>
<p>During a time when we were more desperate than ever to connect with people, it became the most reliable option. The fact that it continued to run nearly seamlessly for up to 100 users per meeting via the free tier and 300+ on the higher tiers only added to its popularity.</p>
<p>Perhaps you’ll find Zoom’s example to be inspiring and perhaps not. Admittedly, Zoom has now also faced its share of issues. Even so, web3 builders can still learn from its team’s dedication to facilitating seamless onboarding and making the product “just work” above all else.</p>
<p><strong>Key takeaways from Zoom’s example:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Reducing the number of signatures required for sign-up to your Dapp</li>
<li>Simplifying the process of initiating transactions</li>
<li>Integrating solutions similar to <a href="https://push.org/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push’s Cross Chain Requests</a> to take the hassle of bridging and related actions away from the end-user</li>
<li>Stripping away complexity that could cause performance issues in the early days and focusing on the core functionalities that are explicitly needed</li>
<li>Beta testing, through multiple iterations in a gamified fashion with points or even tokens to ensure your MVP just works</li>
<li>Releasing your MVP once it’s clear it will run without major issues</li>
<li>Adding new features with direct user input through community calls, surveys, and other direct methods like the governance process, as your Dapp’s user base grows</li>
</ul>
<p>With a list such as the above, you’ll be off to a good start. Still, having a killer product is only one piece of the puzzle. Solving the cold start problem also means having the right mix of users in place, or, as Alexis Ohanian puts it, “the minimum viable community,” from day one.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="bank-of-america-and-bitcoin-atomic-networks-lead-to-hyperscaling">Bank of America and Bitcoin: Atomic Networks Lead to Hyperscaling<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cold-start-solutions-scaling-consumer-crypto#bank-of-america-and-bitcoin-atomic-networks-lead-to-hyperscaling" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bank of America and Bitcoin: Atomic Networks Lead to Hyperscaling" title="Direct link to Bank of America and Bitcoin: Atomic Networks Lead to Hyperscaling">​</a></h3>
<p>To define “minimum viable community,” and why it matters, let’s begin by considering the invention of the consumer credit card. On September 18, 1958, Bank of America mailed the first credit cards to 60,000 residents of Fresno, California. These cards were pre-loaded with $300-$500 of credit and required no application process.</p>
<p>In one day, 60,000 cardholders came into being. This resulted in 300 Fresno-based merchants signing up to support Bank of America’s new network. In just over a year, that network grew to 2 million cardholders and 20,000 merchants.</p>
<p>Bank of America’s gamble worked because it wasn’t a gamble. Their first cardholders weren’t randomly selected. At the time of the launch, 45% of Fresno residents had some sort of relationship with the bank, making Fresno the ideal spot for the first atomic network for their new credit card.</p>
<p>With their experience with Fresno in hand, the bank was able to repeat the same success repeatedly leading to their meteoric rise to prominence in the nascent space of consumer credit.</p>
<p>This is an atomic network, a unique, intentional matching of consumers and producers that just works and can be repeated to scale a networked product.</p>
<p>All successful platforms started in this manner. Still, the atomic network is only one part of the battle. Without a killer product to drive to it, your chances of scaling are virtually non-existent.</p>
<p>Take Bitcoin, for example.</p>
<p>In 2009, when it launched, it already had pre-set users. The cypherpunk community. These individuals believed in widespread financial freedom, the right to privacy, and every other aspect of what is still the wind beneath the wings of the crypto industry. With the cypherpunks as its first atomic network, Bitcoin launched and continued to scale without a central authority.</p>
<p><strong>Key takeaways from Bank of America and Bitcoin itself:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Starting with a specific area or online community where people need what you're offering</li>
<li>Zeroing in on that using similar approaches to how Bank of America built out its credit network and how Bitcoin built out its initial atomic network for future scale</li>
<li>Making sure your product addresses a need expressed in the values of the group or groups involved</li>
<li>Determining through your initial connection with that group or groups what features address a real need for them</li>
<li>Launching with a small set of features that directly address what this initial atomic network or MVC needs</li>
<li>Iterating and expanding based on user feedback and direct usage patterns that arise in your MVC</li>
<li>Using your initial atomic network or MVC as a model for growth into new markets and leveraging the same messaging and overall values that attracted your pioneers</li>
</ul>
<p>Killer products with the right atomic networks can set a Dapp up for explosive growth but you won’t gain and retain your initial atomic network without solving for the power users first.</p>
<p>Whether we’re speaking about a web2 app like Zoom or Bitcoin, the digital gold itself, the principle remains the same.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="wikipedia-ethereum-and-daos-solve-for-the-core-contributors-first">Wikipedia, Ethereum, and DAOs: Solve for the Core Contributors First<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cold-start-solutions-scaling-consumer-crypto#wikipedia-ethereum-and-daos-solve-for-the-core-contributors-first" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Wikipedia, Ethereum, and DAOs: Solve for the Core Contributors First" title="Direct link to Wikipedia, Ethereum, and DAOs: Solve for the Core Contributors First">​</a></h3>
<p>Last but not least, let’s say you have a killer, easy-to-use product and a potential atomic network, but you’re struggling with attracting your first creators.</p>
<p>“Creator,” in this context, may be considered synonymous with “producer.”  Youtubers, Bitcoin miners, developers, or even Wikipedia editors, it’s all the same in this respect. In today’s day and age where we’re trending more and more towards every app involving a two-sided exchange, it’s never been more crucial to attract and retain the right creators from the get-go.</p>
<p>For instance, Wikipedia is largely maintained by 0.02% of its users, who create and edit articles for free. They do so both because they deeply connect with Wikipedia’s vision of “free access to all human knowledge,” and because of the relative prestige their work gains them within their community.</p>
<p>In short, they join the effort and stay with it because they need to see the vision realized. DAOs work in the same manner. So do many crypto projects, including Ethereum itself which has consistently been able to attract and retain builders from all over the world due to its commitment to being the world computer that anyone can build on.</p>
<p>The vision rules. The core contributors create the environment for ideal collaboration which scales the network to new heights.</p>
<p>Wikipedia found its core contributors through sharing its vision across communities that were most likely to resonate with it, like Nupedia, and Slashdot. DAOs tend to publish manifestos, constitutions, or similar documents from day one to do the same. Ethereum used its early technical papers and its ICO, together with memorable appearances at industry events, as jump-off points.</p>
<p>In all of these cases, the founding teams led with incredible attention to detail related to who their initial target market was.</p>
<p>Still, creating an environment that incentivizes consistent growth is incredibly difficult.</p>
<p>Some Dapps will choose to start by surveying their core community and creating a shared vision and set of values as a collective. Some will do so via a delegation representing the whole community. Others won’t need decentralized governance of any kind until the later stages of their development.</p>
<p>While there’s no one-size-fits-all approach to attracting and keeping the first producers or “core contributors” to your Dapp’s growth, there are principles that tend to work across the board.</p>
<p>The below is an attempt at mapping out the steps of that effort.</p>
<p><strong>Key takeaways from Wikipedia, Ethereum, and DAOs:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Creating an impactful vision and using successful vision-driven projects as jump-offs or inspirations for doing so</li>
<li>Aligning your project's vision with the values of your most active users</li>
<li>Publishing a manifesto or a similar document indicating what you stand for and why people should care about what you are doing</li>
<li>Creating an environment that fosters collaboration and innovation</li>
<li>Implementing governance structures and incentives that encourage long-term commitment</li>
<li>Ensuring that any change or new effort you put into place is a value add for your core contributors</li>
<li>Making paths to further growth clear to every community member, whether that’s how an ambassador rises to core status or something else entirely</li>
<li>Opening up growth paths to anyone and having them stewarded by your initial core members</li>
<li>Iterating with community sentiment and realizing that no aspect of your community, even your initial vision, is set in stone forever</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-consumer-crypto-playbook-a-starting-point">The Consumer Crypto Playbook: A Starting Point<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cold-start-solutions-scaling-consumer-crypto#the-consumer-crypto-playbook-a-starting-point" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Consumer Crypto Playbook: A Starting Point" title="Direct link to The Consumer Crypto Playbook: A Starting Point">​</a></h3>
<p>We’re at a tipping point.</p>
<p>Both in and outside of the crypto space, almost all popular apps are platforms. Some sort of supplier is meeting some sort of demand. The rise of Bitcoin, Ethereum, and the industry we hold dear today shifted everything further towards this point. Today, crypto-based applications are starting to break through to the mainstream, but we haven’t yet had our breakout moment.</p>
<p>For now, we’re still sitting on the edge of the chasm towards widespread consumer usage.</p>
<p>To make our way across, we need the right playbook for scaling Dapps which focuses on simplicity reigning across the user experience, growth beginning and consistently centering on the atomic network, and the hard side being solved from the earliest days.</p>
<p>Our discussion here today is an in-roads. How you address the cold start problem is highly context-specific to what your Dapp’s niche is. With all of the above takeaways at your fingertips, you have the foundation for an early-growth playbook that gets you off to a solid start.</p>
<p>As you think about any of the areas that we’ve covered here, consider the following questions to help guide you even further:</p>
<ul>
<li>How can you abstract away complexity from your networked product to make the user experience as easy as possible from day one?</li>
<li>What's the deep purpose of the network you're launching?</li>
<li>Why should people care about that purpose?</li>
<li>Who are the groups in which you’ll find those people who will become your minimum viable community?</li>
<li>Where do those groups gather, online or offline?</li>
<li>How can you most effectively reach them in a way that won’t turn them off from what you’re offering?</li>
<li>Once you’ve got your minimum viable community, what will keep them involved?</li>
<li>What incentives will you offer to show in practice that you’re dedicated to your earliest users?</li>
<li>How will you take in community feedback and how will you show you’re using it in practice?</li>
<li>How will your product be led over time?</li>
<li>Will you DAOify or simply decentralize a part of your product?</li>
</ul>
<p>We, at Push, envision a world in which the on-chain experience is seamless and Universal Apps negate the need to understand the complexity of switching between chains. For that to happen, we need all hands working together towards the same goal. If you’re a builder who is focused on the nascent area of consumer crypto, consider reaching out to us on our socials and even <a href="https://app.charmverse.io/push-dao/proposals" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">applying for our grants program</a>, where we’re already shepherding the pioneers towards a future that champions the everyday user.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Consumer Crypto</category>
            <category>Insights</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Role of Randomness in Push Nodes]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-role-of-randomness-in-push-nodes</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-role-of-randomness-in-push-nodes</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The Role of Randomness in Push Nodes]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of The Role of Randomness in Push Nodes " src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-4f0c05c1273995c7ca8bf139ed4b9a0b.webp" width="2000" height="1125" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>One important aspect of decentralized networks is that they don’t have any central authority that governs their working mechanism. This means, the network must create a system and rules that allows them to not just securely communicate but to also form a consensus on the overall state of the network.</p>
<p>While it's a complicated task and there exists a plethora of imperative ingredients that enable security and fairness in a decentralized network, one of the most significant ones is randomness.</p>
<p>Randomness, in its simplest form, refers to the lack of pattern or predictability in events. It's a concept that plays a crucial role in various fields, from mathematics and computer science to nature itself. Randomness is what makes a dice roll unpredictable, ensures fairness in games, and powers the algorithms behind secure cryptographic systems. In technology, especially within decentralized networks, randomness serves as a fundamental building block that underpins security and fairness, ensuring that processes are free from bias and manipulation.</p>
<p>In this article, we explore the significance of randomness in decentralized networks and how Push nodes incorporate randomness to enhance the security of the Push network.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-do-we-even-need-randomness">Why do we even need Randomness?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-role-of-randomness-in-push-nodes#why-do-we-even-need-randomness" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why do we even need Randomness?" title="Direct link to Why do we even need Randomness?">​</a></h3>
<p>To begin with, let’s understand the importance of Randomness in decentralized networks.</p>
<p>As previously mentioned, decentralized networks don’t have a central authority. Instead, they are made of a group of nodes located at different parts of the world. These nodes are responsible to act and perform certain actions in the network to keep it functional.</p>
<p>The selection of nodes to perform specific tasks must happen in a decentralized and fair manner to ensure no single actor in the network is capable of controlling the operations of the network.</p>
<p>This is where randomness plays a critical role.</p>
<p>In such decentralized systems, randomness is used to ensure the unpredictability of various processes, such as selecting validators, generating cryptographic keys, etc.</p>
<p>This unpredictability is essential to prevent malicious actors from gaining control or manipulating the network. For example, in consensus mechanisms like Proof of Stake, a random selection of validators ensures that no single participant can dominate the process, thereby maintaining the decentralized nature of the network involved.</p>
<p>Randomness also enhances the resilience of blockchains by making it difficult for attackers to predict or influence outcomes. This unpredictability protects against various attacks, such as Sybil attacks or collusion, where adversaries attempt to gain disproportionate control over a network.</p>
<p>Moreover, randomness is vital in achieving fairness as it helps ensure that every participant has an equal opportunity to contribute and benefit from a network, regardless of their resources or influence.</p>
<p>Now that we have a basic understanding of how crucial randomness is, let’s understand its how Push Nodes use randomness to enhance their security and fairness.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="quick-glance-at-push-nodes">Quick Glance at Push Nodes<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-role-of-randomness-in-push-nodes#quick-glance-at-push-nodes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Quick Glance at Push Nodes" title="Direct link to Quick Glance at Push Nodes">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://push.org/blog/explaining-push-nodes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Nodes</a> are a significant step towards the decentralized infrastructure for web3’s leading communication layer, the Push Protocol Network. This network is designed to facilitate secure and efficient movement of web3 notifications.</p>
<p>The Push Network comprises different types of nodes such as Validator Nodes, Storage nodes, etc. A smart contract guards the network to maintain node staking and slashing. This is where the PUSH token is used.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="how-the-push-network-uses-randomness-to-enhance-its-security">How the Push Network uses Randomness to enhance its Security<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-role-of-randomness-in-push-nodes#how-the-push-network-uses-randomness-to-enhance-its-security" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How the Push Network uses Randomness to enhance its Security" title="Direct link to How the Push Network uses Randomness to enhance its Security">​</a></h3>
<p>In this section, we will specifically understand the complete mechanism of how a transaction is submitted onto Push network and the role of randomness involved in the process.</p>
<p>In the Push Network, the role of randomization is incorporated at multiple levels which allows the network to prevent centralization while ensuring that it remains resilient against a variety of attacks.</p>
<p>A crucial security mechanism of the Push Chain is the randomized selection of validators for transaction validation or block production. This mechanism leverages cryptographic randomness to ensure an unpredictable selection of validators &amp;&nbsp;attestants ( <em>who verify whether or not a transaction is legit</em> ) to enhance the network’s resilience and fairness.</p>
<p>A brief overview of the process looks something like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>To send a transaction to the network, the SDK/sender must attach a randomly generated token number to the transaction.</li>
<li>To fetch this token, the SDK can request the same from any validator.</li>
<li>Once received, the SDK attaches this token to the transaction and sends it to the network.</li>
<li>The network then uses this random token to cryptographically decide the specific validator to verify the particular transaction for further processing.</li>
<li>Additionally, the validator also randomly decides the validator set responsible for attesting to the transaction.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="now-lets-dive-deeper-into-the-randomness-of-the-push-network"><strong>Now, let’s dive deeper into the Randomness of the Push Network:</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-role-of-randomness-in-push-nodes#now-lets-dive-deeper-into-the-randomness-of-the-push-network" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to now-lets-dive-deeper-into-the-randomness-of-the-push-network" title="Direct link to now-lets-dive-deeper-into-the-randomness-of-the-push-network">​</a></h3>
<p>The Push SDK selects a random validator (VR1) to generate a special signed (RANDX) hex token.</p>
<p>The generation is performed as follows:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Generation of a Random Token:</strong></p>
<p>The network is designed to ensure that a random token cannot merely be generated by a single validator. Instead, it must be a combined effort as every random token is ideally a collection of digitally signed pieces of random numbers provided by specific validators in the network.</p>
<p>To determine the exact number of such pieces required to form the token, the Validator.sol smart contract defines a parameter called <code>*required_random_number</code>.* This indicates the number of required random peers whose signed values each validator must hold, at a given time. Additionally, the contract also defines an <code>*expiration_time*</code> parameter that defines the expiry time for these tokens which helps ensure that only freshly created tokens can be used for the creation of random tokens.</p>
<p>It should be kept in mind that validators in the network periodically ping their peers to collect and exchange signed random values. The collected value from each validator is a combination of the random value itself and the validator's signature, ensuring it can be verifiable.</p>
<div class="language-jsx codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#F8F8F2;--prism-background-color:#282A36"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-jsx codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#F8F8F2;background-color:#282A36"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">signedRandomValue </span><span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token plain"> value </span><span class="token operator">+</span><span class="token plain"> validatorSignature</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div>
<p>As a result, at any given moment the validators should have a collection of signed random values by their peers, i.e., <strong><code>signedRandomValue[].</code></strong></p>
<p>Once a validator has accumulated the necessary signed random values, it can generate the random token. This token is derived from the network's collective randomness using the following formula:</p>
<div class="language-jsx codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#F8F8F2;--prism-background-color:#282A36"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-jsx codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#F8F8F2;background-color:#282A36"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token maybe-class-name">RANDX_Token</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">XOR</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">(</span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(80, 250, 123)">sha</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">(</span><span class="token plain">signedRandomValue</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">[</span><span class="token plain">i</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">]</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">)</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">)</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token keyword control-flow" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249);font-style:italic">for</span><span class="token plain"> all i</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>The SDK Requests for a Random Token</strong></p>
<p>Next, now let’s understand what happens when the SDK requests for a random token.</p>
<p>As previously mentioned, before sending any transaction to the network, the SDK&nbsp; requests for a random token that must be attached with the transaction being sent.</p>
<p>Now, since a random token value has already been generated ( as mentioned in step 1), any validator can provide this random token to the SDK.</p>
<p>The SDK then attaches this random token to the transaction payloads and sends the transaction to the network.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Randomized Selection of Validators</strong></p>
<p>This random token attached to the transaction plays a crucial role in randomly deciding which validator will process the transaction. With this token, the SDK deciphers the validator ID, to whom it must send the transaction for further processing.</p>
<div class="language-jsx codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#F8F8F2;--prism-background-color:#282A36"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-jsx codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#F8F8F2;background-color:#282A36"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">validator_id </span><span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(80, 250, 123)">f</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">(</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">RANDX_TOKEN</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"> contract_defaults</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">)</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(98, 114, 164)">//OUTPUT looks like: </span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">validator_id </span><span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token plain"> v1</span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">where contract </span><span class="token keyword module" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249);font-style:italic">default</span><span class="token plain"> parameters could be</span><span class="token operator">:</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">a</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">.</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token property-access">min</span><span class="token plain"> required quantity </span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249);font-style:italic">of</span><span class="token plain"> random numbers</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">b</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">.</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token property-access">expiration</span><span class="token plain"> time</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">c</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">.</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token property-access">a</span><span class="token plain"> minimum number </span><span class="token keyword" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249);font-style:italic">of</span><span class="token plain"> peers that acknowledge the validator's online status</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">.</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div>
<p>Upon receiving the transaction, the validator checks the random token in the transaction’s payload and validates it to confirm that it has been correctly assigned the role of handling this transaction.</p>
<p>In case the validator identifies that it has been wrongly chosen, <em><strong>it can reject the transaction.</strong></em></p>
<p>Once the accurate assignment of the validator is confirmed, the validator now creates a similar randomized process for creating a list of validators who must attest to the transaction being processed.</p>
<div class="language-jsx codeBlockContainer_Ckt0 theme-code-block" style="--prism-color:#F8F8F2;--prism-background-color:#282A36"><div class="codeBlockContent_biex"><pre tabindex="0" class="prism-code language-jsx codeBlock_bY9V thin-scrollbar" style="color:#F8F8F2;background-color:#282A36"><code class="codeBlockLines_e6Vv"><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">vlist </span><span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token function" style="color:rgb(80, 250, 123)">f</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">(</span><span class="token maybe-class-name">RANDX_Token_2nd</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"> contract_defaults</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">)</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain" style="display:inline-block"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain"></span><span class="token comment" style="color:rgb(98, 114, 164)">// Output looks like this:</span><span class="token plain"></span><br></span><span class="token-line" style="color:#F8F8F2"><span class="token plain">vlist </span><span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">V2</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">V50</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">V11</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">V8</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">V38</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">V17</span><span class="token punctuation" style="color:rgb(248, 248, 242)">,</span><span class="token plain"> </span><span class="token constant" style="color:rgb(189, 147, 249)">V29</span><br></span></code></pre><div class="buttonGroup__atx"><button type="button" aria-label="Copy code to clipboard" title="Copy" class="clean-btn"><span class="copyButtonIcons_eSgA" aria-hidden="true"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonIcon_y97N"><path fill="currentColor" d="M19,21H8V7H19M19,5H8A2,2 0 0,0 6,7V21A2,2 0 0,0 8,23H19A2,2 0 0,0 21,21V7A2,2 0 0,0 19,5M16,1H4A2,2 0 0,0 2,3V17H4V3H16V1Z"></path></svg><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" class="copyButtonSuccessIcon_LjdS"><path fill="currentColor" d="M21,7L9,19L3.5,13.5L4.91,12.09L9,16.17L19.59,5.59L21,7Z"></path></svg></span></button></div></div></div>
<p>This list of validators is also responsible for verifying its <strong>legitimacy.</strong></p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="summary">Summary<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/the-role-of-randomness-in-push-nodes#summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary" title="Direct link to Summary">​</a></h3>
<p>To summarize, the entire process detailed above adds a security layer with the inclusion of randomization at multiple levels, i.e.,:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>1st Level:</strong> The initial randomization starts with the SDK choosing any random validator to request for a token to be attached to the transaction.</li>
<li><strong>2nd Level: A token is generated</strong> using digitally signed pieces of random values from multiple random validators instead of relying on any single actor.</li>
<li><strong>3rd Level: A specific validator is randomly selected</strong> to create the token to be attached in the transaction occurs.</li>
<li><strong>4th Level:</strong> The final level of randomization determines which specific validator (VR2) will process a transaction and which validator set will act as attestants to verify the transaction.</li>
</ul>
<p>This multi-level randomness ensures that at every step, the network is secure, and fair, while continuing to operate in a completely decentralized fashion.</p>
</li>
</ol>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Products</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Protocol Monthly Updates: A Look Back at July]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-july-updates</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-july-updates</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Protocol Monthly Updates: A Look Back at July]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Push Protocol Monthly Updates: A Look Back at July" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-e56fa1d0193551b5f9e87ee825b18077.webp" width="1600" height="840" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>July was a monumental month for Push Protocol as we hit the huge milestone of <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1824491148229898313" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>100 Million</strong></a> Push Notifications. More than 8.91 Million Notifications were sent with a cumulative 241k subscribers reached ending the month on a high note marking significant progress in protocol user engagement, development, and community growth.</p>
<p>With all of this in mind, we are excited to share the highlights:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="product-updates">Product Updates:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-july-updates#product-updates" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Product Updates:" title="Direct link to Product Updates:">​</a></h3>
<p>Our <a href="https://push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">website</a> has undergone a revamp, as we:</p>
<ul>
<li>Updated the <a href="https://push.org/docs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">developer docs</a> and <a href="https://push.org/docs/roadmap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2024 live roadmap</a>.</li>
<li>Performed various bug fixes for better UX.</li>
<li>Uploaded several new <a href="https://push.org/blog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">articles</a> focused on developer engagement and protocol growth announcements.</li>
</ul>
<p>Our <a href="https://app.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DApp</a> has seen significant upgrades, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>The debut of a new channel creation flow pipeline. Testing has been initiated for it.</li>
<li>The protocol and staking analytics overview features being released in the dashboard UI.</li>
<li>The update of the Development Design System with more components.</li>
<li>The update of the Font Family throughout the platform.</li>
<li>The beginning of work on the new Push Points Program.</li>
<li>The completion of all scheduled priority bug fixes.</li>
<li>We also enhanced the <a href="https://github.com/push-protocol/push-sdk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push SDK</a> by optimizing the code as per the new design system and added support for the ERC1155 Gated Chat Groups.</li>
</ul>
<p>On the backend, we are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Working on improving the response format for our API calls.</li>
<li>Working on a workflow automation tool that allows Push channels to automate their notification logic without writing a single line of code.</li>
<li>Working on developing a custom delivery node that delivers notifications to different platforms like Discord/Telegram/email.</li>
<li>Developing a pricing model for Push channels to leverage the custom delivery node’s capabilities.</li>
</ul>
<p>On the Smart Contracts side, we have:</p>
<ul>
<li>Added additional functional support that enables the update of channel profiles  from any chain.</li>
<li>Completed the setup of an extensive mainnet testing framework for the CCR feature.</li>
<li>Completed the optimizations for additional CCR-related features.</li>
<li>Extended the optimization phase of development to include the gas optimization of the current Core and Comm contracts.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="partnership-updates">Partnership Updates:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-july-updates#partnership-updates" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Partnership Updates:" title="Direct link to Partnership Updates:">​</a></h3>
<p>We're thrilled to announce new partnerships:</p>
<ol>
<li>We welcomed <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0xACF193302115b3e1b5E72402657ca3A2A21BeD87" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rivera</a> -  a liquidity management platform for transforming concentrated positions into DeFi-composable yield tokens who is integrating Push Notifications to enable weekly epoch rewards, APY changes, and more notification alerts for its users.</li>
<li>We partnered with <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1810185041793966136" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ETH Uruguay</a> to co-sponsor the Buildathon event, offering bounties for developing projects using Push’s communication services.</li>
<li>Push Protocol’s long-term partner Unstoppable Domains launched Group Chat powered by Push Protocol for the Crypto ‘<a href="https://x.com/sandy_carter/status/1809736115861221675" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Whale</a>’ group and new gated group chats, powered by Push for <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1816376657915044173" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stepn</a>, <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1815356125178728512" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raiin</a>, and <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1819715311253307611" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">.ubu</a> domain holders.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="ecosystem-highlights">Ecosystem Highlights:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-july-updates#ecosystem-highlights" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ecosystem Highlights:" title="Direct link to Ecosystem Highlights:">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Push Protocol’s Founder Harsh Rajat joined the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-AMYb7UWHQk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Digital Duniya Podcast</strong></a> to talk in-depth about the inception of Push Protocol and entrepreneurial tips for early founders, especially from India.</li>
<li>With Push’s expansion to <a href="https://arbitrum.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Arbitrum</a>, we conducted an exclusive <a href="https://x.com/i/spaces/1eaKbaEbBekxX" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AMA Twitter Space</a> with Arbitrum ecosystem partners  including <a href="https://www.inferium.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Inferium</a>, <a href="https://www.logx.trade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LogX</a>, and <a href="https://factor.fi/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Factor</a>, moderated by our DAO Lead.</li>
<li>We successfully conducted the second iteration of our <a href="https://push.org/brb/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Billion Reasons to Build (BRB) Bootcamp</a>, this time on a global scale via an online medium. Over six weeks, the <a href="https://x.com/pushbuilders/status/1812855006619423049" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">bootcamp</a> attracted 70 participants, featured 10 masterclass lectures, and garnered 60,000+ impressions on social media.</li>
<li>Further, we hosted Wormhole for a <a href="https://x.com/i/spaces/1djxXrbEezOGZ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push X Space</a> to discuss how Push will enable not just cross-chain but all-chain communications. Zaryab and Ian joined from our side, with Os from Wormhole’s ecosystem participating as well.</li>
<li>Push was also invited as a guest at the <a href="https://x.com/i/spaces/1yoKMwPwyalJQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Koala Wallet’s AMA X Space</a>.</li>
<li>We are thrilled to share that <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0xe56f1D3EDFFF1f25855aEF744caFE7991c224FFF" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Coindesk</a> - the leading crypto news platform crossed 10k subscribers for its channel on Push.</li>
<li>We were proud to feature <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0x7239B1896ad2b6A9D3aA6C4B12D8993E78fb67Dc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DappLooker</a>, <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0x094A1ef2F50F36956a90E410Ffc143362340865c" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Simplified Privacy</a>, <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0x90A48D5CF7343B08dA12E067680B4C6dbfE551Be" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ShapeShift</a>, and <a href="https://app.push.org/channels/0x67243d6c3c3bDc2F59D2f74ba1949a02973a529d" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Grantships</a> for the #PushChannelOfTheWeek in July 🔔</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-governance-and-community-updates">Push Governance and Community Updates:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/push-protocol-july-updates#push-governance-and-community-updates" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push Governance and Community Updates:" title="Direct link to Push Governance and Community Updates:">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>The Push Grants Programs V3 received 19 grant applications. <a href="https://dhive.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dhive</a> - A governance data hub platform and <a href="https://www.si3.space/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Si3</a> - a decentralized media-tech platform became the first official new grantees under the Push Grants V3 Program, which is community-run for the first time in history.</li>
<li>Our DAO Council member, SixtyKeys landed speaking slots at <a href="https://ethsafari.xyz/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ETH Safari</a> happening this year.</li>
<li>We onboarded 20 new members to <a href="https://gov.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push DAO</a>.</li>
<li>The Push Alpha Community on Push Chat grew its user base to 500+ participants becoming the largest conditionally gated community on Push DApp.</li>
<li>Push Protocol received a notable mention in <a href="https://www.cryptomarketmap.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Electric Capital’s Crypto Market Map</a>.</li>
<li>The third iteration of the Push India Ambassador’s program has been formally initiated.</li>
<li>We also had a booth set up at <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1811046959353880785" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ETH CC Brussels</a> at the Metamask Building Onchain event, featuring <a href="https://snaps.metamask.io/snap/npm/pushprotocol/snap/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push Metamask Snap</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates as we continue to push the boundaries of the Web3 ecosystem.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Protocol</category>
            <category>Web3</category>
            <category>Blockchain Technology</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Now anyone can write for Push]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/now-anyone-can-write-for-push-protocol</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/now-anyone-can-write-for-push-protocol</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Now anyone can write for Push]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Now anyone can write for Push" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-1610fcb762ae65c4cbe377b08bb20d4c.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>GM Push Fam,</p>
<p>As we go further down our collective path of decentralization, hand-in-hand with our community, we’re opening up more and more of the ecosystem to be directly led by everyone involved.</p>
<p>To reach our goal of providing the future of comms and beyond for all, in a truly trustless environment, we need to double-down on championing the opinions of all involved in our ecosystem.</p>
<p>We need to be not just collective tech for change, but a collective voice for change.</p>
<p>That’s why today, we’re taking the next step towards Push being a truly collectively run ecosystem.</p>
<p>We’re opening the doors of our blog to everyone in the greater Push ecosystem.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="who-qualifies"><strong>Who qualifies?</strong><a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/now-anyone-can-write-for-push-protocol#who-qualifies" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to who-qualifies" title="Direct link to who-qualifies">​</a></h3>
<p>Everyone.</p>
<p>Whether you represent a Push channel, a technical partner, a DAO contributor, a grantee, or something else entirely, this is your time.</p>
<p>Publish an opinion piece with us on one of the themes we’re looking for a the time, and reach our greater community of over 120,000 strong, while contributing to what the collective Push voice becomes.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-kinds-of-posts-are-we-looking-for">What kinds of posts are we looking for?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/now-anyone-can-write-for-push-protocol#what-kinds-of-posts-are-we-looking-for" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What kinds of posts are we looking for?" title="Direct link to What kinds of posts are we looking for?">​</a></h3>
<p>Currently, we’re accepting ideas related to consumer crypto and improving coordination as well as UX in our industry, with more calls for articles to be added over time to the Push DAO Forum!</p>
<p>Make sure <a href="https://gov.push.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">you’re signed up there</a> to view the full process and guidelines for guest posting, including where to submit your drafts, what format to submit them in, who to submit them to, and more!</p>
<p>Let’s inspire builders and widen the boundaries of innovation, together, both in-code, and in-text!</p>
<p>Our team’s already curating the first few pieces to be published. Let us review yours.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Protocol</category>
            <category>Web3</category>
            <category>Blockchain Technology</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Push Protocol x Wormhole AMA for the Cross Chain Request Feature in Push V3]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/ama-with-wormhole-for-cross-chain-requests-pre-pip</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/ama-with-wormhole-for-cross-chain-requests-pre-pip</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Push Protocol x Wormhole AMA for the Cross Chain Request Feature in Push V3]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Push Protocol x Wormhole AMA for the Cross Chain Request Feature in Push V3" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-87165fed06701e8b218562674f1dacdf.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Last week, we debuted Pre-PIP 3 (Push Improvement Proposal) for <a href="https://push.org/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cross Chain Requests</a> on the <a href="https://gov.push.org/t/pre-pip-3-cross-chain-request-feature-in-push-smart-contracts-v3/1794" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Push DAO forum</a> and invited the <a href="https://wormhole.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wormhole</a> team to chat about it, since their tech is a major part of this upgrade.</p>
<p>Here’s a 3-minute recap for those who couldn’t join in:</p>
<p>We kicked off the <a href="https://x.com/pushprotocol/status/1819017203284578483" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">spaces</a> with a bit of alpha on Push’s V3 Smart Contracts and what else is coming up from our side as the 2024 rolls on:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Launch of On-Chain Governance</strong>: The V3 contracts will introduce on-chain governance, allowing the community to govern smart contract execution.</li>
<li><strong>Optimized Contracts:</strong> Push’s V3 contracts will be more efficient. They’ll be capable of handling requests from any chain, which will then be relayed to the Ethereum-based Push core contracts for validations and state changes.</li>
<li><strong>Upgraded Incentivized Chats:</strong> Users will be able to initiate and receive paid chats from any chain to any chain, as long as both are supported by the framework.</li>
<li><strong>Cross-Chain Requests (CCR):</strong> This feature allows users to perform actions like creating channels or requests on any blockchain, rather than just on Ethereum. This move is essential for Push to reach a broader audience across different blockchains, including Layer 2 (L2), Layer 3 (L3), and app-specific chains, without increasing friction in the user’s experience with our tech.</li>
<li>A new hub for builders: All of this will enable a new hub for builders to experiment and widen the boundaries of innovation with web3-based consumer apps.</li>
</ol>
<p>We then moved on to Wormhole’s views on the significance of the integration of Push’s smart contracts with their tech:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-push-x-wormhole">Why Push x Wormhole?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/ama-with-wormhole-for-cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#why-push-x-wormhole" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why Push x Wormhole?" title="Direct link to Why Push x Wormhole?">​</a></h3>
<p>The integration centers on making the $PUSH token natively fungible across all of the connected chains that Push wants, while enabling native-messaging of all sorts on all involved. We came up with this new multi-chain framework, the Native Token Transfer framework, to enable seamless token transfers across different chains without the need for liquidity pools or complex bridging mechanisms. We both agree that the industry needs to involve into one that is truly interoperable. This is a major step in that direction.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-is-pre-pip-3ccr-important">Why is Pre-PIP 3/CCR important?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/ama-with-wormhole-for-cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#why-is-pre-pip-3ccr-important" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why is Pre-PIP 3/CCR important?" title="Direct link to Why is Pre-PIP 3/CCR important?">​</a></h3>
<p>The proposal includes detailed research and considerations, focusing on minimal changes to the existing architecture, a security-first approach, and how the technical aspects of Wormhole will enable CCR. This includes the deployment of manager and transceiver contracts on different chains and how these contracts interact with Push’s existing infrastructure.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-did-push-choose-wormhole-for-this-integration">Why did Push choose Wormhole for this integration?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/ama-with-wormhole-for-cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#why-did-push-choose-wormhole-for-this-integration" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why did Push choose Wormhole for this integration?" title="Direct link to Why did Push choose Wormhole for this integration?">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Native Token Transfer (NTT) Framework:</strong> This framework allows for seamless token transfers across different chains without the need for liquidity pools or complex bridging mechanisms.</li>
<li><strong>Security:</strong> Wormhole’s framework is battle-tested and includes additional security measures like rate limiting.</li>
<li><strong>Future-Proofing:</strong> The NTT framework allows Push to maintain governance control over its tokens across multiple chains, which is crucial for its ecosystem and the evolution of its DAO.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="overview-of-the-wormhole-transceiver-and-security-framework">Overview of the Wormhole Transceiver and Security Framework:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/ama-with-wormhole-for-cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#overview-of-the-wormhole-transceiver-and-security-framework" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Overview of the Wormhole Transceiver and Security Framework:" title="Direct link to Overview of the Wormhole Transceiver and Security Framework:">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Wormhole Transceiver:</strong> This utilizes the general message passing layer of Wormhole, which relies on a security model with 19 independent "guardians" who verify messages. At least 13 of the 19 guardians must agree to validate a message, making the system highly secure.</li>
<li><strong>Flexibility and Future-Proofing: Wormhole’s</strong> system allows for the adding of other transceivers or message verification protocols, such as off-chain processes or ZK transceivers for enhanced security.</li>
<li><strong>Overall Security and Reliability:</strong> Wormhole has processed over a billion messages while maintaining consistently high security and resilience across its network. The platform already provably supports the future of secure message and token transfers across chains.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="push-protocol-and-wormhole-integration">Push Protocol and Wormhole Integration:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/ama-with-wormhole-for-cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#push-protocol-and-wormhole-integration" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Push Protocol and Wormhole Integration:" title="Direct link to Push Protocol and Wormhole Integration:">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Security-First Approach:</strong> Push Protocol has always and continues to prioritize security, ensuring that the deployment of tokens and messages on multiple chains is always protected and that protection always increases.</li>
<li><strong>Cross-Chain Request (CCR):</strong> With CCR live, users will be able to execute actions (e.g., creating channels) across different chains without leaving their native chain or bridging tokens. The integration with Wormhole makes this process more seamless and efficient.</li>
<li><strong>User Experience:</strong> Post-CCR’s launch, actions like channel creation will become more straightforward, with users able to operate across chains without the hassle of managing tokens or gas fees on multiple networks to get to their intended destination.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-greater-implications-of-ccr-for-developers-and-builders">The Greater Implications of CCR for Developers and Builders:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/ama-with-wormhole-for-cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#the-greater-implications-of-ccr-for-developers-and-builders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Greater Implications of CCR for Developers and Builders:" title="Direct link to The Greater Implications of CCR for Developers and Builders:">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Unified API and Multi-Chain Notifications:</strong> Developers can build once and notify everywhere, simplifying cross-chain interactions and enhancing user engagement. This reduces development complexity and improves resource management.</li>
<li><strong>Enhanced Functionality and Interoperability:</strong> The integration allows for smart contracts on one chain to trigger notifications on another, improving the overall functionality of decentralized applications (dApps).</li>
<li><strong>Security Enhancements:</strong> Wormhole’s security features, like rate-limiting, access control, and defense mechanisms, ensure that cross-chain communications remain verifiably secure.</li>
</ol>
<p>The integration of Push Protocol's Cross-Chain Requests (CCR) with Wormhole represents a pivotal advancement in decentralized technology. This advancement strengthens Push’s security, raises its scalability, and broadens its reach across multiple blockchains, paving the way for a more connected and user-friendly Web3 experience for all. As Push continues to innovate, its partnership with Wormhole ensures that it remains on the forefront.</p>
<p>To any of you who are looking to build the future of consumer applications, reach out to our team across our networks, and we’ll help you get started as CCR takes off!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Protocol</category>
            <category>Web3</category>
            <category>Blockchain Technology</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing Pre-PIP 3 (Push Improvement Proposal) for Cross-Chain Requests:]]></title>
            <link>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip</link>
            <guid>https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Introducing Pre-PIP 3 (Push Improvement Proposal) for Cross-Chain Requests:]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Introducing Pre-PIP 3 (Push Improvement Proposal) for Cross-Chain Requests" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/cover-image-57bca9ea6556a16c996e32f0d3721977.webp" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Push Protocol, the leading web3 communication layer, has proposed a major upgrade with the introduction of <a href="https://gov.push.org/t/pre-pip-3-cross-chain-request-feature-in-push-smart-contracts-v3/1794" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pre-PIP (Push Improvement Proposal) for Cross-Chain Requests (CCR)</a>. This proposal aims to enable users to interact with Push Protocol smart contracts on the Ethereum blockchain from any blockchain network, whether it’s EVM-based or non-EVM. Once CCR is implemented, users will be able to stay on their preferred blockchain while accessing Push Protocol's services, offering enhanced convenience and flexibility.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="what-is-ccr-cross-chain-requests-and-its-impact">What is CCR (Cross-Chain Requests) and its impact?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#what-is-ccr-cross-chain-requests-and-its-impact" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is CCR (Cross-Chain Requests) and its impact?" title="Direct link to What is CCR (Cross-Chain Requests) and its impact?">​</a></h3>
<p>In the current Push Protocol architecture, performing any important task related to channels like creating a channel, modification of a channel, changing a channel’s state, etc, requires the user/protocol to interact with the Push Smart Contract which is only deployed on Ethereum Blockchain.</p>
<p>This led to a bad user experience for the user/protocol as they need to switch to the Ethereum network for any interaction they might want to do with the Push Core contract. This is currently a friction point for users who primarily operate on other EVM-compatible chains and even non-EVM users.</p>
<p>Cross-chain requests will eliminate the need to switch to the Ethereum Network making it possible to create a channel, use Push services, or interact with Push Protocol’s Ethereum smart contract from any blockchain they like, whether it’s another EVM chain or non-EVM chain.</p>
<p>Additionally, this was not just something that users faced but more for Push Protocol as it limits Push Protocol's ability to tap into other chains and help solve the communication/notification issues of those chains adequately. This constraint hinders the protocol from reaching a broader audience and solving communication issues across diverse blockchain environments.</p>
<p>Therefore, by enabling the Cross-Chain Request feature, Push Protocol can primarily significantly enhance the UX for average users as well as channel creators/managers from not just Ethereum but multiple other EVM/Non-EVM chains as well. It also allows the protocol to expand its market reach, attract users from different chains, and foster a more interconnected blockchain ecosystem.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="importance-of-ccr-cross-chain-requests">Importance of CCR (Cross-Chain Requests):<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#importance-of-ccr-cross-chain-requests" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Importance of CCR (Cross-Chain Requests):" title="Direct link to Importance of CCR (Cross-Chain Requests):">​</a></h3>
<p>The Cross Chain Requests (CCR) feature is crucial for the future success and growth of the Push Protocol:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Enhanced User Experience:</strong> The CCR feature will significantly enhance user experience by eliminating the need for users to switch networks or manually bridge tokens to interact with the Push Core contract on Ethereum. This streamlined process will allow users to perform key actions like channel creation and incentivize chat requests directly from their preferred blockchain, reducing both complexity and transaction costs. By making these features accessible from various chains, CCR removes barriers for new and existing users, fostering a more inclusive and user-friendly environment.</li>
<li><strong>Broader Reach:</strong> The CCR feature will expand the reach of Push Protocol across the blockchain ecosystem. By enabling interactions from multiple EVM and non-EVM chains, CCR will not only broaden the protocol's user base but also tap into diverse blockchain communities that might benefit from Push’s communication and notification features. This increased accessibility helps Push Protocol grow its market presence and integrate with a wider range of blockchain projects, ultimately supporting the development of a more interconnected and collaborative blockchain network.</li>
<li><strong>Revolutionizing Web3 Communications</strong>: CCR future-proofs Push Protocol against the rapid evolution of the blockchain space. As new chains and technologies emerge, CCR’s cross-chain capabilities ensure that Push Protocol remains adaptable and relevant. By leveraging established technologies like Wormhole’s NTT framework and Relayers, CCR positions Push Protocol to embrace future advancements and continue delivering value to its users across an ever-expanding blockchain landscape.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Here’s a simple overview of how CCR works:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Initiate Request</strong>: A user on another blockchain (like Polygon) wants to perform an action, such as creating a new channel for sending notifications.</li>
<li><strong>Submit Details</strong>: The user uses a special function on the Push Communicator contract on their preferred blockchain to submit the request, providing the necessary details and approving the $PUSH tokens for the action.</li>
<li><strong>Send Data and Tokens</strong>: The Push Communicator contract validates the input, creates a message payload, and uses Wormhole Relayers to securely send this payload and the $PUSH tokens to the Push Core contract on Ethereum.</li>
<li><strong>Process Request</strong>: On Ethereum, the Push Core contract receives the message and tokens, decodes the request, validates it, and performs the required action.</li>
<li><strong>Completion</strong>: The request is completed on Ethereum, and any unused native tokens are refunded to the user on their original blockchain.</li>
</ol>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Cover Image of Diagram for Cross-Chain Requests" src="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/assets/images/image1-2f89fa71911892f627b09ac1af285b45.webp" width="1600" height="901" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="visualizing-channel-creation-with-the-ccr-feature">Visualizing Channel Creation with the CCR feature<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#visualizing-channel-creation-with-the-ccr-feature" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Visualizing Channel Creation with the CCR feature" title="Direct link to Visualizing Channel Creation with the CCR feature">​</a></h3>
<p>Imagine Bob, a Polygon user, wants to create a channel for sending notifications.</p>
<p>Previously, he'd need to switch to Ethereum, bridge tokens, and change networks. With CCR, Bob simply uses the familiar Push Communicator contract on Polygon.</p>
<p>The contract acts as a bridge, relaying Bob's request (channel details) and the required PUSH tokens (bridged via Wormhole) to the Push Core contract on Ethereum.</p>
<p>All behind the scenes, without Bob ever leaving Polygon! This creates a seamless experience for users on any chain, opening Push Protocol to a wider audience.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="why-not-just-deploy-push-core-everywhere">Why Not Just Deploy Push Core Everywhere?<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#why-not-just-deploy-push-core-everywhere" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why Not Just Deploy Push Core Everywhere?" title="Direct link to Why Not Just Deploy Push Core Everywhere?">​</a></h3>
<p>While putting Push Core on every blockchain might seem easy, it's quite tricky.</p>
<p>It would be hard to manage separate fees and keep all the information on different chains in sync, which could even be risky.</p>
<p>That's why we're improving the existing Push Communicator contracts to handle these requests. We'll also use a reliable system called Wormhole to securely send information and tokens between blockchains. This way, everything works smoothly without needing Push Core on every chain. For more details check out <a href="https://gov.push.org/t/pre-pip-3-cross-chain-request-feature-in-push-smart-contracts-v3/1794" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="implementation-how-we-will-build-ccr">Implementation: How we will build CCR:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#implementation-how-we-will-build-ccr" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Implementation: How we will build CCR:" title="Direct link to Implementation: How we will build CCR:">​</a></h3>
<p>To implement Cross-Chain Requests (CCR), we will:</p>
<ol>
<li>Enable $Push Token for multi-chain support.</li>
<li>Build cross-chain support in the Push Communicator and Push Core Contract.</li>
<li>Use Wormhole’s Relayer Interface and NTT framework for token transfers across chains.</li>
<li>Equip the Push Communicator to handle cross-chain actions like channel creation and requests.</li>
<li>Modify the Push Core Contract to process cross-chain payloads.</li>
<li>Conduct security audits and deploy the updated contracts on the testnet and mainnet.</li>
</ol>
<p>For more details on the implementation of CCR check out <a href="https://gov.push.org/t/pre-pip-3-cross-chain-request-feature-in-push-smart-contracts-v3/1794" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="the-future-of-push-protocol">The Future of Push Protocol:<a href="https://push-protocol.github.io/push-website/pr-preview/pr-885/blog/cross-chain-requests-pre-pip#the-future-of-push-protocol" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Future of Push Protocol:" title="Direct link to The Future of Push Protocol:">​</a></h3>
<p>CCR feature is a significant step forward for Push Protocol. It paves the way for a more interconnected and user-friendly communication layer within the ever-expanding blockchain landscape.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further updates as we implement CCR and empower users to unlock the full potential of Web3 communication!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Push Protocol</category>
            <category>Web3</category>
            <category>Blockchain Technology</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>